<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The signs of the times, or, VVonderful signs of wonderful times being a faithful collection and impartial relation of several signs and wonders, call'd properly prodigies, (together with some philosophical and theological descants upon them) which have been seen in the heavens, on the earth, and on the waters, as they have been testifyed by very credible hands, all of which have hapned within the compass of this last year 1680 : which may well be called another annus mirabilis, or wonderful year, wherein the Lord hath given us loud warnings to repent of our sins and return to him, that he may have mercy upon us / by C. N.</title>
            <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 230 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12624088</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12624088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64617</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52817)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64617)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1532:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The signs of the times, or, VVonderful signs of wonderful times being a faithful collection and impartial relation of several signs and wonders, call'd properly prodigies, (together with some philosophical and theological descants upon them) which have been seen in the heavens, on the earth, and on the waters, as they have been testifyed by very credible hands, all of which have hapned within the compass of this last year 1680 : which may well be called another annus mirabilis, or wonderful year, wherein the Lord hath given us loud warnings to repent of our sins and return to him, that he may have mercy upon us / by C. N.</title>
                  <author>Ness, Christopher, 1621-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and published by Langley Curtiss ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title:  Wonderful signs of wonderful times.</note>
                  <note>Woodcut engravings of the "wonderful signs": verso t.p.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 84.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies.</term>
               <term>Apocalyptic literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The SIGNS of the TIMES: OR, VVonderful Signs OF Wonderful times.</p>
            <p>BEING A Faithful Collection and Impartial Relation of ſeveral SIGNS and WONDERS, call'd properly PRODIGIES, (together with ſome <hi>Philoſophical</hi> and <hi>Theological</hi> Deſcants upon them) which have been ſeen in the <hi>HEAVENS,</hi> on the <hi>EARTH,</hi> and on the <hi>WATERS,</hi> as they have been Teſtifyed by very Credible Hands. All which have hapned within the compaſs of this laſt Year 1680.</p>
            <p>Which may well be called another <hi>Annus Mirabilis,</hi> or <hi>Wonderful Year,</hi> wherein the Lord hath given us loud Warnings to Repent of our Sins and Return to him, that he may have Mercy upon us.</p>
            <q>Woe to thm that Regard not the Work of the Lord, neither Conſider the Operation of his Hands. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 5.11.12, 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>By <hi>C. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed for the</hi> Author. And Publiſhed by <hi>Langley Gurtiſs,</hi> on <hi>Ludgate-Hill.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Comet and the Dart</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of comet and dart</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Armies in the Air:</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of armies</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Three Suns ſeen:</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of three suns</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The greathailſtones</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of hail</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>Hatfield maid &amp; Ghost</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of maid and ghost</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Earthquake.</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of earthquake</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The <hi>3</hi> dead Tower-lyons:</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of three dead lions</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>the River dryd: the whale</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of whale</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <figure>
                  <head>The fight of Ships.</head>
                  <figDesc>depiction of ships</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> The Worſhipful <hi>Francis Warner,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <p>AMongſt all my ſmall Acquaintance, I have not had the Happineſs to know perſonally any perſon of Quality (though undoubtedly, ſome ſuch there be out of my reach) ſo much converſant and ſo exquiſitely <hi>vers'd</hi> in <hi>prophetick</hi> Myſteries like your ſelf, and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering That <hi>Prodigies</hi> (which this portable pocket-book treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth upon) are a kind of mute (yet ſpeaking) <hi>Prophecies,</hi> I made bold to <hi>Dedicate</hi> it <hi>(quale quale eſt)</hi> to your Worſhip, being experimentally Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, That you are a lover of Learning, and a candid Patron to all Abſtruſe Eſſays, well knowing that in <hi>magnis voluiſſe ſat est, &amp; Difficilium, facilis est venia.</hi> Sir, your Candour, I preſume, will incline you to pardon me in the whole, in as much as I have been conſtrained throughout this whole Work to tread all in untrodden paths, finding none walking in the ſame way and Method before me: You will find the Labour (ſuch as it is) the more elaborate, in finding out <hi>Sacred</hi> (which are leaſt obvious to Exceptions) as well as <hi>Civil Parallels</hi> to <hi>preſent Prodigies;</hi> and in making ſuch (I hope) Innocent Deſcants upon them, as the Matter doth require<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sir, I look upon you as one above many for Diſcourſing about the <hi>Signs of the times:</hi> both the Signs of <hi>Divine Anger</hi> and of <hi>Divine Favour. Signum &amp; Signatum ſunt correlata.</hi> Every <hi>Sign</hi> muſt have the <hi>thing ſignified,</hi> no <hi>Sign</hi> is ſo <hi>dumb,</hi> but it ſpeaks ſomething which only the <hi>wiſe do underſtand,</hi> Hoſ. 14.9. 'Twas <hi>Daniel</hi> only and not the <hi>South-ſayers,</hi> That could Read the <hi>Handwriting</hi> upon the Wall, and give a Right Interpretation of it. <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.8, 11.12, 15, 16. Such as ſeek to Sorcerers, deſerve no better than a Diſappointment, the loweſt fruit of their ſublime Folly, None of thoſe Wizards of the world (though they might have Deep Reaches in <hi>Humane Affaires</hi>) could give the Senſe of that <hi>Divine Oracle,</hi> that work was reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for a better man than they: <hi>Stultorum plena ſunt omnia;</hi> Store of ſuch <hi>Fools</hi> (no better than <hi>Duſt heaps</hi>) are found in every Corner, who either <hi>know not</hi> the mind of God in myſtical matters, or <hi>Stumble at it.</hi> There be too many <hi>Atheists,</hi> who do extenuate and undervalue all <hi>Prodigies.</hi> Heatheniſhly aſcribing them to <hi>Dame Nature</hi> only, whereby they do dangerouſly Darken the Power and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the <hi>Almighty</hi> God. but there <hi>are not many wiſe, wiſe-hearted,</hi> and <hi>wiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Salvation.</hi> They are few that Underſtand the <hi>Signs of the Times.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Objected, Prodigies</hi> are <hi>common</hi> Things, therefore cannot be <hi>ſpecial</hi> Preſages of future E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, or of the End approaching. I Anſ. (1) 'Tis very obſervable that the Palmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni Hamadabbat or <hi>Prince of Preachers</hi> preached upon <hi>Prodigies</hi> thoſe ſigns and wonders which did preſage the Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and of his laſt Comming, occaſioned by his Diſciples asking [<hi>When ſhall theſe things be,</hi> and <hi>What ſign will there be when theſe things ſhall come to paſs,</hi> Luke 21.7. Mat. 24.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> Mar. 13 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> No ſooner had Chriſt prepared them with due Cautions concerning themſelves, but he declared what was ſatisfactory to their curious queſtion. (2.) The very firſt Text that <hi>Christs Apoſtles</hi> preach'd upon (after <hi>Christ</hi> was <hi>gone</hi> from them, and the <hi>Spirit come</hi> upon them) was concerning <hi>Prodigies</hi> which the Prophet <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi> foretold God would ſhew in the world, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 30, <hi>&amp;c</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> handled that Text ſo powerfully as to prevail with 3000 Converts at one Sermon, Acts 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 17.19.41. Shewing how <hi>New Testament times</hi> do <hi>unvail</hi> and Accompliſh the <hi>vail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> Prophecies of the <hi>Old.</hi> (3) 'Tis the concurrent Opinion of our beſt Proteſtant Authors, that there be ſome Special <hi>Signs of the Times</hi> (call'd <hi>Sacramentis &amp; M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculis cognata,</hi> near a Kin to Sacraments and Miracles) which are more than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, even of a Divine Ordination, declaring how the <hi>Great God</hi> ſtands affected towards <hi>poor man,</hi> in reſpect of his <hi>Favour</hi> or <hi>Anger:</hi> See <hi>Polani Syntagma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 48, <hi>&amp;</hi> 59 &amp; many Claſſick Authentick Divines. (4) 'Tis likewiſe as concur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> a Sentiment of <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Hiſt ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (both Ancient <hi>and</hi> Modern) that <hi>Prodigies</hi> do moſtly
<pb facs="tcp:64617:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Portend the Futurition of ſome extraordinary Events, as, <hi>Herodotus,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Lucan. l.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. telleth, how the ſad calamities of <hi>Rome</hi> were preſaged by many ſtrange <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies</hi> in <hi>Heaven, Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea,</hi> ſinging or ſaying, Thus
<q>
                  <l>— Superique Minaces</l>
                  <l>Prodigiis terras imple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>runt Aethera pontum</l>
                  <l>Igneta obſcurae vidèrunt Sydera Noctes,</l>
                  <l>Ardentémque polum flammis, coelóque Volantes,</l>
                  <l>Obliquas per Inane Faces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>All which do ſignify, that the whole Fabrick of the Univerſe had put upon it (by the <hi>Angry God</hi>) a moſt frightful Face and Aſpect, and <hi>Heaven, Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea</hi> did conſpire together to chaſtize the Pride and Luxury of <hi>Rome</hi> at that Time, and <hi>Claudian</hi> ſaith, That after <hi>Caeſars</hi> Victory over <hi>Pompey,</hi> not only the Heavens drop'd <hi>blood,</hi> but alſo pits and pools flowed with <hi>blood,</hi> as a praeſage of <hi>Caeſars Stabbing,</hi> cum multis aliis, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (5.) Pliny, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 58. ſaith, The <hi>Heathens</hi> were ſtartled at the <hi>Prodigys</hi> of his time, in ſo much that they had their ſolemn Sacrifices for Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Evils portended by them; And will not thoſe Dictates of the <hi>dim light</hi> of <hi>Dame Nature</hi> in theſe blind <hi>Heathens</hi> riſe up in Judgment againſt our <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> who ſcoff at all thoſe <hi>wonderful ſigns</hi> ſo <hi>terrifying</hi> in themſelves, and ſo teſtifying God's wrath for Man's ſin? Alas, <hi>they</hi> had not God's Heifer to plow withall (which we have) yet could they Unriddle thoſe Myſteries (call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, God's prodigious preachments) better than many of us: their very natural Religion was a dark Imitation of the true Divine Devotion, though the Devil (God's Ape) did impoſe upon them therein much Superſtition. If againſt this, it be alledged what is ſaid, <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.2, 3. <hi>Learn not the way of the Heathen, and be not Diſmayed at the Signs of Heaven, as they are, for their Cuſtoms are vain.</hi> I Anſwer (1.) God Cautions his people <hi>there,</hi> (going Captives into <hi>Chaldea then</hi>) that they learn not the vain Aſtrology and Idolatry of the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deans</hi> in their Country. (2.) That Aſtrology which pretendeth to read Fates and Fortunes in the Heavens, aſcribing all to Stars and not to God, is <hi>Idolatry,</hi> condemn'd <hi>there</hi> by <hi>Jeremy</hi> and by <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ch 47: 12, 13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (3) <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſpeaks of Natural and ordinary <hi>Signs</hi> of Heaven which the blind Heathens were diſmay'd at (<hi>Deſying</hi> God while they <hi>Deified</hi> them) as if the Iſſues of their Affairs depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on them: VVherefore Gods people <hi>ſhould not be ſo:</hi> If there were no other Reaſon but that only, Matth: 6.32. but there be other Extraordinary Signs, dreadful Apparitions, whereby God warns his people of ſome enſuing Wrath, as appeareth from <hi>Joel, Christ</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c. (as above) God doth not forbid us to mind them and to be affected with them. Eſpecially conſidering this is Gods laſt way of ſpeaking to us, as it was to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> when God had ſaid <hi>ſoſtly</hi> to him at firſt, <hi>Let my People go, &amp;c.</hi> he hardned his heart, then God ſpake more <hi>ſeverely</hi> to him by <hi>Signs and wonders:</hi> So now, our <hi>Barnabas</hi>'s hath been rejected, God ſends his <hi>Boanerges</hi>'s and preacheth to us by <hi>Prodigies,</hi> and ſuch as are more than Ordinary without a Parallell for this Soo year, and ſo attended with ſuch concuſſions of Kingdoms (e'n Popiſh one againſt another, <hi>&amp;c</hi>) which ſeem to put an Accent on them and though there have been frequent <hi>Prodigies,</hi> yet may they be Signs of the laſt times, as a Diſeaſe is a ſign of Mortality, though a Man recover ſometimes, yet ceaſeth he not to be mortal but dyeth at laſt; So thoſe ſigns (though oft ſeen) do not ceaſe to be <hi>Signs</hi> of the Approaching End: and former <hi>Prodigies,</hi> might have other Praeſages and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, as thoſe in 60, &amp;c: what hath befaln ever ſince, ſuch as, <hi>Plague, Fire,</hi> &amp;c. I ſpeak to a wiſe man (skilful in Myſteries) who will judg candidly what is ſayd by,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my Study this</hi> 
                  <date>10 <hi>of</hi> May, 1681.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yours in the beſt Bonds, Christo. Neſs.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The</hi> Signs of the Times: OR, Wonderful Signs OF Wonderful Times.</head>
            <p>OUR Lord and Saviour hath ſaid, <hi>Except men ſee SIGNS and WONDERS, they will not Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, John</hi> 4.48. There is a natural Itch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in the nature of all Mankind to ſee ſome <hi>ſigns</hi> and <hi>Wonders;</hi> Hence it is, That ſuch an univerſal Aptneſs is found in all the Sons and Daughters of Men to behold Rare Shows and ſtrange Sights, Thus the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Ran forth out of all the Region round about</hi> to get a Sight of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>as of a burning and ſhining Light: Matth.</hi> 3.5. &amp; 11.7. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.7. &amp; <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.35. Seeing they had not any one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet born to them from the Building of the Second Temple un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til His Birth: Then was <hi>[Cathimath Chazon]</hi> a Sealing up of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4.9. No Prophet 'twixt <hi>Malachy</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.5. <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.14. with 17.10. Hence that <hi>Captivity</hi> Pſalm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. complains, verſe 9. that there was no Prophet amongſt them. Hence it is alſo, that we read ſo oft in Scripture of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men <hi>(Good as well as Bad)</hi> asking after a Sight of Signs:</p>
            <p>Indeed (1) <hi>It is an evil and Adulterous Generation</hi> (according to Chriſt's Character) that moſt <hi>ſeeketh after ſigns, Matt.</hi> 12 28, 39. that is, ſo earneſtly, if that were not Done, they were Undone:
<list>
                  <item>(I.) Thoſe carnal Scribes and Phariſees could call for a Sign after ſo many Signs. They had been perſonal Ey-witneſſes How Mighty Chriſt was both in <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Deed</hi> (in Doctrine and Miracles) <hi>before God and all the People,</hi> Luke 24.19. which were
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:64617:4"/>ſo many <hi>Infallible Proofs,</hi> Act. 1.3. that he was the Meſſiah: yet theſe were but SIGNS <hi>on Earth,</hi> they would not believe in him, unleſs he could ſhew them a SIGN from Heaven, and Doe as <hi>Moſes, Samuel</hi> and <hi>Elijah</hi> had done: for <hi>Moſes</hi> call'd for Manna, <hi>Samuel</hi> for Rain, and <hi>Elijah</hi> for Fire, All from Heav'n, <hi>&amp;c. John</hi> 2.18. &amp; 6.30. Chriſt ſhew'd them many <hi>Signs,</hi> Jo. 20.30. and wrought many <hi>Wonders</hi> (which no power but that which is <hi>Divine</hi> could work, <hi>John</hi> 9.32.3.) both beyond the Courſe of Nature, and above the Power of Art, yet (as the Saying is) they could not ſee VVood for Trees. No, they muſt have ſuch Signs as were ſhown and ſeen upon Mount <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nai, Exod.</hi> 19.16, 19. Such <hi>Thunders</hi> and <hi>Lightnings</hi> though they had their <hi>Bath-Kol,</hi> the Daughter of a Voice (which was, as they ſay, the only Oracle abiding with the Second Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple) and ſuch a <hi>Voice of God</hi> (as Thunder is called, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 29.3, to 10) they had from Heaven, <hi>John</hi> 12.29, 30. Therefore Chriſt checks and chides them for requiring ſuch Signs as would rather affright theſe Hypocrites than <hi>inſtruct</hi> them. They ſhould have been contented with his Doctrine and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles which did ſufficiently demonſtate a Divine Power, and though the Thunder-Claps at the Giving of the Law upon Mount <hi>Sinai</hi> were moſt ſuitable to the Rigour of that Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, yet his <hi>Miracles of Mercy</hi> (confirming his Doctrine) were more ſuitable to SION, and to the Grace of the Goſpel. Therefore <hi>went Chriſt about Doing Good</hi> to many by his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>Act.</hi> 10.38. but never (which is very remarkable) Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hurt to Any by them, As moſt other Wonder-Workers Did, for his Name was JESUS a Saviour, not <hi>Abaddon</hi>) [A bad one] or <hi>Apollyon,</hi> a Deſtroyer. In all this thoſe wicked Hypocrites were wittingly, willingly and wilfully blind, and who ſo blind as they that will not ſee.</item>
                  <item>(II.) Another Time Came the Superſtitious <hi>Phariſees</hi> (leaving behind them the Supercilious <hi>Scribes</hi>) and conſpir'd with the Irreligious <hi>Sadduces</hi> to tempt Chriſt by <hi>asking a SIGN,</hi> Matt. 16.1, &amp;c. Thoſe two Sects were deadly Enemies each to the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64617:4"/>other, yet can they here combine as loving Friends for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting of CHRIST. The two <hi>Good Sticks</hi> (Iſrael and Juda) became one in the hand of God, Ezeck. 37 19. but thoſe two <hi>Bad Sticks</hi> (the <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Sadduces</hi>) became one in the hand of the Devil, not onely as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> did, Luk. 23.12. but alſo as the Popiſh Prieſts and Jeſuites, the Monks and Fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars (All which be at deadly Difference amongſt themſelves in as much as they do notoriouſly diſparage and beſpatter one another) yet as <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> could joyn hands againſt CHRIST, ſo thoſe Miſcreants can all conſpire againſt <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> Thus Dogs though they be fighting never ſo fiercely and tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, yet if an Hare run by, they can give over, and all run after her, Accordingly thoſe two ſorts, though of Heterogeneous Principles, could be enough Homogeneous to Aſſault Chriſt with their cavelling Interrogatories, wherein their putid Hypocriſy (courting him at the firſt, and calling him <hi>Maſter,</hi> whom before they had branded with that black name of <hi>Belzebub</hi>) appeared, deſiring him <hi>to ſhew them a SIGN. Them</hi> by all means, as more worſhipful men than the Multitude, e'n ſuch as might well ſeem to merit ſuch a ſignal and ſingular Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. They muſt by all means be the only Men to whom the Meſſiah muſt <hi>ſhew a Sign from Heaven,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Joſuah</hi> ſhewed in commanding the Sun to ſtand ſtill; ſuch as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſhew'd in cauſing the Sun to run Retrogade ten Degrees, or ſuch as <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhewed in calling for Thunder and Rain in Harveſt, &amp;c. or rather ſuchas <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhew'd in Commanding the Corn of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to come down for daily bread to Iſrael, John 6.31.32. and if the Meſſiah would do ſo much for them, none, they <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended,</hi> ſhould be more willing to own him: yet, all this while, they <hi>intended</hi> Malice and Miſchief againſt him, contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his Miracles on Earth as if done by Magick Art, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>III. <hi>Herod</hi> alſo was of no better Bran than thoſe, who <hi>Deſired to ſee Jeſus for a long time, that he might ſhew him ſome ſign,</hi> Luke 23.8. Such as would recreate his Eyes and his Mind in behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for he look'd upon our Lord as no better than a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64617:5"/>Juggler, that would undoubtedly (to ingratiate himſelf with the King) ſhew to him the very beſt Trick in his Budget. Thus that Fox would gladly have been gratified, but he was notoriouſly deceived, inaſmuch as Chriſt was not ſo profuſe of his Divine power as to put it forth at the pleaſure of bad men, mearly to ſatisfie their vain Curioſity.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But (II.) we do not only find (upon Scripture Record) wicked men Deſirous to ſee Signs, but even Godly men alſo, as (1.) <hi>Moſes,</hi> Exod. 4.1. who had Experience of his Brethrens reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting him, and thruſting him from them, Exod. 2.14. Act. 7.27. and ſo they might Do again, If he had not ſomething to ſhew what might well warrant his Extraordinary Call: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, he ſaith, <hi>They will not believe me,</hi> &amp;c. that is, I dare not Venture upon a bare Divine Call and Commiſſion, unleſs ſome Divine ſigns be ſhew'd me for my farther Confirmation: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon God condeſcends to gratify him with the Two firſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Signs; Thus, in the firſt Sign 'tis obſervable, That the turning of <hi>Moſes</hi> Rod into a Serpent, was a manifeſt Diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of any Power borrowed from the Devil, in all thoſe won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which he was to work with that Rod, for that Sign did demonſtrate <hi>Moſes</hi> power over the Devil or <hi>Serpent,</hi> (his expreſs Type) and exercis'd againſt him. in handling him (though not without ſome Fear at firſt) through a ſtrengthned Faith at his Pleaſure: <hi>Moſes,</hi> indeed, took this Serpent or Crocodile by the Tail only, 'Twas the Work of the MESSIAH to break the Serpents Head: In this firſt Miraculous ſign, the ROD ſhew'd the flouriſhing State of Iſrael while <hi>Joſeph</hi> was Lord of the Land of Aegypt, and ſo held the Rod or Scepter for their Comfort, but its Turning into a Serpent (or Dragon) did plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly portend the Afflicted Eſtate of that Church, when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that <hi>Dragon,</hi> Ezek. 29.3.) with the Subtlety of the Old Serpent moſt grievouſly oppreſſed Iſrael; and yet this Serpent muſt be turn'd back again into a <hi>Rod,</hi> to ſignify that the afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Eſtate of the Church ſhould be turn'd into a flouriſhing E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate again by the Miniſtry of <hi>Moſes</hi> (more glorious than that of
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64617:5"/>
               <hi>Joſeph</hi>) who was called <hi>King</hi> in Jeſurum, Deut. 33.5. (a Title above that of <hi>Joſeph</hi>) and who was commanded to <hi>take the Serpent by the Tail,</hi> Exod. 4.4. which was dreadful to be done, becauſe of the Innate Antipathy and probable Danger of the Sting, yet <hi>Faith</hi> fortifies <hi>Moſes's</hi> Heart againſt his <hi>Fear</hi> of this formidable Creature, and carries him through the Difficulty of this Duty; he doth as God bids him, and had no Dammage thereby, but the Serpent was turnd into a Rod again:</p>
            <p>Moreover (2.) for Humbling <hi>Moſes</hi> and helping him to know That this miraculous Sign was not wrought by the Power of his own hand, therefore was his hand made a Leprous one, to ſhew, That ſuch great Wonders could not be wrought by ſo unclean a Hand, without the Help of a better and greater Hand than his own: and yet the Accompliſhment of this Second Sign was a farther Confirmation of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Faith, that Leprous hand of his <hi>(as white as Snow)</hi> muſt be return'd to its Natural ruddy Complexion again, <hi>Moſes</hi> found the Leproſy in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and there alſo he immediately left it: This was to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy to him, That the ſore Eſtate of the Church ſhould preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be cured, the Time of Her Healing now was at Hand, tho ſhe <hi>had lain long among the Pots</hi> (and ſo were not only as poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpis'd Lepers covered over with a white Leproſy, but all blak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and beſmutch'd in the Boſom of Aegypt their Houſe of Bondage) yet God would reſtore her again to a Sound Eſtate and <hi>give her Wings of Silver,</hi> and <hi>Feathers</hi> of <hi>Yellow Gold,</hi> Pſal. 68.13. Thus the moſt high God doth vouchſafe to ſtoop ſo low to the meanneſs of Man, as to give <hi>Moſes</hi> ſign upon ſign, as he had done before to him, Exo 3.3.12. Giving him then a Double Confirmation (1.) That of the <hi>Burning Buſh,</hi> for the preſent: (2.) That of <hi>Serving God at Horeb</hi> for the future. The like Favour the Lord likewiſe vouchſafeth to us by giving us a frequent Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, whereby he doth Seal and Seal again the Confirmation of our Faith in the <hi>exceeding great and precious Promiſes of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. God ſaid to Moſes, Such as will <hi>not Hear the voice of the firſt Sign,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64617:6"/>they will believe the Voice of the latter ſign,</hi> Exod. 4.8. <hi>Lekol Haoth,</hi> the voice of the Sign, plainly importeth That every of God's Signs hath a Voice, and therefore the Pſalmiſt faith, That they have not only a Voice, but Words alſo. <hi>[Dibre oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>othau]</hi> he ſhew'd the Words of his Signs, So 'tis in the Hebr. Pſal. 105.27. They ſpeak not to our Eyes only, but to our Ears alſo. Thus doth Sacramental Signs, They have a Voice, as <hi>Abel</hi>'s Blood is ſaid to have, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.4. <hi>which yet ſpeaketh,</hi> How much more the Blood of Chriſt, <hi>which ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth better things than the Blood of Abel,</hi> Hebr. 12.24. The ſign hath a Voice in it (as Exod. 4.10. Ezek. 1.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> Job. 4.16. God Annexing his Word with his Sign that it may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heard and underſtood) becauſe it (as it were) ſpeaketh that to the Eye, which words do to the Eear; and on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that which is plainly declared to the Ear, is ſometimes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented as if it were acted, and exhibited to the Eye, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.1. Thus the Adminiſtratiom of the Lords Supper is a lively Reſemblance of Chriſt crucified upon the Croſs; and thus the ſtung Iſraelites were heald by looking upon the Brazen Serpent advanced upon the Pole, Num. 21.8. 'Twas but <hi>Look and live</hi> then, and, tis but <hi>Look and live</hi> now, John 3.16. As they that look'd upon their Sores, and not upon the Sign, Dyed for it, So, they that fix their Eyes upon their Sins, and not upon their Saviour, do Deſpair, and Dye: and, as they that look'd upon the Sign though but with one Eye, though but with a ſquint Eye, or but with half an Eye, they were preſently hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, So, thoſe that look up to Chriſt, though <hi>Weak in Faith,</hi> yet <hi>Faithful</hi> in <hi>Weakneſs,</hi> are ſure to be ſaved, Iſa. 45.22. <hi>Look unto me All the Ends of the Earth, and be Saved,</hi> as the Moon when ſhe looks moſt fully in a direct line upon the Sun, then is ſhe in the Full, and moſt fully inlightned: This is the great Duty Required, <hi>to look vpon a Crucified Saviour,</hi> Zech. 12.10. and Salvation (in the Extent of it) is in the former Scripture propounded as the Grand Wages of that work and Duty and that Univerſally to all Right <hi>Lookers</hi> both Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:64617:6"/>The <hi>ſecond</hi> Inſtance of a godly man (deſirous to ſee <hi>Signs</hi>) is <hi>Gideon,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> was the <hi>firſt,</hi> both of them reckoned among Gods Renowned Worthies. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.20.32. This <hi>Gideon</hi> though but <hi>weak</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> yet was faithful in weakneſs, and therefore is he dignified with a Room in that Court-Roll, of the moſt radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Starrs in Scripture Horizon, yet his Faith though true, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing weak, required ſome Supporters, hence he ſaith [<hi>then ſhew me a Sign</hi> [Judg. 6.17. This Sign <hi>Gideon</hi> ſought not, as that Adulterous and Evil Generation (the Phariſes, &amp;c.) did, out of Curioſity and Incredulity, but (as <hi>Moſes</hi> before him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) for far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Confirmation of his Faith, concerning his call to ſo great a Work, whereby he might be ſatisfied that it was God (and not man or Devil) that called him: A good Cauſe, a good Call, and a good Conſcience, will make a good Courage, and all are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to a Captain or Soldier. Eſpecially <hi>the Lord looked upon him,</hi> as well liking his ſpeech. <hi>v.</hi> 14. vouchſafes him a Sign, <hi>v.</hi> 21. ſignifying, that the <hi>Midianites</hi> ſhould be Deſtroyed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mans labour, ſeeing Fire came out of the Rock (as before Water had done, <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.7.) without any humane help to conſume the Sacrifice; therefore did <hi>Gideon</hi> erect an Altar to the Lord, who had thus confirmed him (not only by theſe Signs, <hi>v.</hi> 17. but by two other Signs, <hi>v.</hi> 36.37.) and thus com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted him againſt his deſpondencies, and called the name of his Altar <hi>[Jehovah Shalom]</hi> the Lord of Peace, <hi>v.</hi> 23.24. O that this Inſcription were upon all our Hearts, as 2. Theſſ. 3.16. <hi>The Lord of Peace give us peace always by all means,</hi> this would anſwer all Doubts, and advance Faith above Fear. The ſign of the <hi>Fleece, Gideon</hi> deſired to be doubled, not out of <hi>Incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity</hi> to tempt God, but out of <hi>Humility</hi> to be ſupported under the ſence of his own weakneſs and unſuitableneſs to ſo great an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, againſt which he found marvelous Relief, in the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Wonder of the <hi>Fleece,</hi> which intimated two things to him. 1. Concerning <hi>Iſrael.</hi> 2. Concerning <hi>Midian.</hi> (1.) As to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that was repreſented by the Fleece, being ſometimes wet with the Dew of Heaven, and ſometimes dry. (2.) As to <hi>Midian,</hi> they
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64617:7"/>had Fleeced Iſrael of all their good things, and pull'd all the Wooll from off their backs, as the Shearer (in that Fleece) had don to the poor Sheep, turning him naked out of doors into the open Fields; but now <hi>Gideon</hi> (with the Lords help) ſhould fleece <hi>Midian:</hi> the Sword of the Lord and of <hi>Gideon</hi> ſhould do as much for them, as they had done for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> pay them home in their own Coyn, and requite them to the full, after the Law of retaliation: hereby <hi>Gideons</hi> Faith, weak at firſt, did gradually grow ſtrong by thoſe confirming Signs; ſo comes he in as a Candidate in that Apoſtolical Catalogue, <hi>Heb</hi> 11.32. Amongſt the higheſt Favourites in the Court of Heaven: Beſides thoſe two Godly Men (<hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Gideon,</hi> that <hi>deſired</hi> confirming Signs) there be many others, to whom God vouchſafed Signs, though <hi>undeſired:</hi> as, the Tree of Life to <hi>Adam,</hi> Gen. 3.22. The Fire of God to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 15.17. The budding of the Rod to <hi>Aaron,</hi> Num. 17.5. The Sun ſtanding ſtill to <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> Joſh. 10.13. And its running back to <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> 2. Kings. 20.8, 9. Fiery Tongues to the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> Acts 2.3, 4. A Draught of Fiſh to <hi>Peter,</hi> John. 21.6. A Star to the three Wiſe men, Mat. 2.2.9. Dumbneſs to <hi>Zechariah,</hi> Luke 1.20. and many other Signs to Believers, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17, 18, 20.</p>
            <p>Yet ſometimes we find God forcing Signs, even upon wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, as upon that branded one <hi>Ahaz,</hi> Iſai. 7.10.11.12.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Though <hi>this was King Ahaz,</hi> wicked with an accent, even he ſhall ſee, that while he was under the power of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Devil, yet hath he to do with a moſt gracious God, who by a wonderful condeſeenſion will needs give him a Sign; 'tis an unheard of vouchſafement to vouchſafe a Sign to ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Unbeliever, this is more than Chriſt would do to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> whom he calls a baſtardly Brood, for deſiring a Sign, as before. <hi>Matt.</hi> 12.39. [<hi>Ask a Sign either in the Depth,</hi> &amp;c.] Here was a fair offer to a moſt foul Sinner, he might have had a ſight of Heaven or of Hell for a Sign, yet inſtead of an humble and thankful asking, he ſordidly anſwered (tantamont) Ile ask no askings, Ille try no Signs, I know a trick worth two of that, I'le
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64617:7"/>ſend to the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> ſo help my ſelf, God may keep his Signs to himſelf, I crave no ſuch courteſy at his hands, &amp;c. Did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any branded Belialiſt or black-mouthed Bedlam ſpeak worſe to God than he in all this: no wonder if God ſet a black brand upon him, ſaying, <hi>This is that</hi> Ahaz, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.22. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this ingratitude and provocation, God (of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) <hi>gave Iſrael a Sign,</hi> Iſa. 7.14. A ſingular Sign, a Sign both from above and from beneath, inaſmuch as this <hi>Immanuel,</hi> born of a Virgin, did joyn pure Heaven and baſe Earth together, in his two Natures. Again, thoſe Signs which the Scripture men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are manifold; as, 1. Such as be meerly Natural, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.14. 2. Praeternatural, beſide the power of Nature in her ordinary production, ſuch are Prodigies in Heaven and Monſters on Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3. Supernatural, which are either <hi>Divine</hi> (ſuch as were the Miracles God wrought by the Prophets and Apoſtles) or <hi>Diabolical,</hi> as the <hi>Lying Wonders.</hi> Deut. 13.2.3. 2. Theſſ. 2.9. and Rev. 13.13. As there be Natural Signs, ſo there be Inſtituted Signs, to wit, the Sacraments which are call'd <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Seals</hi> of the Covenant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.11. Moreover the Signs God ſhews to men, are either ordinary or extraordinary, <hi>commnnia aut Inſolita Signa:</hi> Except we ſee (not common, but) <hi>unuſual ſigns, we will not believe.</hi> John. 4.48. We have a frequent ſight of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Signs, and of Artificial Signs, the former hanging in the Heavens, expoſed to open view, the latter hanging over every Houſe (almoſt) in this great City, yea and ſuch ſigns as be ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, indeed ſome Signs are ſignificant, <hi>ex primaria intentione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituentis,</hi> purpoſely and primarily Inſtituted to ſignify ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whether the Inſtitutor be God or Man. God is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Inſtitutor of all ſignificant ſigns in Sacred things, as he Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted the two Sacraments under the Law, and the two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments under the Goſpel; other ſignificant Signs or Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which are only mans Inſtitution (<hi>and never came into the mind of God,</hi> Jer. 7.31. <hi>Nor out of the Mouth of God,</hi> Deut. 4.1.2.) ought juſtly to be exploded. All <hi>Divine Worſhip</hi> muſt have <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Warrant,</hi> and Divine Inſtitutions may not be mingled with
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64617:8"/>Humane Inventions: This is to Plow in Gods Field, with an Ox and an Aſs, and to ſow therein mingled Seeds (even <hi>Tares</hi> as well as <hi>Wheat,</hi>) and to worſhip the Lord in a Linſy-Woolſy Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.9.10.11. There be alſo ſignificant ſigns in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> and common things (as well as <hi>Sacred</hi>) whoſe proper and primary end in the purpoſe of their Inſtitutor (man) is to ſignify ſomething, as the Signs at every <hi>Door</hi> in the <hi>City,</hi> and at every Inn in the <hi>Country,</hi> and the Eſcucheons at Great mens Houſes: And there be other <hi>Signs,</hi> which be ſignificant only by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and ſecondarily, not eſſentially and from the <hi>primary</hi> purpoſe of their Inſtitutors, Thus Steeples and Poſts <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may ſignify by their ſhadows what time of the day it is, which is not the proper and peculiar purpoſe for which they are made, or uſe of them, as is of Clocks and Dials, 'tis a <hi>ſecundary</hi> uſe only.</p>
            <p>But to inſiſt only upon extraordinary <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>ſigna inſolita</hi> unuſual Marvels) according to my preſent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign: conſider, that as their <hi>Ends</hi> ſo their <hi>Kinds</hi> are various, 1. Their <hi>Ends</hi> are from their Author and Original) manifold: as, 1. They are intentionally deſigned, by the great and ſole Wonder-working God, for the confirming of that Truth, <hi>once delivered to the Saints,</hi> Jude 3. Mark 16.17.18.20. and Hebr. 2.4. Thoſe extraordinary Signs, are well called, the Swadling-bands of the Infant Church, therefore was ſhe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally Dignified and Fortified with Miracles, always and only while and when ſhe was young, tender, and needed ſome corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boration: Tis true, there were ſome ſprinklings of Miracles upon other emergent occaſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But the main body of them were wrought firſt by <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſhuah; Moſes</hi> was the <hi>firſt and new giver of the Law,</hi> then the <hi>Church in the Wilderneſs</hi> (ſo called <hi>Act.</hi> 7.38.) was but a weak Infant, ſo needed thoſe <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> which <hi>Moſes</hi> wrought, both in <hi>Aegypt</hi> Act. 7.36. and in the Wilderneſs, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.39.40.41. with 27. to 38. Yet none were wrought after ſhe got into <hi>Canaan,</hi> though <hi>Joſhuah</hi> did in conveying them thither. 2. By <hi>Elijah</hi> and <hi>Fliſha,</hi> who were the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64617:8"/>two new <hi>Reſtorers of the Law,</hi> (which amounts almoſt to a Giver of it, ſo tantamont a Law-giver) then the Church was newly Born again, and ſo ſtood in need of a ſecond ſwadling, by many more Miracles, after her Recovery from her worſe Relaps in <hi>Ahabs</hi> time, &amp;c. 3. By <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles,</hi> who were both new <hi>Givers</hi> and Reſtorers of the Goſpel inaſmuch as the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel was preached in Paradice, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.) Then did the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Goſpel by diverſe Miracles, as by the Wings of the Wind, fly abroad and was divulged at firſt all the World over; and 'tis very remarkable, though <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt came in the ſpirit and power of <hi>Elijah,</hi> yet did this <hi>Type do no Miracles,</hi> as the <hi>Anti type</hi> did, <hi>John</hi> 10.41. leaſt he ſhould be miſtaken for the Meſſiah, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.15. who was to <hi>do many,</hi> John 7.31. and 11.47. Yet <hi>John</hi> was a <hi>burning</hi> and a <hi>ſhining Lighn,</hi> John 5.35. <hi>burning</hi> in himſelf and <hi>ſhining</hi> to others, he Thundred in his Doctrine, and Lightned in his Life without Miracles, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was he ſo much admired, as a great Reformer in a moſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Age. Chriſt and his Apoſtles were all Wonder-work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecured by it while it is tender, and 'tis oft watered, but ers, which was as an Hedge to a young Plant, that is when once grown up, the Hedge is removed, and the watering left off. Hence we ſay to the Romaniſts, That all the Miracles of the New Teſtament, are ours of the Reformed Religion, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as they all did Demonſtrate the ſame Doctrine, which we do defend, We need no new Miracle, to conform an old Truth that hath been before ſo confirmed: He that now requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a Miracle, is therefore himſelf a Miracle. The Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our preſent Reformation is and will be that great Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which we are in theſe times to look for: 'tis that wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Work which <hi>former Ages</hi> did deſpair of, the <hi>preſent</hi> Admireth, and the <hi>future</hi> will ſtand amazed at: concerning the <hi>Lying Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> the Romiſh Church ſo much boaſts of, I have diſcovered the fallacy of them at large, in my <hi>Diſcovery of the perſon and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of Antichrist</hi> from <hi>page</hi> 48. to 55. to which I refer the Reader.</p>
            <p>The Second End of Extraordinary <hi>Signs and Wonders</hi> is for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:64617:9"/>Awakning a droufy, ſluggiſh and ſecure World, which will not know the Signs of the Times, Matt. 16.3. yea, and for Rouſing up the Slumbring Virgins of the Church, both the Wiſe and the Fooliſh, As the Midnight Cry did. Matt. 25.2, 5. 6. This is certainly the great End why the great Wonder-working God worketh Wonders and ſheweth ſigns ſuch as are Extraordinary and Univerſally aſtoniſhing, to Alarm, as with thoſe Trumpets, both Saints and Sinners, that none might be ſurprized, He therefore doth moſt graciouſly ſound his Trumpet in and by them, that his Judgments may not come as a Thief in the Night upon us, as he hath oft foretold us, Matth. 24.44. 1 Theſſ. 5.3. Revel. 3.3. and 16.15. The Thief gives no Warning, but comes unexpectedly: So doth not a Gracious God who giveth Warning, for which <hi>Charles</hi> the Great bleſſeth God for Rebuking his Sluggiſhneſs out of his Tender Mercy by thoſe his Signs, as a Blazing Star, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As I ſhew in my little Book of this late Comet, pag. 22. 'Tis undoubtedly moſt dear <hi>Divine Clemency</hi> to give timely Warnings of Approaching Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, for, Humane Calamity the more <hi>ſudden,</hi> the more <hi>gric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous</hi> it is, as (1.) It <hi>amates,</hi> (or Daunts,) and <hi>Exanimates</hi> a man, as the ſudden Storm doth the Marriner, and as the Devil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd <hi>Job</hi>'s Meſſengers ſhould do him, in coming, one at the Heels of another, ſo unexpectedly upon him. 2. It ſurpriſes him at unawares, he ſtands not upon his Guard, ſo can no more prevent it, than unweildly <hi>Eglon,</hi> could <hi>Ehud</hi>'s deadly thruſt.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> are Various, 1. In their <hi>Ends,</hi> ſo, 2. In their <hi>Kinds;</hi> as, 1. There are <hi>Miracula &amp; Miranda.</hi> Many things are <hi>miracula,</hi> much marvelled at, as exceeding the common Courſe of Providence which yet are not, <hi>Ex natura Rei, Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula,</hi> of the proper Nature of Miracles. The latter exceedeth the Power of all created Agents, but the former doth not ſo, A true and proper Miracle is the Stopping or Altering the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Courſe of Nature, and 'tis a producing of ſome ſuch E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects as do tranſcend Natures Law, Power, and Capacity: 'tis
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64617:9"/>indeed, an Extraordinary operation of the Almighty Creator in Nature, either without the Interpoſition and Concurrence of Second Cauſes, or Above their natural Capacity: In a word, 'tis the production of Something out of Nothing, either as to <hi>Matter</hi> or as to <hi>Manner</hi> of production, ſo that the Almighty can only work true Miracles either in himſelf or in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants impour'd by him. 2. There are <hi>mira ceu miranda,</hi> marvelous Works and Wonders, 1. of God's Working, and 2 of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's, who is God s Ape herein, and who by his Impreſſion, which, through his Angelical Nature, he is able to make up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on matter, can do wonderful things to cheat the blind world, as he did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and the Aegyptians by his Vaſſals the Sorcerers. But he cannot work ſuch a Wonder as is a Miracle. The Lending Power will never accommodate the Borrowing party with ſuch a Power as may be prejudicial to his own ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and glorious Deſign. The only wiſe Creator will never gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify his Creatures, nay the worſt of his Creatures, ſuch are all Sorcerers) for any ſuch end as either to obſtruct his WORK, or to cheat the World Hereupon <hi>Austin, de Unit ate Feeleſ. cap.</hi> 16. ſaith excellently, That the pretended Miracles of his time were either <hi>figmenta mendacium Hominum, aut Portenta fallacium Spirituum,</hi> either the Forgeries of lying Men, or the Portents of Deceitful Devils: for a true Miracle is the work of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Power, whether primarily or Secondarily performed: and hence <hi>David</hi> ſaith. That <hi>God only doth wondrous Things,</hi> Pſ. 72.18. Indeed God ſomtimes uſeth men as moral Inſtruments, but never as natural Cauſes in working VVonders, which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs the Power of Nature. Hence alſo <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> when God <hi>drove him from men</hi> by his own Courtiers and ſubjects, and ſo had tam'd him, and taken him a loop or link lower, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him graze among the Beaſts, himſelf becomes a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Preacher to the VVorld, publickly proclaiming the Great God to be the only Author of <hi>Signs and Wonders;</hi> 'Tis the Lord only that <hi>ſheweth</hi> them, And they are all His, with an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaſis, and not only So, but they are [Rab Rabbin] <hi>Great
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:64617:10"/>many,</hi> and <hi>Magnificent,</hi> as the word ſignifies, Dan. 4.2, 3.33, 34, 37. Mark how he enlargeth upon this point again and again, and he calls God's great Acts towards him, (in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion from his Throne) 1. SIGNS, as they did ſignify Gods Wiſdom Power and Juſtice to him; and 2. VVONDERS, as worthy to be Wondred at by him, when yet in the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Ruffe of his Pride and Proſperity, ſhould have both a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Execution of his Downfal from the Higheſt Pinacle of his Arch Triumphant: Mark, <hi>Nebuchadn.</hi> hereupon celebrates God's Kingdom only, had <hi>David</hi> handled this, he had added (as in his <hi>Hilled Gadol,</hi> or great Gratulatory Pſalm, the 136.) He doth often, <hi>His Mercy endureth for ever,</hi> which is the foot and burthen of the whole Song, not as an idle tautologie, or <hi>vain Repetition,</hi> but as a moſt notable intimation of the Saints unſatisfiableneſs in praiſing GOD, for his never-failing mercy, his Covenant-mercy, his ſpecial mercy in CHRIST (who was the moſt ſignal Sign, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.14.) in and by whom God only worketh wondrous things. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 72.17.18. Where <hi>David</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth God, for all the forementioned Benefits by the Lord Chriſt, of whom his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> was but a Type: hereof <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezar</hi> was Ignorant, However 'tis admirable, he could go thus far, as to acknowledge the Lord Jehovah to be the true and wonder-working-God, whereby he teſtified his Repentance in his admiring (as in a Rapture) the mighty and matchleſs pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, he was conſtrained to give God the Glory of all his wonderous Works, hence ſome think he was truly and throughly Converted here, ſeeing he falls ſo kindly under the mighty hand of God, whereby (as he penitently acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) thoſe great <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> were wrought concerning him, that ſuch a mighty Monarch (as he was) ſhould be chaſed from his Kingdom, yea and from among men, and live among brute Beaſts, feeding upon Graſs as they fed (who had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fed on the choiceſt fare, the chiefeſt Cates and Delicates in the World) and that for 7 long years, yea deprived of his Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Underſtanding all this time (oh that the proudeſt Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:64617:10"/>of the World, would well ponder this wonderful Work) and yet after all this, be reſtored to his <hi>right Intellectuals,</hi> and to his <hi>Royal Dignitys.</hi> How well doth he ſtile them Gods <hi>great Signs and Wonders</hi> for <hi>who</hi> but God <hi>can look upon the proud and bring them low,</hi> Job 40.11, 12, 13. God did <hi>abate</hi> his Pride, and <hi>abaſe</hi> his Power, to bring him to Repentance <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God hath a moſt powerful Eye, both for <hi>Everſion</hi> as here, and for <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk.</hi> 22.61. and here (probably) alſo. The whole work being a ſupernatural change both forward and backward, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and inward) and every circumſtance (occaſion, manner, degree and time, &amp;c.) ſeeming no leſs then a new Creation.</p>
            <p>Again 3ly. The Wonders of Gods working are either <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> or <hi>Extraordinary.</hi> 1. <hi>Ordinary,</hi> God often ſhews himſelf <hi>maximum in minimis,</hi> the greateſt Artiſt in the <hi>ſmaleſt</hi> matters, not only in that miraculous plague of <hi>Lice</hi> (made of the Duſt) upon the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> which ſo fainted under theſe poor Vermin (armed with the power of God) that they were forced to cry out, <hi>This is the very Finger of GOD,</hi> Exod. 8.17, 18, 19. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 'tis very Admirable to obſerve how this Act of Omnipoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency in ſuch baſe and vile Creatures, as are Duſt and Lice conſounded the Impoſture and Power of Jannes and Jambres 2 Tim. 3.8, 9. yea, and of the Devil their Maſter) yet th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Great God was highly honored thereby, for, 'tis ſaid, <hi>All th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> duſt of the Land was made Lice by Moſes,</hi> ver. 17. then the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians had no matter leſt them to try their Diabolical Art upon unleſs they could <hi>create Duſt,</hi> and ſuppoſe they had ſome Du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> left them for an Experiment, yet, though they ſtretch'd ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their hands with Rods, and did their utmoſt Endeavours, <hi>The could not,</hi> verſ. 18. They could neither <hi>Create</hi> Duſt where there was none, nor, where there was ſome, <hi>convert</hi> it into Lice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neither could theſe Magicians ſave their own Skins, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thus it plainly Appeareth, That the power and Providence of God extendeth even to the loweſt and vileſt things in the Creation, and that God can, after a Miraculous manner, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Greateſt power either of Men or Devils therewith at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:64617:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pleaſure. And this is Gods ſhewing himſelf the greateſt Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator in the leaſt of his Operations, and not only, I ſay, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, but alſo even in ordinary Caſes: Indeed the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the eternal Power and God head</hi> is manifeſt and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the whole Creation, yea in the Decimo-Sexto's as well as in the Great Folio's thereof: Every Creature hath <hi>Aliquid Dei aeque ac aliquid Nihili,</hi> Something of God in it as well as ſomething of Nothing; otherwiſe it could not be ſaid to be created out of Nothing by the Creator, and many times we Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire that there ſhould be more of Art and Activity, in a Dwarf, Bee or Ant, than in a Giant, or Elephant, moſt great Souls are ſometimes couch'd in moſt little Bodies. Amd the truth is, True and real Wonders are God's daily work (upon which Account they may be called Ordinary) as I ſhew in my Crown of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, upon that Book with Three leaves (the Creation of God) <hi>viz. Heaven, Earth</hi> or <hi>Sea,</hi> Pſal. 135.6. There be Wonders <hi>without number</hi> in all thoſe Three, Job 9.10. Such as the Wiſeſt may well wonder at, and more obſervable than either the moſt are aware of, or affected with: 'Tis manifeſt, That <hi>Jehovah</hi> is the true and only Thaumaturgus the great and ordinary Wonder-worker: To omit the Wonders of the Creation (for which ſee Pſalm 136, 4, 5, 6, 7. and my little Book aforeſaid upon Meditation, pag. 125. to 145. and give but a Specimen, or ſmall Scantling of them: (1.) 'Tis a Wonder to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred at, How the <hi>Bones grow in her that is with Child,</hi> Eccleſ. 11.5. <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf, who was Natures Secretary, wonders at this; and ſo did <hi>David</hi> before him, Pſalm. 139.14. 2. The double Motion of the Lungs, call'd Syſtole and Diaſtole, and of the Pulſe in mans Body, is a Wonder which that Famous Phyſician <hi>Galen,</hi> tho an Heathen, was ſo amazed with, that he would needs offer Sacrifices to that God whom he knew not, who yet as he ſuppoſed muſt be the Original of that Wonder, 3. The Strength of the Nether Chap is a Wonder, whereof no man could ever give a Sufficient Natural Reaſon. Nor 4. of the Heat in the Stomach for Digeſtion, of all Meats <hi>in Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64617:11"/>&amp; Sanguinem,</hi> into juice and Blood in a little time. Nor. 5. Of the various Colours in the Rain-bow: Nor, 6. of the Flux and Reflux of the <hi>Sea:</hi> Nor, 7. of the Magnetick Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of the <hi>Loadſtone;</hi> to let paſs many others, that are <hi>Wonders</hi> all, though ordinary: No nor 8. of this common caſe, that <hi>Chaff</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>cold,</hi> as to keep <hi>Snow</hi> (hid within it) from melting, and yet ſo warm as to haſten the Ripning of Apples which are coverd with it. <hi>Gods wonders are without Number:</hi> But 2. Inſtances more. The 9th wonder is, God's <hi>turning water into Wine,</hi> as his <hi>Daily Work.</hi> 'Tis true, this is called, The Beginning of <hi>Chriſts Miracles,</hi> Joh. 2.11. and 'twas a mighty Miracle, yea better than that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> for, the Giver of the Law <hi>turn'd Water into Blood,</hi> but the Giver of the Goſpel <hi>turn'd Water into Wine;</hi> the former could not be drank without danger of dying, the latter was delightful to Drink, and Heart-Reviving: yet this VVonder of turning water into VVine, is a daily work with God, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> excellently obſerveth, Inaſmuch as the <hi>Rain water</hi> which falls upon the Root of the Vine and nouriſheth the Tree, Doth in time turn into the Grape, The Juice, Blood or VVine is originally VVater. In the 10th and laſt place, <hi>Auguſtin</hi> excellently alſo maketh Gods multiplying a grain of <hi>Corn,</hi> ſown in the Earth, to 30, 60, or 100 Corns, a more miraculous wonder than Chriſts multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the few Loves to feed 5000 perſons: his words are, <hi>mirabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or eſt Grani in Terra multiplicatio, quam illa quinque panum;</hi> Tract. 24. in Joh. 6.9, 10, 11. yet was that miracle of the 5 loaves exceeding marvelous, Inaſmuch as the Loaves, by a ſtrange kind of Arithmetick, were <hi>Multiplied</hi> by <hi>Diviſion,</hi> as they were diſtributed among the Multitude, and an <hi>Addition</hi> to them was made by <hi>Subſtraction:</hi> As each perſon had his piece ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted from the Loaves, yet were they augmented thereby: Notwithſtanding all this. That Reverend Father prefers the common Experience of every Husband-man, the multiplying of one grain, as a greater wonder:</p>
            <p>Thus, ſomething <hi>may be known</hi> of God in the whole Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rom. 1.19. and much more in Divine Providence, God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64617:12"/>never <hi>leaves himſelf without Witneſs, Acts</hi> 14.17. yet, <hi>leaves he all men without excuſe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without any Apology, Rom. 1.20. for though natural light is not available to bring faln Man into the Favour of God, yet it is ſufficient to convince him of Moral wickedneſs both againſt God and Man: oh then what pity it is, that Chriſt ſhould ſtill ſay, <hi>Ye will not believe, except ye ſee Signs and Wonders,</hi> whereas men live in the very midſt of many ſuch like Signs and wonders (as are the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid: <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet, they come not up to ſo much as amounts to an Old Teſtament Faith, of <hi>Believing in GOD,</hi> (though a New Teſtament Faith is requiſite alſo, as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Ye believe in God, believe alſo in Me,</hi> John 14.1.) but are Intoxicated with Atheiſm, and live according to their Luſts, as if they were all become <hi>David</hi>'s Fools, which <hi>ſay in their Heart, There is no God,</hi> though they Daily ſee God ſufficiently ſealing up his General Goodneſs to Man, in doing him Good <hi>pro victu &amp; amictu,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing upon him Daily Bread and Daily Cloathing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides thoſe Ordinary, God hath alſo his Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Wonders: The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very great and Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Works of GOD, Act. 2.11. for, though the Great GOD doth limit Nature to her Common Products, yet will he never limit himſelf, but <hi>Will Do whatever pleaſeth him,</hi> Pſal. 115.3. without either the Help or the Hindrance of any Whether it be <hi>Miracles</hi> or <hi>Marvels,</hi> or <hi>Ordinanary Occurrences:</hi> As to the firſt of thoſe, I have ſpoke ſo largely already, and ſhall only add, that there were never any Miracles for <hi>Weight, Meaſure and Number</hi> (for God is ſaid to do all things <hi>pondere men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura &amp; Numero</hi>) equal to thoſe in the time of the Goſpel: none of thoſe either <hi>before</hi> or <hi>under the Law,</hi> can be parralel'd with thoſe under the Goſpel, upon all thoſe three accounts, they are not like them for <hi>weight, meaſure</hi> and <hi>number,</hi> It may eaſily be Demonſtrated how far <hi>Law-Miracles</hi> come ſhort of <hi>Goſpel Miracles,</hi> in all theſe reſpects. To Inſtance only in that one aſorenamed; Moſes <hi>indeed turned Water into Blood,</hi> but the <hi>Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah turned Water into Wine,</hi> and how much the latter exceeds and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64617:12"/>excels the former, is obvious to every ordinary underſtanding, inaſmuch as the former was made <hi>peſtiferous</hi> the latter <hi>ſalutife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Drink:</hi> therefore the captious and carnal Jews were excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly irrational, in rejecting thoſe Miracles the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> wrought amongſt them, and requeſting ſome ſuch as <hi>Moſes</hi> had wrought for their Forefathers (as giving them <hi>Manna</hi> from Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Seeing thoſe of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> did far ſurmount thoſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> both in <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>quantity</hi> and in <hi>pondereſity,</hi> Inaſmuch as that <hi>Manna Moſes</hi> gave their Forefathers melted, putrified, bred Worms, and periſhed in the uſing, but the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> gave himſelf the true Bread from Heaven, to feed them up to Everlaſting Life, his own <hi>Fleſh</hi> for them to eat, and his own <hi>Blood</hi> for them to Drink, a Meat and Drink that muſt laſt (without putrifying) ſo long as the World doth laſt, <hi>Manna</hi> was but the <hi>Type,</hi> which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the <hi>leſſer, Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Antitype,</hi> which is always the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and better; If our Saviour ſay of himſelf, <hi>that he is greater than</hi> Solomon, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.42. We may likewiſe ſay of him, he is <hi>greater and better than</hi> Manna. Moreover, that which more aggravated the Jews Contempt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> perſon and his Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, is, that their knowledge of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Miracles they had upon Credit only, they received it by Tradition from their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers: But as to the Miracles of our Bleſſed <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived them not by <hi>Hear-ſay,</hi> but were perſonal Eye-witneſſes of them, therefore doth the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> make his Solemn Appeal to their own Knowledge and Conſciences, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.22. So that he leaves them no liberty of doubting, for CHRIST was by ſo many manifeſt Demonſtrations <hi>Approved of</hi> GOD (to be his grand Embaſſad or to the World) and ſhould therefore be alſo <hi>approved of men,</hi> eſpecially of thoſe men who could ſay <hi>[Hiſce oculis ejus miracula Vidimus]</hi> we have ſeen with our very Eyes, the wonderful Works which he wrought, and which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any Man before him did Work. <hi>John</hi> 9.32. No not <hi>Moſes</hi> whom they called their Maſter, ſo that even the very <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in Jeruſalem did know that Chriſt was mighty in Word and Deed</hi> (<hi>as well as</hi> Moſes <hi>Act.</hi> 7.22.) <hi>both before God and before all the People,</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64617:13"/>whoſe very preſence Chriſt wrought his Miracles. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.18.19. for he <hi>did nothing in a corner,</hi> as <hi>Act.</hi> 26.26 but before mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Spectators and Eye-witneſſes thereof. As to the <hi>third,</hi> to wit, <hi>Ordinary Occurrences</hi> which cometh to paſs commonly and uſually by the <hi>power of Nature</hi> (and often by the dexterity of Art) is not my deſigned Subject in this ſhort Diſcourſe, though there be whole bundles of Wonders, even in the common courſe of <hi>Natural</hi> (if not <hi>Artificial</hi>) productions, as I have Inſtanced in ten particulars aforementioned, which at this time may be ſufficient. As to the <hi>ſecond,</hi> to wit, <hi>Marvels</hi> (which are certain middle things, betwixt <hi>Miracles</hi> and <hi>Ord ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Occurrences</hi>) thoſe are the principal matter intended to be Diſcuſſed in this little Treatiſe (which though it be little in its Bulk) yet Treateth upon the <hi>great things</hi> of GOD. 'Tis a Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Maxim, that an <hi>increated liberty</hi> is an Attribute of the Divine Eſſence, and this being <hi>Infinite,</hi> (as well as <hi>Increated</hi>) cannot be limitted by any of its objects, but Acts freely and out of his meer good pleaſure, and not out of any neceſſity of Nature. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 115.3. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 27.5. and 18.4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hereupon the <hi>Great God,</hi> being a <hi>Free Agent</hi> may ſometimes ſtep out of his common Road, and ordinary courſe of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and ſo work beyond the reach of <hi>Nature,</hi> and above the skill of <hi>Art,</hi> to the producing of not only <hi>Miracles</hi> (as above) but alſo <hi>Marvels</hi> or <hi>Wonders.</hi> Thus God is Deſcribed to be one <hi>that doth great things and unſearchable, yea marvelous things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number,</hi> Job 5.9. Thus Eliphaz <hi>here</hi> ſpake the Truth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the wonderful <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and Almighty <hi>Power</hi> of God; and <hi>Job</hi> himſelf doth readily ſet his Seal to that great Truth, <hi>Job</hi> 9.10. He is a God <hi>Glorious in Holineſs, fearful in Praiſes, and doing Wonders,</hi> Exod. 15.11. 'Tis a moſt ſtately Deſcription of God, crying <hi>who is like thee,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> cryes alſo <hi>Who, is a God like our great God, a God that doth Wonders. Pſ.</hi> 77.13.14. Sua mirabilia ſunt omnimodo memorabilia, <hi>He maketh his marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Works, all worthy to be remembred. Pſ.</hi> 111 4</p>
            <p>In Sacred Scripture, we find <hi>Miracles</hi> and <hi>Marvels</hi> or VVon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:64617:13"/>are promiſcuouſly taken for each other, yet are they not convertible Terms: All <hi>Miracles</hi> are indeed <hi>Marvels,</hi> but <hi>[vice verſa]</hi> on the other hand all <hi>Marvels</hi> are not <hi>Miracles:</hi> there is this difference <hi>[Ex parte Rei]</hi> betwixt them, <hi>Miracles</hi> do exceed the power of Created Agents, but <hi>Marvels</hi> do not ſo, yet are they extraordinary Productions of Divine Providence, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Natural Agents: God is ſaid to work three ways: <hi>1ſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> according to Nature: <hi>2ly.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> beſides Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>3ly</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> above Nature; but never (as ſome ſay) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> directly againſt Nature: The ordinary products of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, are <hi>according to Nature:</hi> Extraordinary Miracles are <hi>above Nature:</hi> and extraordinary Marvels are only <hi>beſide Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;</hi> but ſhould the Great God put forth his power againſt Nature, Nature would be deſtroyed, and the Deſtruction of Nature would be the Deſtruction of the World, for it is as a round chain conſiſting of many links all linked one to another) and if one of thoſe links be looſed, the whole chain falls in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and becomes uſeleſs: As to thoſe <hi>Marvels</hi> or <hi>Wonders,</hi> which are beſide Nature (the preſent Subject of my Diſcourſe.) A right underſtanding may be had hereof, in this manner; we muſt ſuppoſe the God of Nature is above Nature, ſo can over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rule it at his pleaſure: No <hi>Natural Agents</hi> can poſſibly. Act without the leave of <hi>Supernatural Providence.</hi> The <hi>Fire</hi> cannot burn (as in the Caſe of the <hi>Buſh,</hi> Exod. 3.2. and of the three Nobles of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Dan. 3.28.) nor can the <hi>water</hi> drown (as in the Caſe of the <hi>Red-Sea</hi> and of <hi>Jordan</hi>) without (as Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy phraſeth it) a <hi>Divine concurſe:</hi> God is the <hi>primus motor,</hi> and his Providence is the <hi>primum mobile</hi> of all Created things, and have their Dependency upon their Creator (both as to <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and as to <hi>motion</hi> and as to <hi>all-things,</hi> Act 17.25.28.) and no created being can make any motion, more than the leſſer Wheels can move in a <hi>Clock</hi> or <hi>Watch,</hi> without the Impulſion of the greater Wheels thereof: yet ſtill we muſt know, when this Great Creator worketh any <hi>Marvels</hi> (yea or Miracles) he ſtill holdeth Nature as a <hi>Pen</hi> or <hi>Pencil,</hi> in his Hand, and draws his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:64617:14"/>own Models or Platforms (either <hi>Ordinary</hi> or <hi>Extraordinary</hi>) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own pleaſure, yea 'tis all one with GOD whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he act with it or without it, by a power that is Almighty, All ſufficient (of it ſelf) and infinitely Superior to it, for he is under no obliging neceſſity of being confined to uſe <hi>Nature</hi> as his <hi>Pen</hi> or <hi>Pencil.</hi> Though this general Diſcourſe hath (beyond my expectation) ſwoln much upon my Hand, yet have I all along judged it neceſſary to ſay all that I have ſaid, for a fuller <hi>Explication</hi> of my preſent Subject (which ought to be diſtinctly diſcourſed) before any <hi>Application</hi> can be made thereof: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to avoid any farther prolixity, I ſhall (for brevity ſake) confine my ſelf to three Heads. <hi>1ſt.</hi> The <hi>Sorts. 2ly.</hi> The <hi>Scenes. 3ly.</hi> The <hi>Significations</hi> of thoſe marvelous <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>wonders,</hi> &amp;c. 1. Of the <hi>Sorts</hi> or <hi>Kinds</hi> of them: 1. Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy telleth us of three <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Signs:</hi> 1ſt. Such as are <hi>memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> (called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which recalleth ſomething that is <hi>paſt,</hi> to preſent remembrance, as the <hi>Rain-Bow</hi> is a ſtanding Sign and Monument of the paſt Flood, and as that ſtately and lofty Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, lately Erected nigh <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> is a Monument (ſo called) of the late dreadful burning of <hi>London.</hi> 2ly. Such <hi>Signs</hi> as are <hi>Demonſtrative</hi> (called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which do ſhew ſomething <hi>that is preſent,</hi> as Smoak doth Demonſtrate ſome Fire to be preſent, and the Buſh, that Wine is then and there to be ſold, and ſuch like, as are <hi>Ordinary;</hi> and ſo thoſe <hi>Signs Extraordinary,</hi> which accompanied the primitive Believers: <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17.20. did all ſignify Gods preſence co-working with them, working wonderful Works, both in Preachers and Hearers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 3ly. Such <hi>Signs</hi> as are <hi>Predictive</hi> (call'd <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) which preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth or foreſheweth ſomething that is <hi>Future,</hi> and will come to paſs, as redneſs of the Sky, at the Evening, betokens a fair day approaching; but in the morning the ſame is a <hi>Sign</hi> of Rain or Wind, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.3. This is proved and approved, by Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Experience, the probable Reaſon whereof in the courſe of Nature, may be this, the Setting-Sun carries off thoſe red Clouds all along with it, out of our Horizon, into the other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64617:14"/>Hemiſphere, and there diſperſeth them, either to a Conſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or to a Rainy day unto our Antipodes, but the Riſing Sun, carries the Red Clouds up aloſt along with it, into our Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and then diſſolves them into Wind or Rain; not unlike to this, is that Prognoſtick Monaſtick of the Poet, from the vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous colour of the Firmament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeruleus pluvias, Denuntiat Igneus Euros.</hi> A watery Sky fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth Rain, and a red fiery Sky foreſignifies high, boiſterous and tempeſtuous VVinds. Theſe (and ſuch like) are call'd na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and <hi>ordinary</hi> Prognoſticks, and not at all unlawful in their own nature, for CHRIST did not reprove the <hi>Phariſes</hi> and <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces</hi> (in Matt. 16.3.4.) for their being weather-wiſe (though it belonged not to their Profeſſion) and for their diſcerning the Face of the Sky, concerning fair and foul Seaſons, to the more aptly ordering their ſecular Occaſions, he did not blame them for this <hi>abſolutely</hi> but <hi>comparatively</hi> only, becauſe they could be ſo skilful in the Book of <hi>Nature,</hi> yet were ſo unskilful in the Book of <hi>Scripture;</hi> ſaying, certainly, you Leaders of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple cannot be ignorant what the Scripture teſtifies, that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhall make the Deaf to Hear, the Dumb to Speak, the Dead to Live, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such <hi>[ſigna inſignia]</hi> VVonders hath been wrought by me, as never were ſeen or heard of, and ye your ſelves cannot but acknowledg it, <hi>John</hi> 11.47. Beſides, the Teſtimonies 1. of Angels. 2. Of the Star. 3. Of the <hi>Dove.</hi> 4. Of my Father. 5. Of <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> 6. Of the very De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. Yea 7ly. Of the Multitude, yet cannot yee <hi>Diſcern the Signs of the Times.</hi> Yee muſt all therefore be (ſaith our Lord) either a ſort of ſordid ſorry Sots, or deep Diſſemblers and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolical Hypocrites, or both, in ſceming ſo <hi>criticall</hi> to enquire after the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> ſo <hi>curious</hi> to ſearch after the Truth, which yee are neither <hi>careful to know,</hi> nor <hi>conſciencious to obey.</hi> Yet there be other <hi>Signs,</hi> which are) beſides thoſe <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary,</hi> even <hi>preternatuacl</hi> and <hi>extraordinary,</hi> which are progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks alſo of future things, Neither is it Unlawful, to paſs a General Judgment, tho a Particular without a Special Gift
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64617:15"/>may be) upon them, as will be made more Diſtinctly manifeſt in the <hi>Application</hi> of the whole. Again, Thoſe prognoſtick or preſaging SIGNS are Reduc'd to Three Heads, They are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 1. <hi>Omens,</hi> or 2. <hi>Monſters,</hi> or 3. <hi>Prodigies.</hi> As to the 1. to Omit all the <hi>Omens</hi> obſerved by the Superſtitious in a way of Divination, as, Sneezings, Valentines, ſtumbling upon the Threſhold in the Morning at firſt going out, ſtepping over the Threſhold with the left leg firſt, or knocking the Knees or Leggs one againſt another, even to a Fall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition whereof I have Demonſtrated in my Antidote againſt Popery, pag. 14, to 18. However Dreams appear to be <hi>omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous</hi> either for Good or for Evil, or for both, not only out of the Platonick, Stoick and Pythagorean Philoſophers, but alſo out of the Scriptures as in <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s, young <hi>Samuels, Daniels,</hi> and <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Dreams, there was an <hi>Omen</hi> in them all: now, They are either 1. <hi>Natural,</hi> and ſuch are very Deceitful, Eccleſ. 5.7. So not to be Regarded unleſs, for ſuch and ſuch Ends, as I have mentioned in my <hi>Treachery of the Heart.</hi> pag. 92.2. <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi> ſuch as (ſome ſuppoſes) <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Wives was, whereby the Devil might endeavour to hinder the Work of our Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption. 3. Divine Dreams, which ſometime be doubled, and ſo do make a deep impreſſion, as that of <hi>Pharaoh, &amp;c.</hi> Gen 41.1, 5. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus 'tis ſaid, <hi>God came to Abimelech in a Dream,</hi> Gen. 20.3. This was frequent under all the Old Teſtament, and at the beginning of the New: but now ſince God has ſpoke his Will, in his Word, to us by his Son, Hebr. 1.1.2. We muſt not now expect any New Revelation about any Divine Truth from God in <hi>Dreams:</hi> yet poſſibly God may communicate ſome Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation about <hi>Humane Events</hi> to his Godly Servants by <hi>Dreams:</hi> Inſtance <hi>Monica</hi>'s Dream concerning her Son <hi>Auguſtin</hi> while he was a <hi>Manichee,</hi> That her Son ſhould return to the true Faith of his Mother, which ſhe conſtrued as a good <hi>Omen,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly the Lord heard her Prayers and Tears for him, and cauſed him to return: There be ſundry others in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hiſtory which I paſs-by, and pitch only upon bleſſed <hi>Pareus</hi>'s
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64617:16"/>Dream, related by his Son <hi>Philip</hi> writing his Fathers Life, as a Preface to his Comments. Saying this, <hi>I dream'd in the year</hi> 1618. (The very year of a great Comets appearing,) <hi>that I ſaw all</hi> Hildeberg <hi>in a thick Smoak, but the Princes Pallace all on a light fire: Hereupon I Prayed, Oh moſt merciful GOD! divert from us this moſt ſad Omen, and ſave thy Sarepta from theſe Deſolations by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, both within and without.</hi> Thus the Good man dream'd, and thus he pray'd, but the Decree was gon forth, and ſhortly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter executed acccording to his Dream. Yet this is a moſt certain Truth, That all Dreams are not ſignificant, much leſs have any thing Divine in them: Therefore 'tis not only Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but iniquity alſo to put ſuch an Univerſal Streſs upon them, as if God alwayes warn us in and by them concerning future Events: This is not only Vain Curioſity, to ſearch into Secrets, but alſo a Sinful Superſtition.</p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Predictive Sign</hi> are <hi>Monſters,</hi> ſo called <hi>à monſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> becauſe they do premonſtrate ſome future Events, though it be not every ones part to aſſign them in particular; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Deſtruction of Jeruſalem, a Cow did bring forth a Lamb; the Deſtruction of the City was preſag'd by it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers telleth us, That there are no <hi>Monſters</hi> properly among Plants, but only among Animals, and among them, 'Tis not barely Exceſs, as in <hi>Gyants,</hi> or Defect of Quantity, as in <hi>Pygmees</hi>) that make a <hi>Monſter:</hi> but when the Animal doth ſo much vary from the Right Diſpoſition of its own Kind, as to make it either Horrible or Miſerable, then 'tis a <hi>Monſter.</hi> Thoſe Animals are Monſters, that have two Heads and but one Heart, which is the Fountain of Life: this makes but one Animal, yet Monſtrous: but, If there be two hearts as well as Two Heads, This make 2 Monſtrous Animals, for in ſuch 'tis obſerved, when the one ſleeps, the other can wake, when the one laughs, the other can weep, when the one Dyeth, the other may over-live, as <hi>Buchanan</hi> obſerveth, Rer. Scot. lib. 3. Some, indeed, do make thoſe exceſſes and Defects of Nature (mentioned, Lev. 21.17. to 23.) monſtrous marks of Diſgrace,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64617:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>as if Nature had See her black Brand of Diſgrace upon them, and as if thoſe monſtrous Deformities of the <hi>Body</hi> did Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the like Defects and Deformities in the <hi>Soul:</hi> 'Tis true, concerning thoſe that are crook'd-back'd (which is one of thoſe brands of Nature mentioned in Levit. 21.) Plutarch ſaith, They do <hi>[Nemeſin propriam portare]</hi> carry upon their Backs their own Deſtinies, and ſo, indeed, our crook-back'd <hi>Richard</hi> did, &amp;c. But the Tenderneſs of God in the Levitical Law, towards ſuch is very obſervable, that tho none ſuch muſt be admitted to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up fire-offerings to the Lord, leſt <hi>they ſhould pollute Gods San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary,</hi> both as they were to be Types of a Comely Chriſt, Pſ. 45.3. and Cant. 5.10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and as they ſhould be better than their Sacrifices, which were to have no blemiſh, Levit. 22.20. The Offerer muſt be no more blemiſhed than the Offering, yet might <hi>they eat the Bread of their God,</hi> Levit. 22.22. which ſhews us, That our <hi>Involuntary</hi> weakneſſes ſhall not Debarr us of the Seals and Benefits of Chriſt: But the other Prieſts for Voluntary Uncleanneſs were Depriv'd of that Priviledge which the Deformed ones (wherein they were not blamable) had Admiſſion unto, Levit. 22.3. yea further, The Scripture telleth us, That Halting <hi>Jacob</hi> was true hearted, that Blear eyed <hi>Leah</hi> was both fruitful and faithful, Stammering <hi>Moſes</hi> was the meekeſt man upon Earth, and <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> tho he was <hi>lame,</hi> yet was he loyal, &amp;c. as if the God of Nature did commonly compenſate and Recompence all the Defects of the <hi>Body,</hi> with a better and more bleſſed Surpluſſage in the <hi>Sůl:</hi> But to paſs-by all the Defects in Nature, and Speak only of the <hi>Exceſs,</hi> which Philoſophy phancyeth cannot make a <hi>Monſter,</hi> Seeing 'tis no more than the Higheſt Vigour of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wherein ſhe exerteth her utmoſt ſtrength for producing of <hi>Gyants,</hi> yet thoſe prodigious mighty men, the Scripture mentions, Gen. 6.4. Numb. 13.28, 33. Deut. 1.18. and 3.11. Amos 2.9, &amp;c. were probably <hi>Monſters,</hi> being both monſtrous in their Manners, and in their Mightineſs: Some as tall as Oaks and Cedars, Amos 2.9 and one of them, <hi>viz. Og,</hi> was ſo maſſy, that a Bed of wood was not ſtrong enough to bear the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:64617:17"/>Vaſt Weight of his overgrown Body in turning himſelf upon it, but he muſt have a Bed-ſtead of Iron, and that too, that it might be as a juſt Proportion to his Bulky Body, muſt be fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen foot, that is, five yards eight Inches long and ſeven foot broad, Deut. 3.11. yea ſo great ſome of them were, that the Greatneſs of the great God himſelf is aſcribed to them, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare Numb. 13.33. with Iſai 40.22. where other men were ſaid to <hi>be as Graſhopppers,</hi> poor, low, contemptible things in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of thoſe <hi>Monſtrous Gyants,</hi> as well as in compariſon of the <hi>Mighty God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that Theology (more noble than Philoſophy) doubteth not to call that Race of Rephaims <hi>Monſters,</hi> ſuch as <hi>great Goli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah,</hi> who could not only bear and wear Weapons which (at the leaſt) weighed above two hundred pounds weight, and walk with them, but he was able to weild them and to War with them. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.4, 5, 6, 7. Oh what a prodigious <hi>Monſter</hi> was this <hi>man,</hi> Arm'd Cap-a-pee, and <hi>ſtalking</hi> in the Field like a <hi>whole walking Armory.</hi> However that Gyant (call'd <hi>[iſh middah]</hi> a man of mighty meaſure) having <hi>twenty four Fingers and Toes.</hi> 2. Sam. 21.20. 1. Chron. 20.25. may well enough be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a <hi>Monster</hi> among men, yet notwithſtanding thoſe two mighty <hi>Monſters</hi> aforenamed went into the Field like Thunder and Lightning (defying the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) they went off (both of them) like ſooty ſmoak, and ſtinking Snuff: Now the God of Nature never ſent any of theſe mighty Monſters into the World, in thoſe ancient times, but it was to <hi>praemonſtrate</hi> that much Rapine, Violence, Arbitrary Oppreſſion and Tyranny ſhould be perpetrated by them amongſt men, as <hi>Nimrod,</hi> that <hi>mighty one</hi> or Gyant (according to the Greek) that <hi>Magnifico,</hi> or Grand Rebel (as Hebr. <hi>Nimrod</hi> ſignifies) and that firſt Babel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builder, was a crafty and cruel Hunter (not ſo much of Beaſts as) of men, whom he ſacrificed to his Luſts, he was the firſt who (after the Flood) ſet up an Arbitrary and Violent Domination o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Men (purſuing thoſe that would not ſubmit to his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Yoak) with no more pitty than Hunters ſhew to Beaſts,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64617:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>which they Hunt for their Pot or Spit: Hereupon Tyranny is in Scripture alluded to Hunting. <hi>Jer.</hi> 16.16. <hi>Lam.</hi> 4.18 <hi>Monſters</hi> in magnitude prove moſtly <hi>Monſters</hi> in manners too, this <hi>Nimrod</hi> who was a <hi>Rebel</hi> to <hi>God</hi> his <hi>Superior</hi> (as his name ſignifies) was alſo a <hi>Tyrant</hi> to <hi>Men</hi> that were his <hi>Inferiours,</hi> haveing a <hi>Belluine</hi> not a <hi>Genuine</hi> greatneſs: and though our preſent Times doth not produce ſuch <hi>litteral Monsters,</hi> as the ancient Times did, yet God knows) we have too many <hi>myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>moral Monſters,</hi> both <hi>Inferiours</hi> who become <hi>Monſters in Iniquity,</hi> (<hi>none ſuch Sinners</hi> and matchleſs among men) and <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours</hi> who become <hi>Monſters in Tyranny,</hi> grinding the Faces of their poor people, both thoſe ſorts of Monſters do <hi>premonſtrate</hi> the Judgments of God againſt them, they are link't together: but above all, the greateſt <hi>Monſter,</hi> that this day affordeth is that Behemoth, that Beaſt of Beaſts, the <hi>Antichr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> who may well be call'd a <hi>Monſter</hi> (according to the Philoſophers definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it) A <hi>Monſter</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>eſt peccatum naturae,</hi> &amp;c. A Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of Nature, wherein ſtrange Members in the Body, and Strange qualities in the Mind, are produced and expoſed to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen view: how well this doth <hi>[quadrare]</hi> and accordeth with the Romiſh Beaſt, appeareth by conſidering two Scriptures. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.7. and <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Daniels</hi> 4th. Beaſt (which was the Roman Power (is not likened to any certain Beaſt (as the other three aforementioned are) becauſe no particular Beaſt (amongſt the moſt ſavage the World bringeth forth) can be named ſo cruel and ſo monſtrous as to expreſs the Cruelty and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſneſs of that fourth Monarchy, no not, although it were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mer</hi> ſaith, a <hi>Lion</hi> before, a <hi>Dragon</hi> behind, and in the midſt a Chimera: 'tis therefore a <hi>nameleſs Monſter,</hi> made up of all the curſed properties of the forenamed Beaſts: This <hi>Beaſt</hi> is ſaid to be <hi>diverſe from all the Beaſts,</hi> not only for its <hi>monſtrous qualities in the mind</hi> (having all and more of all the other Beaſts) but alſo for its <hi>monſtrous Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the Body,</hi> Deſcribed by <hi>Daniel,</hi> and 2ly. by <hi>John.</hi> Revel. 13.1.2.11. Having 7 <hi>Heads</hi> (to <hi>Plot</hi> with) and 10 <hi>Horns</hi> (to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64617:18"/>
               <hi>puſh</hi> with) the <hi>Feet of a Bear,</hi> and the <hi>Mouth of a Lyon, Himſelf like a Leopard,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon giving him Power,</hi> as if all Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Immanity were met together in him; This is the <hi>man</hi> of <hi>Sin,</hi> and the mighty <hi>Monſter</hi> of preſent times, which doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly premonſtrate, nothing can be expected but Barbarous and Savage Out-rages, until <hi>Chriſt</hi> (our true Hercules) come to cut off all the <hi>Heads</hi> of this <hi>Lernean Monſter,</hi> and his Carpenters come to ſaw off all his Horns. <hi>This is that Ahaz,</hi> 2. Chron. 28.22. This is that <hi>Nimrod</hi> (or Rebel againſt Chriſt, even <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ</hi>) of our Day, that <hi>mighty Hunter</hi> (even of the Lives and Souls of men) before the Lord, who dare Hunt thus, in ſpight of an All-ſeeing God, who beholdeth all his bold, boiſterous and brutiſh Huntings, <hi>Ezod.</hi> 3.7. This is that <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,</hi> and <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>Harlots,</hi> that has made ſo many Kings of the Earth drunk, with the Intoxicating Cup, of her (both of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and ſpiritual) Fornications. I have ſometimes wondred why Sir <hi>Edward Cook</hi> (that ſtrenous Lawyer and Lord Judge) uſed to call Royal Prerogative, a <hi>mighty Monſter,</hi> and I cannot tell how to put a ſounder ſenſe on it, than by Interpreting his Words thus; That <hi>Popery</hi> in all Kings and Kingdoms brings forth <hi>Tyranny,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Evil Bird, Evil Egg, as is the <hi>Mother</hi> ſo is the <hi>Daughter;</hi> This Monſtrous <hi>Beaſt</hi> brings forth moſt Monſtrous <hi>Births:</hi> no doubt but there is a juſt <hi>Prerogative</hi> (well butted and bounded) belonging to Kings, yet may it be ſaid of it, as Naturaliſts ſay of the Dragon <hi>[ſerpens ſerpentes vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando-fit Draco]</hi> as when an overgrown Serpent hath devoured other Serpents, that are leſſer and below him, thereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coms a Dragon. So when Royal Prerogative hath ſwallowed both <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliaments</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> or <hi>Property</hi> of <hi>Subjects,</hi> then doth it Degenerate into a <hi>Tyrannical Monſter,</hi> and this is evident in Popiſh Kingdoms, where the King is called a <hi>King of Aſſes,</hi> their Subjects being as ſo many Vaſſals, Peaſants, and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Aſſes, <hi>tamely couching down under every Burden,</hi> that an unlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prerogative Impoſeth on them: As that <hi>Creature</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly Reputed a <hi>Monſter</hi> wherein the common Rules of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64617:19"/>(which never intendeth any monſtrous thing) are prevari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated: ſo this <hi>Prerogative</hi> (that Sage Judge ſo Styleth) may well be accounted a <hi>Monſter,</hi> when there is any notorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varication from the known Fundamental Laws of the Land there y when all Law becomes ſwallowed up with an Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and Arbitrary Domination, and when no rule is obſerved therein, but <hi>Sic Volo ſic Jubco, ſtat pro ratione voluntas.</hi> And <hi>quod libet licet</hi> which are the Propoſals of Popiſh Paraſites to Popiſh Princes, Thus one <hi>Monſter</hi> begets and brings forth another in its own Monſtrous likeneſs. The beaſtly Religion of that Monſtrous Beaſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> both begets and brings forth Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Tyranny, changing <hi>Due Prerogative</hi> into a <hi>true Monſter.</hi> God Almighty bleſs this poor Land from all ſuch Prerogative-Monſters, which have ſo long infeſted <hi>Europe:</hi> Though <hi>Affrica</hi> hath been always accounted famous for affording moſt <hi>Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlers,</hi> according to that old Adage <hi>[Africa ſemper aliquid novi ſen Monſtra Aſſert]</hi> and I find this Story in Record, That in <hi>Africa</hi> near <hi>Nilus</hi> were found a few Mice, only one half made up, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was there taken in the very Nick, how ſhe was prevented from perfecting her Work I know not, yet this (ſaith my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) I know, ſhe had wrought Life in the foreparts thereof (Head and Breaſt) but the hinder parts ſtill remainedunform'd, unquickned, ſtill abiding in the faſhion of a little lump of Earth, and ſo ſhe leſt them; but by the Premiſes it appeareth that <hi>Europe</hi> as well as <hi>Africa</hi> aboundeth with <hi>Monſters,</hi> and not ſo much with monſtrous <hi>Mice which marr the Land,</hi> as 1. Sam. 6.5. Or as <hi>Pliny</hi> writes, with ſuch Mice which drove out the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants out of <hi>Troas</hi> and the Iſland <hi>Gyarus.</hi> Pliny <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 28. and 10. and 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 65.68. Nor with ſuch <hi>Mice</hi> as <hi>Speed</hi> in <hi>Eſſex</hi> mentioneth in the year 1581. (juſt an hundred years ago) which came in a great Army and over-ran the Marſhes of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> Hundred, near unto <hi>South Minſter,</hi> ſhearing the Graſs to the very roots, and ſo tainted the ſame with their venemous Teeth that a great Murrain ſell upon their Cattel that grazed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Alas <hi>Europe</hi> is now Infeſted not only with Land Marring
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64617:19"/>
               <hi>Mice</hi> (which threatneth both a <hi>Famine of Bread,</hi> and a <hi>Famine of the Word</hi> too, Amos. 8.11.) but alſo with monſtrous and Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marring Beaſts, ſuch as are butting puſhing <hi>Rams</hi> and ſlinking nauſty <hi>Goats,</hi> Ezek. 34.17.18.19.20. to wit, the Popiſh Clergy, who eat up the Beſt, and beat down the reſt, with their foul Feet, and for wholeſom, obtrude Brakiſh water upon men, to quench their Thirſt, muzling and miſleading ſome ſilly Souls, to feed upon Traditions, lying Legends, cheating Indulgences, vowed Pilgrimages, hard Pennances, <hi>&amp;e.</hi> They are glad to eat ſuch as they can catch, but other more enlightned Souls as cannot <hi>touch, taſt</hi> nor <hi>handle</hi> with them, <hi>they thruſt with the ſide,</hi> and with <hi>the ſhoulder,</hi> v. 21. <hi>and puſh them with their Horns</hi> of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications and Perſecutions, <hi>until they have ſcattered them ahroad.</hi> They force them out of the <hi>Fold, Flock,</hi> and <hi>Paſture</hi> of Gods Ordinances, adminiſtred in power and purity: in ſuch a caſe <hi>what can the Righteous do?</hi> Pſ. 18.3. They are not able to abide the puſhings of thoſe Monſtrous <hi>Beaſts,</hi> they muſt either <hi>Fly</hi> or <hi>Dye,</hi> they have not a Third for their choice, oh pray, that Chriſt (the good Shepard) may come and <hi>ſave his Flock from being a Prey</hi> to thoſe Monſters, and to <hi>Judge between Cattle and Cattle,</hi> and to <hi>cauſe thoſe unclean Beaſts to ceaſe out of this Land,</hi> and other Lands in <hi>Europe, v.</hi> 22 to 26. The Lion <hi>Nero,</hi> and other Slaughter-Slaves of Satan, aſſuredly ſhall not worry Gods Flock for ever. Tis Gods promiſe <hi>I will cauſe the unclean Spirit</hi> (of the monſtrous Beaſt) <hi>to paſs out of the Land,</hi> Zech. 13.2. But what a deadly Bite this deadly Beaſt may give at paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and parting we know not, <hi>morſus Beſtiae moribundae ſunt maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me mortiferi,</hi> the good Lord give us a good Deliverance from the laſt Bite. The third Predictive Sign or Wonder, is <hi>prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es prodig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> ſome Etymologizeth <hi>quaſi predicium,</hi> becauſe 'tis predictive and prognoſticating: others <hi>quaſi porro agendum</hi> [more and further to do] as a Prodigy portends God hath ſome <hi>more and further great Work to do</hi> in the World: in Greek 'tis cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>terren,</hi> becauſe a Prodigy is an affrightful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. In Hebrew 'tis called [Mopheth] <hi>a Jaſaph Splenduit, fulſit,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64617:20"/>Illuxit,</hi> becauſe <hi>Prodigies</hi> (eſpecially thoſe in the Heavens) have a ſhining ſpendour, which do dazle the Eyes of beholders, and oft Aſtoniſheth their Minds with their ſparkling and ſhining Luſtre. The word [Mopheth] <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.2. Is Tranſlated <hi>por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentum</hi> (<hi>quia Indicat quid porro tendatur,</hi> becauſe it portends ſome further tendency of Providence) though there it be uſed for fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious Wonders, which the Devil (by <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi>) wrought, through Gods permiſſion, for the further hardning of <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s <hi>Heart.</hi> True Portents, Prodigies, or Wonders (that do exceed the common courſe of Nature) are always Gods Seals, which he never ſets on for confirming an untruth: they have (in the general) a perſwading power to believe, and prompting us to awake out of our lazy ſlumbers; hence one wittily compares <hi>Prodigies</hi> expoſed to View, unto a Muſitians firſt ſtrokes upon his Inſtrument, to try in what tune it is: and then he puts forth his moſt excellent dexterity in playing over ſundry choice Leſſons, with moſt melodious and Raviſhing Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick: Thus when the great God doth expoſe his wonderful <hi>Prodigies</hi> unto Publick view, and the knowledge of Mankind, it plainly portends that he therein is tuning his Inſtrument, (as he is the chief Muſitian, according to <hi>Davids</hi> Dedication to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Pſalms) and that he is about to play over ſome emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Acts of Providence (which he will mannage throughout with moſt excellent skill) upon the Stage of the World, even ſuch curious Leſſons, (though conſiſting of Diſcords) which may prove ſad cordoliums to the VVicked, yet ſweet Cordials to the Godly.</p>
            <p>The ſecond particular in this General Diſcourſe, is the <hi>Scene</hi> whereon the great God ſhews his marvelous <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> and where they have their extraordinary ſcituation: whereof we cannot have a better account from any better Hand, than from the ſweet ſinger of Iſrael <hi>Pſ</hi> 135.6. VVhere after he had declared. 1. Gods <hi>Goodneſs, v.</hi> 3. Then 2. Gods <hi>Greatneſs, v.</hi> 5. Yea <hi>greater than all Gods,</hi> either <hi>Deputed</hi> (as Magiſtrates, Pſ. 82.1.6.) Or <hi>Reputed</hi> as Idols Pſ. 115.4.1. Cor. 8.4. He comes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:64617:20"/>to declare what a moſt free Agent, this <hi>good</hi> and <hi>great God</hi> is. <hi>v.</hi> 6. Doing <hi>whatever pleaſeth him,</hi> whereby he confuteth three ſorts of the Truths Adverſaries: <hi>1ſt.</hi> The <hi>Stoicks</hi> that bind Gods Almighty Hands, under a Fatal neceſſity, as if God could do nothing but as ſecond Cauſes do move and oblige him: 2. The <hi>Epicureans,</hi> who dotingly Dream, that God (called <hi>Actus puriſſimus</hi>) is altogether Idle, ſitting in Heaven at his own eaſe, and altogether unconcerned with the Affairs of this low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er World which (they ſay are managed by <hi>chance</hi> and <hi>fortune:</hi> 3. The <hi>Ethnicks,</hi> who confeſs God to be concerned in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt matters of this lowermoſt World, but not with the leaſt of them, ſaying,
<q>Non vacat exiguis Rebus Adeſſe Jovi.</q>
               <q>Jove <hi>is not at leiſure to be preſent at ſmall matters.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David</hi> here doth Demonſtrate the groſſneſs of all thoſe three miſtakes; ſaying, God is always at work, as <hi>John</hi> 5.17. and he works freely what he pleaſeth. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 115.3. and under no <hi>Conſtraint</hi> or <hi>Reſtraint,</hi> no ſecond cauſe can either <hi>help</hi> him or <hi>hinder</hi> him, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the ſeeming Impediments he over-ruleth, and making them ſerviceable to his own irreſiſtible Will: as <hi>Phaorah</hi>'s Daughter is made to <hi>preſerve</hi> Moſes, who was to <hi>Deſtroy Pharoah</hi>'s King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And laſtly, he nameth the three grand Stages or Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters whereon God <hi>worketh</hi> what he <hi>willeth,</hi> both his Ordinary and extraordinary works, to wit, <hi>Heaven Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea,</hi> the great God is concern'd in all things that come to paſs in all theſe; parts of the viſible World: This leads me from the <hi>General</hi> to a <hi>particular</hi> Diſcourſe of thoſe mighty <hi>Signs, Wonders</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies,</hi> which the great God hath very lately ſhewn to the World, upon all thoſe three <hi>Scenes</hi> or <hi>Stages.</hi> And firſt in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> this Mighty God (<hi>Jehovah</hi> not <hi>Jove</hi> or <hi>Jupiter</hi>) is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the <hi>Maker of all Meteors,</hi> Jerem. 10.13. Pſ. 135.7. whether they be Fiery, Airy, or VVatery, and whether they be <hi>Ordinary</hi> or <hi>Extraordinary.</hi> 1. <hi>Ordinary,</hi> 'tis the great God that <hi>cauſeth Vapours to aſcend from the ends of the Earth.</hi> Pſ. 135.7.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:64617:21"/>And Jerem. 10.13. Thoſe Vapours the Sun, Moon and Stars exhaleth out of the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea</hi> (by the Ordinance of the Creator) whereon thoſe uſual Meteors (as <hi>Clouds</hi> either with Rain or without, <hi>Thanders</hi> and the <hi>Rainbow</hi> &amp;c) are made as on their proper matter: This may be exemplified in the <hi>lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle World (Man)</hi> in whom Vapours are experienced to <hi>Aſcend</hi> up from below unto the Brain, and from thence again do <hi>Deſeend</hi> in a Defluxion of Rheum down upon the Lungs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus it is in the <hi>Great World,</hi> as to the <hi>firſt</hi> common Meteor, to wit, <hi>Clouds,</hi> which are moiſt Vapours dra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n up (as is aforeſaid) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the middle Region, where being, by the coldneſs thereof, condenſed and congealed, they ſo continue there, until by the warmth of the Sun they come to be diſſolved and turn'd into Rain. <hi>Zanch. de Op r. Dii. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 381. Hereupon they are called, <hi>Gods Garden-Pat</hi> for watering Plants, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he duly watereth, the wide Garden of the World. Now this, though Common, is one of Gods mighty <hi>Sig s</hi> and <hi>Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> that he ſhould <hi>bind</hi> up ſuch a vaſt <hi>weight of water in his Clouds,</hi> which are nothing but Vapours knit together, and ſo are Veſſels much thinner than the Liquor contained in them, 'tis a mighty Wonder, <hi>that the Clouds are not rent under them,</hi> Job. 26.8. And ſo to cauſe a <hi>Cataclyſme</hi> (or warer Spouts, as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners call them) to drown not only <hi>Ships</hi> at Sea, but alſo the whole <hi>Globe</hi> of the <hi>Earth.</hi> This wonderful work of God, (that ſuch a Maſſy weight of VVater, ſhould be confin'd to a thin Cloud, as if a ſtrong man ſhould be conjur'd into a ſlender Cob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>web, and there be kept <hi>Nolens Vole<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi>) If well weighed, would be ſufficient to convince the greateſt Atheiſt in the VVorld, of an Omnipotent Deity: no meer man can ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft the thinneſt Curtain <hi>[abſque fulcris]</hi> without ſome ſolid thing to uphold it. Yet the great God <hi>ſpreadeth</hi> thoſe thin Curtains (the Clouds) over the whole Face of the Firmament, <hi>Job.</hi> 25.9.36.29. ſuch as have great Floods <hi>bound up,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>in them, as in a Garment,</hi> Prov. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.4. Yet have they no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fluid Air to ſuſtain them; there be alſo <hi>Clouds
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:64617:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>without</hi> water (as well as <hi>with</hi>) which ſeem to carry the leſs VVonder in them: yet if we Conſider, that all Clouds are <hi>Gods Spunges</hi> (as <hi>Zanchy,</hi> that Divine Philoſopher calleth them) which are in time filled with the waters that are above the Firmament, and the true reaſon, why ſome Clouds do Rain up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth, and others doe not, is, becauſe God doth not ſqueeze all thoſe Spunges with his mighty Hand: and thus God ſaith, I will command the Clouds to Rain no Rain upon this or that place. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.7. Thoſe are Clouds <hi>without Rain</hi> Prov. 25.14. For God preſſeth them not, and thoſe which God ſqueezeth (as man doth a Spunge,) he doth it not with all his might, but gently, that they may moderately drop upon the Earth to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh</hi> it, but not to <hi>Ruine</hi> it, as was done to the Old VVorld, when God opened the Cataracts of Heaven and wrung thoſe Spunges <hi>hard</hi> upon them: the Conſideration hereof ſhould bring man to the knowledge of the <hi>Power, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> Rom. 1.19. <hi>Job.</hi> 38.37. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.22. The ſecond <hi>common Meteor</hi> is <hi>Thunder,</hi> &amp;c. This is alſo <hi>Wonderful,</hi> that <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Water,</hi> ſhould mingle in one <hi>Cloud,</hi> and that <hi>Hard Stones</hi> (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the vulgar Opinion) ſhould come out of the midſt of <hi>thin Vapours.</hi> Theſe are <hi>Wonders</hi> in Nature far beyond Humane Apprehenſion, that one and the ſame <hi>Cloud</hi> ſhould one while be an <hi>Aery Sea,</hi> to powr down a whole Tide of VVater, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while, (even immediately) be as ſome <hi>Aery Furnace,</hi> which ſcattereth abroad flaſhes of Fire, into all parts of the Earth, aſtoniſhing the VVorld with the dreadful noiſe of that Erupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that God ſhould fetch <hi>Fire</hi> out of the midſt of <hi>Water,</hi> and hard <hi>Thunderbolts</hi> out of the midſt of ſuch a ſoft Exhalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Cloud is: <hi>Hac ſunt ſane Tremenda, atque admiranda,</hi> no leſs to be Dreaded than Admired: The third <hi>comman Wonder</hi> in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the <hi>Rain-Bow,</hi> fixed upon a watery Cloud, by the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Sun upon it, This is ſuch a wonderful work of God, that the very Heathens feigned it to be the Daught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Thaumantias</hi> (which ſignifies VVonderment. This is a work top-full of VVonders, witneſs <hi>1ſt.</hi> The beautiful <hi>Form</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64617:22"/>and <hi>Faſhion</hi> of it, a Semi-Circle, the ends whereof were never ſeen by any Mortal, but as 'tis terminated by the Horiſon. <hi>2ly.</hi> The <hi>Various Colours</hi> it carrieth exceeding the ſplendour and lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the deepeſt Dye in the World) which have (as ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) their various Significations, as the two grand Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Old <hi>World,</hi> and of this <hi>New</hi> by <hi>Water</hi> and by <hi>Fire,</hi> the watery colour of the <hi>Rain Bow</hi> ſignifying the former, and its fiery colour the latter. <hi>3ly.</hi> The ſeveral Prognoſticks of it, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Scalage,</hi> ſaying, a morning <hi>Rain-bow</hi> portends Rain, but an evening one, fair weather. 4. The <hi>Shape</hi> of it, being that of a <hi>Bow</hi> (therefore called the <hi>Rain-bow</hi>) which yet never ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any man, unleſs it be with <hi>Admiration, Delight,</hi> &amp;c. 5. The <hi>poſture</hi> of it, the <hi>Bent</hi> of the Bow is from the <hi>Earth</hi> and towards <hi>Heaven,</hi> as if <hi>man</hi> were ſhooting at <hi>God,</hi> and not <hi>God</hi> at <hi>man.</hi> This Bow with both ends downwards and its back to Heaven; muſt needs be <hi>[nuntius faediris &amp; ſerenitatis]</hi> an Emblem of Peace, and a meſſenger of Mercy to mankind, for he that ſhoot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth holdeth the Back of his Bow always from him, and this may be the Signification of its third (to wit Green) colour, that is, the merciful preſervation of the VVorld, betwixt thoſe two grand Deſtructions of it, ſignified by its watery and fiery colours aforeſaid. <hi>6ly.</hi> The <hi>unreadineſs</hi> of it, as to any Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Divine Diſpleaſure. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <hi>God hath bent his Bow, and made his Arrow ready,</hi> Pſ. 7.12.13. But here, though the Bow ſeem bent, yet we ſee no <hi>String,</hi> neither do we either read of (as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> well obſerveth) or behold any <hi>Arrow</hi> ordained for this Bow: If he doth ſo at any time, 'tis, (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> there tells us) againſt <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> and not againſt his <hi>People:</hi> The time would fail me to ſpeak of the <hi>Wind,</hi> both Tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and VVhirlwinds (whereof I have ſpoke ſomething of it in my <hi>Crown of a Chriſtian,</hi> in Chapter of Meditation) and of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Meteors,</hi> in the Firmament, that are ordinary products of <hi>Nature,</hi> yet <hi>Marvelous Wonders in Nature,</hi> as to mans Capacity and Apprehenſions; It ſhall ſuffice to ſay only this in <hi>General</hi> at this time, which is no leſs a ſignal and ſingular <hi>Wonder,</hi> that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64617:22"/>out of one and the ſame equal matter (to wit, out of thoſe ſame <hi>Vapours,</hi> which are exhaled out of the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Water</hi>) ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeveral and differing <hi>Meteors</hi> ſhould be engendred by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Power, and unſearchable VViſdom of God.</p>
            <p>Come we now to thoſe that are <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> and confine our ſelves to this paſt year (1680.) only which God hath made <hi>Annum Mirabilem,</hi> a wonderful year, as he did that paſt year (1660) alſo. How thoſe two famous years run in Paralel lines, and yet how that <hi>Congruity</hi> hath alſo its <hi>Diſparity,</hi> is made manifeſt in the Application: The <hi>1ſt. Sign from Heaven</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy</hi> in the Heavens that this VVonder-working God ſhewed to the VVorld, was according (to my now modell'd method) that prodigious <hi>Comet,</hi> or Blazing-ſtar, ſeen all over <hi>Europe,</hi> upon which I have Publiſhed, (for publick good) a little ſtitcht Book of three ſheets, Entituled, A Philoſophical and Divine <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> Blazoning upon this <hi>Blazing-Star,</hi> unto which, I muſt here refer the Reader, for a diſtinct diſcerning of the <hi>Product, Form, Colour, Motion, Scituation,</hi> and <hi>Signification</hi> or <hi>Probable Prognoſticks,</hi> &amp;c. Thereunto <hi>Here</hi> adding this little ſupplement, at this time: This laſt <hi>Comet</hi> (in the year 1680.) was ſo prodigious, that the like hath not been ſeen (for length and breadth of its Train) this 800 years. I have conſulted <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiander</hi>'s Epitome of the Centuries, who (indeed) mentioneth a <hi>Comet</hi> of an unuſual magnitude, a little before the Death of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the <hi>Great,</hi> which (he ſaith) was expoſed to publick view, <hi>[tanti principis obitum Deſtgnâſſe]</hi> as a Prognſtoick of the period of ſo great and ſo good a Prince, <hi>Cent.</hi> 4. <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Cap.</hi> 25. <hi>pag.</hi> 214. And the ſame Author tells of another <hi>Comet,</hi> of a prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious greatneſs, ſhooting his Dreadful Rays above the City <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and reaching almoſt (as he ſaith) from Heaven to that City, which was (as he addeth) to give warning of <hi>Gajan</hi> the <hi>Scythian</hi> and Arrian's Deſign to ſet that great City on Fire, yet through the goodneſs of God (at the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his People in it, that Helliſh Plot (as he ſayth) was moſt graciouſly prevented) and that by an <hi>Apparition of an Hoſt of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64617:23"/>Angels,</hi> which terrified this Curſed <hi>Arian,</hi> from his burning project. See <hi>Cent.</hi> 5. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 19. <hi>Pag.</hi> 89. I would to God the ſame mercy may be ſhown to <hi>London,</hi> for the prayers of many in it. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.32. <hi>Iſay</hi> 65.8. The ſame Author al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo telleth of another <hi>Comet,</hi> in the 6th. Century, which did por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Overthrow of the Metropolis of <hi>Cilicia</hi> by an Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, and much more miſchief done in the Eaſt. <hi>Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 34. and of another Horrible one of an unuſual Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude in <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the Emperors time, which fore-ran that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Butchery the <hi>Hunns</hi> made over moſt of <hi>Europe. Cent.</hi> 6. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. in the year 557. after Chriſt. But I do not find (in my Reading any ſuch prodigious <hi>Comet</hi> (as to its Train) ſave only that one which was the fore-runner of the Turkiſh Monarchy in the 6th. Century, and who knows, but this para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel Blaze may likewiſe preſage the Approach of the fifth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of our Dear Redeemer, who will (ſooner or later) take <hi>to himſelf his great power and Reign.</hi> Rev. 11.17. He will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Divide the ſpoil with the ſtrong,</hi> Iſa. 53.12. He will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be an underling in the World, but will put in for his part which his Father gave him. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2.8. in deſpight of a ſtrong <hi>Turk,</hi> ſtrong <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſtrong <hi>Potentates,</hi> and a ſtrong <hi>Devil,</hi> (who is the Maſter of them all) for his Father will make all his Sons Foes his Footſtool. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.2. and <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.44. He will put down all power that is oppoſite to the power of this <hi>Prince of Glory.</hi> 1. Cor. 15.24. and put them (who now Creſt it high againſt Chriſt) into the fitteſt place for them, to wit, under <hi>Chriſts Fect.</hi> Tis beyond doubt, that this preſent <hi>Comet,</hi> put <hi>Rome</hi> into a ſtrange Conſternation; oh pray, pray, pray, that the Influence of it may conſume all the dreggs of the Roman Church, in all that <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſts</hi> Dominions, as <hi>Kep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerus</hi> foretold long ago, ſhould be the effect of that Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in <hi>Leo,</hi> a ſign of the Fiery Trigon. And the reaſon why ſuch an Effect was expected, may be this; The various Returns of thoſe eminent Trigons, fall out very rarely in the World. Acute <hi>Tychobrahe,</hi> thus reckons
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:64617:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>them. The firſt was under <hi>Enoch.</hi> The ſecond under <hi>Noah.</hi> The third under <hi>Moſes.</hi> The fourth under <hi>Solamon.</hi> The fifth under <hi>Chriſt, Tabernacling in Fleſh.</hi> Then the Roman Empire was in its Zenith or higheſt Advance: The ſixth under <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, when the <hi>Roman</hi> was turned into the <hi>German</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and the ſeventh draweth nigh, which is ſuppoſed to have a Sabbatiſm (as the Sabbath of Reſt, followed the 6 Days la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour at the Creation) in its Womb. Our Bleſſed [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or] Maſter of the Marriage Feaſt, reſerveth his beſt Wine for this laſt time: Although (that Univerſal Schollar) <hi>Alſted</hi> make a little variation of thoſe 6 aforeſaid Conjunctions and Revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, yet he fully agreeth with <hi>Tychobrahe</hi> in this, that the ſeventh great Revolution of the ſuperior Planers, falleth upon our laſt times, and doth certainly portend ſome great and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal mutation (as all the other ſix hath formerly done (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering that thoſe Planers in their ſeventh Return, hath perfectly compleated their circular Motion, and then are in the ſame point and poſture that they were placed in at the <hi>Creation</hi> of the VVorld. <hi>Alſteds</hi> Encupl. Uranoſc. Lib. 11. Pag. 125.</p>
            <p>That which ſtartled the great men of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo much, at the Blazing out of this <hi>Comet,</hi> was, the Mathematicians there ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it to be in the Train of it, ſix times longer than that which did portend the laſt Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII. <hi>Exit</hi> out of the World: This Diſcovery put the preſent Pope into ſuch a cold paroxyſm, that nothing but a Dutch Stove could keep him warm: I doubt not but that cold Sweat which hath ſeized now upon all the Limbs of Antichriſt, will (in due time carry off, not only him, but ſuch as ſhould ſucceed him, by the <hi>Breath of Chriſts Mouth,</hi> and by <hi>the brightneſs of his coming.</hi> 2. Theſ. 2 8 A <hi>prodigious Comet,</hi> and a <hi>Climacterial Conjunction</hi> (Aſtrologers ſay) are a double Seal of the great God, to aſeertain this great Truth.</p>
            <p>In that leſſer <hi>Conjunction</hi> of the two ſuperior <hi>Planets,</hi> in the year 1664. The <hi>Comet</hi> followed the Conjunction as a <hi>Seal,</hi> for
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64617:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>Confirmation that dreadful Effects were portended thereby, which not only this Land (in Fire, Plague and Plots, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) but alſo moſt of <hi>Europe</hi> (in moſt Deſolating Wars) ſmarted under, but as to the Total, Greateſt, or Clymacterical <hi>Conjunction</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching (which cometh to paſs only every 800. year) this hath as its Seal) a <hi>Dreadful Comet</hi> as its [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binger going before it, and ſhewing it ſelf firſt to awaken and amaze the Drowzy Secure World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> However we (well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) may call it a <hi>Divine Preacher</hi> (or Preco) ſent from God, to point out ſome ſacred Truth out of <hi>Heaven,</hi> to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants upon <hi>Earth;</hi> 'tis an <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and Authentick Preacher, backed with ſuch inſuperable Authority, as neither the proud <hi>paſhur</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor any of his popiſh <hi>Prelates,</hi> can <hi>ſuſpend</hi> from its Office, or put to <hi>Silence,</hi> until it hath delivered its meſſage, and done its Work, that its Creatour gave it to do: It cannot be obſcured (in its aſtoniſhing light and luſtre) or dwindle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by any created Hands, but only by the hands of its own Maker. And now when it is gone off the Stage, Oh that the loud <hi>Sermons</hi> it hath preached, may ſtill <hi>Sound</hi> in our <hi>Ears,</hi> and <hi>Sink down</hi> into our <hi>Hearts,</hi> taking deep Impreſſions there, though it be a good while after, as did thoſe <hi>Sermons</hi> loudly and luſtily cryed out by Chriſts <hi>Cryer,</hi> or <hi>Fore-runner (John the Baptiſt)</hi> who did <hi>lift up his Voice like a Trumpet,</hi> Iſa. 58.1. and thoſe ſacred Truth, he had preached long <hi>before,</hi> had their bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and ſaving <hi>Effect,</hi> long <hi>after,</hi> as John 10.41. The Word preached ſometime <hi>before,</hi> ſometimes Works, (and that conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable) <hi>after.</hi> Yea, may we not ſay of this <hi>late Comet,</hi> that it was ſome <hi>Prince-Peracher,</hi> having ſuch Attendants before it and after it) all, as ſo many <hi>Curats</hi> under it, God himſelf (ſpeaking to <hi>Job</hi> out of the Whirlwind, <hi>Job</hi> 38.1.) doth magnify <hi>Arcturus</hi> that Star of the firſt magnitude, and that always <hi>Riſeth</hi> upon the <hi>10th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> exactly when the <hi>Sun</hi> Setteth) by deſcribing how Stately he is attended with his <hi>Sons</hi> (the little Stars) that wait upon him. <hi>Job</hi> 38.32. In like manner the great God, hath ſo Ordered, that this late Blazing-Star (of a prodigious
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64617:24"/>Magnitude in its Train) ſhould have other Apparitions attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (as ſmall <hi>Curats</hi> to that Illuſtrious Preacher the <hi>Comet</hi>) eſpecially that <hi>Fiery Dart</hi> which followed its extinction, within a few weeks after: This is the ſecond <hi>Phaenom non</hi> or <hi>Apparition,</hi> which the great God ſhewed to poor man as a <hi>Sign</hi> from <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> ſeeing none ſhewn on <hi>Earth</hi> will convince us, it being with us as it was with thoſe <hi>Chriſt-Tempters</hi> in the Goſpel. <hi>Luke</hi> 11.16. They muſt have a <hi>Sign</hi> from <hi>Heaven,</hi> over and above all thoſe mighty and matchleſs Miracles that Chriſt wrought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them upon <hi>Earth;</hi> They muſt have the Meſſiah to Thunder from Heaven upon them, as <hi>Samuel</hi> had done upon their Forefathers. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.16.17. to convince them of their Sin (in <hi>asking a King</hi>) and to bring them to <hi>Repentance:</hi> for as <hi>Johns</hi> Baptiſt, was Chriſts Fore-runner into the <hi>World,</hi> ſo <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> muſt be his <hi>Fore-runner</hi> into Mens <hi>Hearts, Houſes,</hi> Cities and Countries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore to bring men to it, when they will not comply with the Council of Mortal Miniſters up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth (as thoſe would not with that of <hi>Samuel</hi>) God ſends ſome <hi>Signs</hi> Extraordinary from <hi>Heaven,</hi> ſeeing <hi>[ſigna de Caelo ſunt Formidanda]</hi> ſuch Signs as God ſends from Heaven are moſt formidable: <hi>Samuel</hi> bids that people <hi>firſt ſtand and Hear, v.</hi> 7. that is, <hi>Buſtle not, Briſtle not,</hi> but ſuffer a word of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13 22. When this would not do (the good old man being contemned by them, both in his perſon, preaching and power) he ſet GOD at work to ſpeak to them by <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> and then <hi>Samuel</hi> ſaith, <hi>Secondly Stand</hi> and <hi>ſee, v.</hi> 16. that ſo thoſe two <hi>Learned Senſes</hi> (as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> calls <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Seeing</hi>) being both <hi>Affected,</hi> might be alſo <hi>Inſtructed:</hi> ſo God ſaith likewiſe <hi>Heartye Deaf, look ye Blind,</hi> Iſa. 42.18. Thus the Lord ſaith to us in our Day, ſo gives us not only the <hi>Word to Hear,</hi> but alſo <hi>Signs to ſee,</hi> and that one Sign upon another, <hi>that they which will not Hear the Voice of the firſt Sign, might be moved to hear the Voice of the ſecond,</hi> Exod. 4.8. Therefore did God ſend a <hi>ſecond ſign</hi> (the <hi>Bolis</hi> or <hi>Fiery Dart</hi>) immediately after the <hi>firſt,</hi> (to wit, the <hi>Comet</hi>) as a Seal annexed to it, in its direful <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64617:25"/>and <hi>prognoſticks:</hi> 'Tis true I cannot ſay of this latter, as I can of the former, that <hi>[<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſce Oculis Vidi]</hi> I ſaw it with my own Eyes, but ſundry ſpectators of it doth aſſure me, that it was a <hi>long ſtr am of Fire,</hi> pointing down towards the Earth, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing but two or three nights, which was the cauſe of my not beholding it; Letters alſo from the <hi>Hague</hi> and from <hi>Copenhagen</hi> give a dark account of this Blaze, about the 27th. of <hi>February:</hi> This Liery Lance or Dart, Philoſophers calleth <hi>Bolis,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit,</hi> to Caſt, as if it were Gods Javelin which he caſteth at ſinful men, as <hi>Saul</hi> did his againſt <hi>David.</hi> 1. Sam. 18.11. The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew word [chanith] ſignifies alſo a very long Spear to thruſt through at diſtance, yet no mortal man is armed with ſo long a killing Spear, as the <hi>great God</hi> is, no not <hi>great Goliah</hi> (himſelf) whoſe [chanith] or Spear was of a prodigious length and thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Sam. 17.7. It was 26 foot in <hi>length,</hi> and like a Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Beam for <hi>thickneſs,</hi> beſides its <hi>head,</hi> which according to the Hebrew [lahab] <hi>Flamed</hi> and which weighed twenty five pound: yet this long Flaming Spear is nothing to <hi>Gods Glittering Spear,</hi> Habb. 3.11. Which he <hi>draweth out,</hi> to <hi>ſtop the way of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Perſecutors,</hi> Pſ. 35.3. Where the word [chanith] is uſed. And although the great God is able to cut off the Greateſt men with a bare <hi>nodd of his Head</hi> or <hi>frown of his Face,</hi> Pſ. 80.16. Yea to blow them away as ſo many ſmall Duſt-Heaps, <hi>Job</hi> 4.19. Yet the Holy Ghoſt here atributeth to him, <hi>Armour</hi> both <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive</hi> and <hi>Ofenſive,</hi> that his appearing for his people might appear ſufficient, Pſ. 35.2, 3. Notwithſtanding God needs no bigger a [chanith or] <hi>Lance to kill an Atheiſt with than an Hair,</hi> as the dying Noble-man once acknowledged upon this occaſion: He ſitting in the Great <hi>Moguls</hi> Court, dallying with one of his Miſſes, ſhe pluck't an Hair out of his Breaſt, this little Wound, (made by that ſmall means) preſently Feſtered, and turning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an incurable Canker ſoon killed him: yea, ſuppoſe, <hi>man</hi> be as great as the Great <hi>Pope,</hi> yet <hi>Adrian</hi> the IV. (an Engliſh man) can tell them by woful Experience, that though his name (before he was Pope) was <hi>Break-ſpear,</hi> yet could he not <hi>break</hi> Gods Spear,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64617:25"/>though it be no ſtronger then an <hi>Hair</hi> or <hi>Fly</hi> (in Gods Hands) wherewith he was Choaked: The word [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <hi>Jaculum.</hi> A Dart, is uſed Heb. 12.20. Yet it alſo ſignifies that Plummet of Lead which Marriners caſt down with a long Line to plum the depth of the Waters, leaſt the Ship run upon the ſhallow and there be ſhut up in the Sands and be broken; or which Carpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters uſe, to meaſure and mark out that part which they intend to Hew off or Plain. If we take it (in the firſt Sence) as a Fiery Dart, Philoſophy ſaith, it ſignifies Drought, and portends War. <hi>Alſted</hi> Encyclop. Lib. 7. Cap 9. Pag. 469. If (in the ſecond) as <hi>1ſt.</hi> The <hi>Mart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers</hi> Plummet, then it may ſignify God is ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Depth of Religion in our Land, Oh that the <hi>Ship</hi> (the <hi>Church</hi>) may not be found upon the <hi>ſhallows</hi> running all Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into a <hi>Form</hi> only, denying the <hi>Power</hi> of it. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. Alas then the Quick Sands will ſwallow us up, or we ſhall run upon ſome ſplitting Rock. <hi>2ly.</hi> As the <hi>Carpenters</hi> Plummet, then God Bleſs us from the dreadful Divine Threatning menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned 2. <hi>Kin.</hi> 21.13. That God <hi>wip</hi> not our Jeruſalem (or <hi>London</hi>) as one <hi>wipeth</hi> a Diſh when tis dirty, and <hi>turn it upſide down.</hi> This he will do, <hi>If he lay judgment to the Line and Juſtice to the Plummet.</hi> Iſa 28.17 This ſhould make wicked mens (who ſhall certainly have their Due) <hi>Ears tingle,</hi> and their <hi>Hearts tremble,</hi> through Terror, Horror and Dolor, for God will not give over wiping untill all the Dirt be done away; yet loveth he to fore-ſignify it, thus threatning that he may not ſtrike, as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>broſe</hi> obſerveth, God giveth us many warnings hereof, If God ſay to us as he did to <hi>Amos</hi> ch. 7.9. <hi>What ſeeſt thou?</hi> The ſight of this ſecond Apparition was, as Gods <hi>Line</hi> and <hi>Plummet,</hi> to meaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut how much is to be cut off, yet the <hi>Square Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> or <hi>Stone</hi> ſhall be ſpared: Chriſt (that Skilful Carpenter, <hi>Mark.</hi> 6 3) will not cut an Hair-breadth beyond his Mark or Meaſure, when he gives the wicked their Due, it may be done without damage to the Godly. May we but ſee the <hi>Line</hi> or <hi>Plummet</hi> once in the <hi>Hands of our Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ls,</hi> as Zech. 4.10. The Perpendicular put once into Parliamentary Hands, the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64617:26"/>wicked may be pulled down, and the Godly built up. But if nor, and God <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon our Iniquity.</hi> Pſ. 130.3. We can expect nothing but the <hi>Line of conſuſion,</hi> and the <hi>ſtones</hi> (or <hi>Plumm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi>) of <hi>Em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Iſa. 34 11.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> Dreadful [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,] or <hi>Apparition</hi> in the Air, was on <hi>Dec</hi> 17. 1680. at <hi>Ottery</hi> nigh <hi>Exeter,</hi> near 5 at night, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared two great <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mies,</hi> the one out of the <hi>North,</hi> whoſe Leader had a Coronet on his Head) the other out of the <hi>South,</hi> ſeeming furiouſly to joyn Battle, and a little Retracting, charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed again moſt vigorouſly, this continued about an hour, till at laſt there came a Reſerve and joyning with the <hi>Southern,</hi> beats back the Northern in great Diſorder, many were Tertified at it, and 'tis as true as it was terrible, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Account came from a Reverend Miniſter, who (with many others) was an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs of it, while viewing the <hi>Amazing Comet,</hi> as publiſhed in Print.</p>
            <p>And the like before had appeared on <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. Though the Relation and Confirmation thereof, came not to Hand till <hi>Jan.</hi> 14. after. The ſame year near <hi>Portſnet,</hi> in <hi>Monmouth-ſhire,</hi> as the <hi>Scheme</hi> and Letter Teſtimonial of a judicious Miniſter of that Place, doth abundantly Teſtify: The Narrative is as follows.</p>
            <p>The firſt things that appeared were a <hi>Grove of Trees,</hi> a <hi>Houſe</hi> on a <hi>Mountain,</hi> and a <hi>Church</hi> on its South-ſide. Next we ſaw a Hill on the North ſide, with a Grove and Houſes therein. Then we <hi>noted</hi> a green ſquare Meadow, between the two Hills, then void of men. We ſaw many great Rocks towards the bottom of the South Hill, and a great Golden Globe, glittering gloriouſly on the top of the Spire of the <hi>Church,</hi> and a red <hi>Vane</hi> upon it. Then a great River broader on the North than on the South, in which were Ships Sayling, from <hi>North</hi> to <hi>South</hi> under the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with the Tide, where one of the Ships which was hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt tacked about, and Sailed through the Fleet, and got before the reſt. Then we obſerved the other Fleet Sayling with the Wind and againſt the Tide, from the South Point of the South Hill, and then meeting the other Fleet under the Grove, then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64617:26"/>the great Ship in the North Fleet, firſt ſhot, and the reſt in or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der; then the South Ships ſhot at them, the Fire and Smoak we clearly diſcerned, and we heard the noiſe of Guns, after this we obſerved the Army marching under the foot of the Hill along the Cliff, by the Sea-ſide; conſiſting both of Horſe and Foot, from the South-point of the South-hill, towards the Square Meadow, then the North Army over the top of the Hill on the North-ſide, towards the ſquare Meadow, where the Armys met, and after a ſhout, fought: the Swords and Pikes we cleerly diſcerned. We noted more Ships in the North Fleet, and moſt men in the South Army, when we drew to the upper end of the Field, and after the Land Battle, we heard o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Heads three lamentable and ſad Groans, Oh, Oh, Oh, at which we were much affrighted.</p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Apparition</hi> of <hi>Armys</hi> (yea and ex abundanti of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vies</hi> too) was doubled as was <hi>Pharoah</hi>'s <hi>Dream:</hi> Gen. 41.32. on a three fold account, <hi>1ſt.</hi> To ſhew the <hi>certainty</hi> of its Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks accompliſhment. <hi>2ly.</hi> The <hi>celerity,</hi> or ſpeedineſs of theſe things coming to paſs. <hi>3ly.</hi> To ſtrike the greater <hi>Terror</hi> and <hi>Aſtoniſhment</hi> in right thinking minds, which <hi>Joſeph</hi> the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretor of the 2 Dreams) prudently concealed from that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidel <hi>Pharoah,</hi> yet though the Viſions or <hi>Apparitions</hi> (in the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Dreams) were two, the ſignification was but one. <hi>v.</hi> 25. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting one and the ſame matter; Thus it may be in this <hi>Aery Apparition</hi> (which was doubled) as it is thus alſo in many <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations,</hi> whereof we find in Scripture ſome ſrequent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, which yet have their ſingular uſe, to wit, a making more deep Impreſſion upon the minds of Men, and importing both <hi>Aſſurance</hi> and <hi>Expedition</hi> of the matters foretold therein: Alas we need <hi>Line upon Line,</hi> and <hi>Precept upon Precept, Here a little</hi> and <hi>there a little,</hi> Iſa. 28.13. and all little enough to praepon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate the <hi>dulneſs</hi> of our <hi>Hearing,</hi> and the <hi>deadneſs</hi> of our <hi>Hearts: to write the ſame</hi> things to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> though 'twas <hi>grievous</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> yet was it <hi>ſafe</hi> and advantagious to the <hi>People.</hi> Phil. 3.1. Twas not a vain Repetition or an idle Tautology, but
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64617:27"/>ſerved to ſet forth the <hi>Neceſſity, Difficulty</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi> of the matter ſo reinforced. <hi>Nunquam ſatis Dicit, quod Nunqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Diſcitur,</hi> Truth is never enough ſaid, till it be enough learnt. And becauſe mens Breaits are Brawny, and their Heart-ſtrings Horny, therefore are the <hi>Apparition</hi> of Armys in the Air <hi>Doubled</hi> upon us, the more and better to beat upon, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate and imprint thoſe Divine warnings in the minds of men: Upon my diligent Search for Scriptural Paralells, and exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of Apparitions of Armys, I do find three eſpecially: The <hi>firſt</hi> of them is very <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> yet ſuch as might have been prevented by a timely and true Repentance: the other are very <hi>comfertable:</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> is that of <hi>Joel</hi> the Prophet who had ſuch a Prophetieal Viſion or <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arition</hi> of the <hi>Bab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>am</hi> Armys, that ſhould ſo ſwarm in upon <hi>Judaea,</hi> as to make that very Day a <hi>Day of Darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>of Gloomineſs</hi> a <hi>Day of Clouds and of thick Darkneſs.</hi> Joel 2.2. As if it had been (no light matter as they made it, but) a light-leſs Day, and (as it were) a <hi>doleful Dooms-day.</hi> Their numerous Armys ſhould come in great Swarms, which, as the Cloud of Locuſts would Darken the Air, ſo as to turn Day into Night and ſpread far and near all the Country over, and that ſo ſuddenly, as the <hi>morning</hi> ſpread over the tops of the <hi>Mountains:</hi> and in this <hi>Apparition Joel</hi> boheld Flames and Flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Fire, <hi>burning up all before them.</hi> v. 3. Thoſe <hi>Locuſt,</hi> ſhould ſo conſume the Country, as they go along with their vaſt Armys (as if all had been burnt up by Fire) turning the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Eden <hi>into a Barren Wilderneſs</hi> &amp;c <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. wherein the <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians</hi> are Deſcribed. <hi>1ſt.</hi> In their perſons to be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, numerous, ſwift, terrible, skilful orderly couragious</hi> and <hi>Innumerable. 2ly.</hi> In their <hi>Actions,</hi> to wit, <hi>Depopulating</hi> the <hi>Land</hi> (which occaſioned Famine,) <hi>Deſtroying</hi> their <hi>ſtrong Forts,</hi> and <hi>filling</hi> all (both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi>) with Confuſion.</p>
            <p>The Lord God Almighty preſerve this Land from ſuch <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and ſuch <hi>Actions.</hi> Oh pray, pray, That God may not <hi>Hiſs</hi> for the <hi>Fly of Aegypt,</hi> and for the <hi>Bee of Babylon.</hi> Iſa. 7.18. for thoſe <hi>Flys</hi> would <hi>Bite</hi> us, to <hi>disturbus in our peace,</hi> but thoſe <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ees</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64617:27"/>would ſting us to <hi>deprive us of our lives.</hi> God Bleſs us from thoſe Romiſh <hi>Locuſts</hi> (ſo called <hi>Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 9.3) to wit, the Popiſh Prieſts, Monks, Fryars and Jeſuites, being (all) both <hi>numerous</hi> and <hi>voracious</hi> Creatures. Oh that ſuch Peſtilent Vermin may never have Commiſſion from God to <hi>Marr our Land:</hi> As the Prophet propoſed Repentance as a Remedy (before the Decree brought forth) to them. <hi>v.</hi> 12.13.14. ſaying, <hi>now,</hi> though it be <hi>late,</hi> yet not too <hi>late,</hi> Nunquam ſerô ſi ſeriô. Though <hi>ſome Locusts</hi> be already come, as <hi>Kimchy</hi> ſenſeth it. So your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting for Sin,</hi> be but proportionable to your <hi>Rebelling againſt GOD.</hi> So ſweet is his <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo <hi>gracious,</hi> ſo <hi>merciful,</hi> ſo <hi>flow to Anger,</hi> &amp;c. He will <hi>Repent of the Evil,</hi> and <hi>who knoweth, if he will not leave a Bleſſing behind him.</hi> Yea he will <hi>certainly turn to thoſe that turn to him.</hi> Zach. 1.3. Oh that <hi>England know ſuch things as belonged to her Peace.</hi> Luke 19.42. Before the Gate be ſhut, the draw-bridge taken up, and the Taper of Mercy be quite burnt out, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then God would ſend out his <hi>Mandamus:</hi> Pſ. 44.4. and come with his <hi>Non Obſtante,</hi> Pſ. 106.8. and Iſa. 57.15. Yea and <hi>turn</hi> things to the contrary, as in <hi>Hamans</hi> Day. <hi>Eſt.</hi> 9.1.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> Inſtance of a Scripture <hi>Apparition,</hi> is that of <hi>Jacob.</hi> Gen. 32.1. Which was not <hi>Terrible,</hi> but <hi>Comfortable</hi> to him, for it was not a viſible <hi>Apparition</hi> of Armys of men fighting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, but 'twas an <hi>Army of Angels:</hi> neither muſt we think (with the Hebrews and ſome others) that one Troop or Company of thoſe Angels (which appeared as armed Soldiers) were for <hi>Jacob</hi> and the other againſt him, or yet that thoſe two Armys appeared under the command of two diſtinct Generals, the <hi>one</hi> under the Preſident Angel of the Country of <hi>Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> (from whence <hi>Jacob</hi> was coming) and the other under the Preſident Angel of the Country of <hi>Canaan</hi> whither <hi>Jacob</hi> was now returning: this is a preſumptuous fancy, and as falſe as preſumptuous, for this would have rather affrighted than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted <hi>Jacob,</hi> as to the Iſſue, but we find that <hi>Jacob</hi> without any fear, ſaid upon the firſt ſight of it <hi>[This is Gods Hoſt]</hi> v. 2. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanaim,</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:64617:28"/>Hebr. or two Armys: The Hebrew Rabbies ſay well in this, that <hi>Jacob</hi> in this third Apparition knew them to be the <hi>ſame Angels</hi> whom he had ſeen (in his Apparition) <hi>Aſcending</hi> and <hi>Deſcending</hi> upon the lofty Ladder. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12 The Scope of this Apparition of Armys to <hi>Jacob</hi> was to ſtrengthen his <hi>Faith</hi> in the way of his <hi>Obedience: Jacob</hi> was now going whether God had commanded him to go. <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.3. <hi>Labans</hi> lowring look, makes <hi>Jacob</hi> look homeward (Oh that the Frowns of the World had this bleſſed effect on us) <hi>Laban</hi> purſues him, which put <hi>Jacob</hi> to a fright. <hi>v.</hi> 25. But God had whiſpered a word in <hi>Labans</hi> Ear. <hi>v.</hi> 24. So was better to him than his own Fears. God had ſpoke for him (and ſo he can for us) in the Heart-of his Enemys. Now, 'twas not true that <hi>Laban</hi> ſaid [<hi>it is in the power of my Hand,</hi> &amp;c.] v. 9. <hi>Jacob</hi> was now as one that Fled from a <hi>Lyon</hi> (<hi>Laban</hi> had ſome ſhamefacedneſs) and a <hi>Bear</hi> (that had none) to wit, <hi>Eſau</hi> met him, <hi>ſaith</hi> a Rabby, This Apparition of an <hi>Hoſt of Angels</hi> came to fortify his Faith, againſt his next and worſt Fear; that he ſhould now hope the ſame power which had protected him from the <hi>Lyon Laban,</hi> would alſo preſerve him from the <hi>Bear Eſau,</hi> though he had ſworn his Brothers Death, and came armed with 400 Cut-Throats (at his Heels) againſt him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacob</hi> (who in his excellent Wraſtlings) had <hi>power with God and prevailed.</hi> Gen 32.26. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could not want power to <hi>prevail with men.</hi> Hoſ. 12.4. Let <hi>Perſons,</hi> yea <hi>Parliaments</hi> go but that way God bids them as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, and they ſhall not want a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hanaim,</hi> or Heavenly Hoſt to <hi>convoy</hi> them through a boiſterous Sea, where the Winds are <hi>contrary.</hi> Math. 14.24. and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct them through a wayleſs Wilderneſs, through never ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Prophane <hi>Eſau</hi>'s, with Hundreds and Thouſands of Cut-Throats do way-lay them: <hi>Jacob</hi> was back-ſet by <hi>Lowring La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> and fore-ſet by <hi>bloody Eſau,</hi> yet this Hoſt of Angels carry him through both and all.</p>
            <p>The third Scripture Inſtance of <hi>Apparitions</hi> of Armys, was that in 2. Kings 6.17. which was a <hi>comfortable Apparition</hi> alſo,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:64617:28"/>being an <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> too, not of <hi>Men. Benhadad</hi> ſuſpected his Councellor of Treachery: Some Courtier (that had been with <hi>Naaman</hi> ch. 5) tells him, it was <hi>Eliſha</hi> that diſcloſed his Secrets, and ſo fruſtrated them by his Prophetick Spirit; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King ſends Horſes and Chariots to fetch him. <hi>v.</hi> 12.13.14. as ſoon his Spys brought him Word, he was come to that little Town <hi>Dothan;</hi> the Town is preſently begirt with the <hi>Syrian</hi> Army. <hi>Gehazi</hi>'s Succeſſor (being yet but a little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with his Maſters Miracles) could ſee the <hi>Danger</hi> (ſo crys, <hi>alas my Maſter, what ſhall we do. v.</hi> 15.) but could not ſee the <hi>Deliverance, Eliſha</hi> was no more concerned than to have his Servants Eyes opened, (that his <hi>Faith</hi> alſo might be above his <hi>Fear</hi>) God opened them, and then he ſaw better Horſes and better Chariots for their <hi>Defence;</hi> Their <hi>Remedy</hi> would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match their <hi>Malady, v.</hi> 17. The ſame <hi>Horſes</hi> and <hi>Chariots</hi> that had carried up <hi>Elijah,</hi> were now come to protect <hi>Eliſha,</hi> from the Horſes and Charriots of <hi>Benhadad: Horſes</hi> and <hi>Chariots</hi> of <hi>Fire,</hi> muſt needs be too hard for the <hi>Syrians of Fleſh: Eliſha</hi> thus guarded, goeth out to his Adverſaries, and as he prayed open his Servants Eyes, he prayed his Enemies Eyes into blindneſs. <hi>v.</hi> 18. ſo led them thence to <hi>Samaria,</hi> where he entrapped <hi>them,</hi> that thought verily they had entrapped him in <hi>Dothan,</hi> not far from <hi>Samaria. v.</hi> 19.20. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> While the Prophet ſtaid in <hi>Samaria</hi> (his place of chiefeſt Reſidence and the chief City of the Kingdom) he was ſecure from the Syrians Aſſaulting him, but if he be Removed to <hi>Dothan</hi> (to a place of deſection, as the Hebrew word ſignifies) a leſſer Town of leſſer ſtrength, there and thither may the <hi>Syrian</hi> Hoſt better Aſſemble, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Aſſault, the P. is ſafe there alſo, <hi>having more for than againſt, v.</hi> 16. They <hi>that be with us are more than they be with them.</hi> 2. Chron 32.7. more Friends than Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>There is yet a <hi>fourth</hi> Scripture <hi>Apparition</hi> of Armys, which, according to the Sentiments of ſome, is an <hi>Army of Men,</hi> but of others an <hi>Army of Angels,</hi> ſo ſeems a mixture of both, to wit, <hi>Zech.</hi> 6. from <hi>v.</hi> 1. to 9. <hi>1ſt.</hi> Some ſence that Apparition of 4.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64617:29"/>Charriots, to ſignify the four Empires <hi>[in ordine ad Eccleſiam]</hi> all ordered from their Riſe to their Ruin (in each of them) by the Decrees of God, which lay hid as it were in Mountains of Braſs, and ran like a River under ground, till they broke forth, and ſhewed themſelves in their due execution, with reſpect (all along to the Church of God. And if we admit of this Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, then this Apparition was an <hi>Army of Men,</hi> yea of four ſeveral ſorts of Men, The <hi>Aſſyrian,</hi> The <hi>Perſian,</hi> The <hi>Grecian</hi> And the <hi>Roman.</hi> Thus the four Empires (<hi>coliectively</hi> taken) muſt be underſtood: But the <hi>ſecond</hi> Senſe is, that it was an <hi>Apparition</hi> of four <hi>Squdaron</hi> of <hi>Angels,</hi> and this is more probable, as more agreeable to the Interpretation which the Prophets-<hi>Tutor</hi> (rather than <hi>Tutelar Angel</hi>) gives of it. v. 5. calling them the <hi>Spirits of Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. And though the word [Ruachoth] Signify <hi>Winds,</hi> by which <hi>Daniel</hi> prefigures the four Monarchys, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.2. Yet more emphatically, <hi>Angels</hi> are called Spirits. <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.7.14. And the <hi>Spirits of Heaven,</hi> Math. 24.36. and Gal. 1.8. Who as <hi>Miniſtring</hi> Spirits doe <hi>Stand before the Lord of the whole Earth.</hi> Mat. 18.10. To ſerve his Providence and to be ſent out (as his Agents and Inſtruments) upon various Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, at his pleaſure: and therefore are they Deſcribed here <hi>Gods Chartots,</hi> as Pſ. 68.17. and of diverſe colours, 1. <hi>Black,</hi> when their Errands are <hi>Sorrowful.</hi> 2. <hi>White,</hi> when <hi>Joyful. 3ly. Red,</hi> when <hi>Bloody.</hi> 4. <hi>Grizled,</hi> when mixt of both <hi>Joyful</hi> and <hi>Sorrowful,</hi> as to contrary Subjects. 'Tis very Remarkable here. 1. That Divine Decrees are unſearchable, inſuperable, unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, unremoveable, they ſtand like <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>Braſs,</hi> which can never be removed: <hi>2ly.</hi> All <hi>Humane Events</hi> are ordered in the World by <hi>Divine Decrees:</hi> Therefore tis our part to put our <hi>Amen</hi> to Gods <hi>Amen;</hi> and to ſay in the Language of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians <hi>(the will of the Lord be done)</hi> Act. 21.14. 3. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> are Gods Agents for moveing the wheel of Providence, in all Events, The Spirit of the living Creatures is in the Wheels. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 1.20. and 10.9.11.13. 'Tis a Comfort to <hi>Holy Men,</hi> that all Occurrences are managed by the <hi>Holy Angels,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64617:29"/>4. The Work God Employs <hi>Angels</hi> to work in the World, is various work, 'tis <hi>Black</hi> work and <hi>White</hi> work, <hi>Red</hi> work and <hi>Mingled</hi> work. 5. Their <hi>Black</hi> work is upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> and their <hi>White</hi> work is upon <hi>Sion:</hi> The <hi>Black</hi> Horſes were ſent to deſtroy <hi>Babylon,</hi> that lay North of <hi>Judea,</hi> and the <hi>White</hi> Horſes were ſent after them into the ſame Northern Country to deliver <hi>Sign,</hi> which then in a great part lay among the Pots in <hi>Babylon.</hi> 6. Their grizled or mingled work, was upon <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bia,</hi> which lay South from <hi>Judea,</hi> the Puniſhment whereof was ſomewhat mixed and mitigated, they ſhould be in ſome better caſe than <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet not ſo good as to retain the Jews there from their own Country. 7. Their <hi>Black</hi> work done upon <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> is ſaid to <hi>quiet Gods Spirit.</hi> v. 8. To <hi>eaſe him of his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries,</hi> Iſa. 1.24. to pacify his Anger and to give God full con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. 8. The Errand of the <hi>Red</hi> Charriot, is wholy omitted, probably becauſe 'tis a work reſerved for the laſt times, as the Black Charret did deſtroy <hi>Babylon Literal,</hi> ſo the red Charet (not mentioned as to its going out here) may be Reſerved to deſtroy Babylon Myſtical, and to give her Blood to Drink, for ſhe is worthy. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.6.9. After all this is done, comes in the Kingdom of the Branch. <hi>v.</hi> 12. Thus the <hi>Prophet</hi> here concurrs with <hi>Daniel,</hi> who after he had mentioned the downfal of the four Monarchys brings in the <hi>Kingdom of the Stone,</hi> Dan. 2. (the Kingdom of Chriſt our dear Redeemer) <hi>Daniel</hi> had ſuch <hi>Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of mighty things, as <hi>Zachary</hi> had.</p>
            <p>The fourth fearful <hi>Phaenomenon</hi> was that fiery flying Bullet, falling from the Firmament, whereof this Account from <hi>Roſtock</hi> in <hi>Silecia</hi> is given, that in <hi>Jan.</hi> laſt, the Heavens ſeemed to be Ruffled up like a ſheet of Paper, at which time a white glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Bullet</hi> appeared, which ſeemed to yeild ſome drops of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, being attended with two great flaſhes of Lightning; The <hi>Bullet</hi> was ſeen (by many ſpectators) to fall down, but none of them could tell where it fell, only in this all do unanimouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agree, that the ſaid <hi>Bullet,</hi> in its ſaling, gave a greater light in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Houſes than the greateſt lights they burned for three
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64617:30"/>or four Miles round the place. I know not how to Exemplify this <hi>Apparition</hi> with a more ſuitable Paralel, out of Scripture Record, than with <hi>Zachary</hi>'s <hi>Flying Roll:</hi> Chap. 5.1.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Roll is called a Volumn, or a Scroll of Paper or Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, rolled up (as the Heavens ſeemed to be in this <hi>Prodigy</hi>) yet <hi>Flying</hi> and flecting ſwiftly all a long as a Bird of Prey in a ready poſture to ſeize on his Prey. <hi>Volans Velociſſimum ultionis incurſum denotat.</hi> This very poſture of Flying doth demonſtrate ſome ſudden Incurſion of Divine Vengeance, ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> but God only knows where it will fall: <hi>Nemo ſcelus gerit in pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctore, qui non idem Nemeſin in Tergo.</hi> No man can carry any di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh wickedneſs in his Breaſt, but the ſame man muſt bear Nemeſin (ſo was the Goddeſs of Revenge called) or Divine Vengeance upon his Back. This the blind Heathens could ſay, by the light of Nature, into whoſe <hi>Hearts</hi> the <hi>Remarks</hi> how the Holy God Revengeth himſelf upon wicked men, caſt a greater light, than could this Flying Bullet, into the <hi>Houſes</hi> of thoſe <hi>Villages</hi> which were enlightned with it. Hereupon they called Vengeance <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifies <hi>unavoidable,</hi> becauſe no Offender can either <hi>Avert</hi> or <hi>Avoid</hi> the Revenging hand of God, there is no eſcaping its coming, nor abiding it when it cometh: This Flying Roll is deſcribed by the Prophet to be <hi>ten yards long</hi> and <hi>five broad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Remarkable Meaſure of the Flying Roll is <hi>1ſt.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſurate to the <hi>Porch of the Temple,</hi> which is exactly deſcribed to be of the ſame <hi>Breadth</hi> and <hi>Length.</hi> 1. Kin 6.3. And as it bore a proportion in meaſure to the <hi>Porch,</hi> ſo it may be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to come out from thence, as a <hi>Voice from the Temple.</hi> Iſa. 66.6. And unfolding as it came thence, it appeared in the Air in a Flying poſture, haſtning and hovering over the Heads of wicked Perſons. <hi>2ly.</hi> It bears likewiſe a proportion to the Land of the <hi>Jews,</hi> which Geographers Deſcribe to be twice as <hi>long,</hi> as it was <hi>broad,</hi> and now it being covered all over <hi>with the Guilt</hi> and <hi>Filth</hi> of <hi>Mens Sins,</hi> it was ready to be covered all over <hi>with the ſence and ſmart of Gods Judgments. 3ly.</hi> 'Tis commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurate
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64617:30"/>alſo to the whole <hi>World of Gentles,</hi> the length whereof, (take it from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt</hi>) much exceeded the breadth of it from <hi>North</hi> to <hi>South,</hi> as Geography obſerveth, and thus it ſignified that as all the Habitable Lands had <hi>filled</hi> themſelves with all kind of <hi>Sins,</hi> ſo God would now fill them with all kind of <hi>puniſhments:</hi> 'Twas every way large enough to plague all ſorts of Sins, and to puniſh all ſorts of <hi>Sinners,</hi> whether in every corner of <hi>Judea,</hi> or in the utmoſt parts of the Habitable World. Thus the Flying Roll is ſaid to <hi>go forth,</hi> yea Fly (more ſwiftly than the <hi>Eagle,</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or a Flaſh of Lightning) <hi>over the Face of the whole Earth, v.</hi> 2.3. And the <hi>Curſe of God</hi> (contained in the Roll within and without) is as the <hi>Fiery Bullet,</hi> that burns on all ſides, being like <hi>Ezekicls</hi> Book, filled with ſuch contents as <hi>Lamentation</hi> and <hi>Mourning,</hi> and <hi>Woe,</hi> Ezek. 2.9.10. This <hi>Curſe</hi> of <hi>God</hi> when it falleth upon the People of <hi>Gods Curſe,</hi> Iſa. 34.5. hath a more mighty and mortal fall than the bulkieſt Bullet in the World, far beyond the Burthen of that mountanious Bullet, which (Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory telleth us) was ſhot out of that monſtrous murdering-piece, called Grand Diabolo, or the <hi>great Divel:</hi> Inaſmuch as the mighty Hands of the Almighty and All-Creating <hi>God in Heaven,</hi> can give a greater and more fatal Blow, than can the created Hands of the greateſt <hi>Divel in Hell.</hi> This is the <hi>Fiery Bullet</hi> that <hi>Droppeth</hi> the <hi>bitter Water which cauſeth the Curſe.</hi> Num. 5.18. and which will make the <hi>Thigh to Rot,</hi> and the <hi>Belly</hi> to <hi>Swell. v.</hi> 21.23. Neither let any man ſay, that the <hi>Curſes</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in <hi>Gods Book,</hi> are but Bug-bears, and that <hi>words</hi> are but <hi>wind,</hi> as <hi>they ſaid,</hi> Jer. 5.13. for the words written in that Book (or Hebrew <hi>Scroll</hi>) ſhould cauſe the waters thus to work, which (in themſelves) had neither any diſcerning Virtue, nor any deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Vigour, yet the Divine Inſtitution made the ſame potion, either Poyſon or Medicine, according to the cleaneſs or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſs of the party: Thus alſo Gods <hi>Word</hi> which Scoffers call but <hi>Wind,</hi> yet may have Dreadful Effects, for even <hi>Wind,</hi> when gotten into the <hi>Bowels</hi> of the Earth, may cauſe an <hi>Earth-quake,</hi> ſo this Word of the Curſe, when gotten into the <hi>Bowels</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:64617:31"/>of a mans mind, may make an <hi>Heart-quake.</hi> Beſides, that very <hi>Word</hi> which thoſe <hi>Mockers</hi> made light off as <hi>Wind,</hi> ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Fire,</hi> and themſelves <hi>Fuel</hi> to feed it. Jer. 5.13.14. And as <hi>Fire</hi> ſlyeth upon <hi>Fuel</hi> that is fully dryed, and conſumeth it in an inſtant, <hi>Nah.</hi> 1.10. So Gods <hi>Flying-Roll</hi> will lick up wicked Livers, as that <hi>Fire</hi> from <hi>Heaven</hi> did the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> the <hi>Wood,</hi> the <hi>Stones,</hi> and the <hi>Duſt,</hi> with all the <hi>Water</hi> in the <hi>Trench,</hi> 1. Kin. 18.38. <hi>Divine Threatnings,</hi> in Gods Flying-Roll, are (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſaith of <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.18.) <hi>Fulmina potiùs quàm Verba.</hi> Hot Thunderbolts, rather than ſuch <hi>Words as be but Wind</hi>) The ſame God that hath denounced it, will certainly do it, he will ſee his own Law Executed. <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.4. and will (himſelf) <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the Judgment written in this Roll:</hi> Pſ. 149.9 Yea and more <hi>than is written:</hi> Deut. 28.61. Upon the Head of the <hi>Thief</hi> (great as well as ſmall, as the <hi>Pyrate</hi> told <hi>Alexander</hi>) under which is compriſed all other Sinners againſt the ſecond Table; and upon the Head of the <hi>Swearer</hi> (comprehending all againſt the firſt) God hath Sworn that Swearers ſhall not enter into his Reſt. We live in the Dreggs (the laſt and worſt) of Times, wherein Blaſphemous Oaths, are belched out of Black Helliſh Mouths, both ordinary and openly, yea ſome Oaths are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Rhetorical Inrerjections of Speech to the Vulgar ſort, and other ſome meer Phraſes of Gallantry to the Damme-Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants: but <hi>mark the end.</hi> The direful <hi>Curſe</hi> comes flying with a Divine Commiſſion breaks into the Houſes of thoſe <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Swearers</hi>) which they call their <hi>Caſtles,</hi> wherein they think themſelves out of the reach of Gods Rod) there it <hi>remains</hi> as a troubleſome Inmate in deſpight of them, they cannot rid or remove this curſing Roll, untill it hath not only <hi>ſauced their Meat</hi> and <hi>ſpiced their Drink,</hi> with the <hi>Wrath of God,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> 20.23. but until alſo the Fire thereof hath <hi>kindled the Brimſtone that lay ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered upon their Habitations,</hi> Job 18.14.15. This puts their All into a light Flame, conſuming both <hi>Timber</hi> and <hi>Stones,</hi> their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and their Eſtates, which they have raked together by Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine, Sacriledg, Perjury, and other wicked ways: Such <hi>Balls</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:64617:31"/>of <hi>Fire</hi> (Reſembling this Flying Roll, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) have been ſeen fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Heaven (Gods Temple) upon <hi>Woods, Ground,</hi> yea <hi>Houſes</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> The bigneſs of which <hi>Fire Balls,</hi> have ſeemed to Spectators as large as the greateſt Chaldrons, theſe muſt be predictive <hi>Signs</hi> to us, as <hi>Jeremys</hi> Boyling-Pot was to the <hi>Jews,</hi> Jer. 1.13. and as <hi>Ezekiels</hi> was, Ezek. 24.3.4.13. Repreſenting <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> which then had a <hi>mighty Scum in her,</hi> but the Fire of Gods Wrath ſet the Pot on boyling (by the <hi>Chaldeans</hi>) until it had boyled out all the <hi>Bones</hi> and the <hi>Fleſh</hi> (the <hi>Stouteſt and Richeſt</hi>) at which they had Scoffed. Ezek. 11.3.7. But when they go <hi>to the Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and boyl luſtily there, their Scoffs are forced back down their own Throats, and their Hearts might then beſpeak them, as the Heart of the Tyrant <hi>Apollodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> (who dreamed he was taken and flead by the <hi>Scythians,</hi> and boyled in a great Chaldron) did, cry out of the Kettle or Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron to him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 'tis I that am the Cauſe of all this thy Miſery. No leſs a <hi>Sign</hi> was <hi>Ezekiels Iron Pan,</hi> to the Hard-Hearted <hi>Jews.</hi> Ezek. 4.3. both which Hieroglyphicks and Emblems did not only ſignify, their City ſhould be hardly Beſieged, but alſo that God would ſo <hi>ſeeth them in a Pot,</hi> and ſo <hi>fry them in a Pan,</hi> as that they <hi>ſhould pine away in their Iniquitys.</hi> Levit. 26.39. The good Lord <hi>Divert</hi> this ſore Judgment from <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Direct</hi> it to <hi>Rome</hi> or myſtical <hi>Babylon,</hi> for ſhe is <hi>worthy.</hi> Revel. 16 6.</p>
            <p>The <hi>fifth wonderful Signs</hi> in the Heavens, is, the <hi>Several Suns</hi> that have been ſeen in the Firmament, at ſome due diſtance one from another, as hath been Teſtifyed to me: but I ſhall not Inſiſt upon this, (as I have upon the former) not only becauſe my Book begins to ſwell beyond my Expectation, but alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have reſolved to enlarge upon nothing, no nor inſert here any thing upon ſlender Evidence, without evident and ſufficient Teſtimony: It ſhall therefore ſuffice to ſay but little to this, ſave only, that ſuch an Apparition need the leſs to be doubted of, ſeeing natural Phyloſophy mentioneth it, as one of Natures Products, though not ordinarily, calling them <hi>parelia</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:64617:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>or Mock-Suns: yet that Divine Philoſopher <hi>Zanchy,</hi> doth not only (in concurrence with Heathen Philoſopers) ſuppoſe ſuch Apparitions to prognoſticate abundance of wet weather, but alſo (as he ſaith further) various Judgments, as Famine, Sword, <hi>&amp;c. Zanch. de Oper. Dei. Pag.</hi> 348. Yea our own Engliſh Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicles tell us, that ſuch an Apparition was ſeen in the Heavens in the beginning of Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Reign as there had been the like before, to preſage the Death, of that inſolently proud Prelate, <hi>Thomas Becket</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, both time and room (and it may be Credit too) would fail me, ſhould I inſert the other Apparitions in the Air (we hear off if not ſee) as the Dreadful Thunders and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, the Impetuous Wind and Whirlwinds, and many ſtrange Meteors which I deſignedly omit, until I get better prooff, (which I truly deſire from all good Hands) well knowing my Brethren that went before me, in this Work 20 years ago, ſome do blame for <hi>credulity: Alterius perditto mea fit cautio.</hi> The Cenſure paſſed upon my Predeceſſors (in the like work) for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over <hi>Credulous,</hi> hath been cogent to make me a little the more <hi>Cautelous:</hi> Therefore I paſs on to the ſecond <hi>Scene</hi> or Theatre, whereon God ſhews his <hi>Wonderful Signs</hi> or <hi>Prodigies,</hi> to wit, <hi>on the Earth</hi> (as well as the firſt in the Heavens or Air) And firſt of the Prodigious <hi>Hail-ſtones,</hi> which God caſt out of the <hi>Air,</hi> down to the <hi>Earth,</hi> which cannot be called Apparitions in the Air (and ſo belong to the firſt Scene) ſeeing their prodigious bulkineſs could not be diſtinctly diſcerned, until they appeared (faln, taken up, and meaſured) upon <hi>Earth.</hi> This ſame <hi>Prodigy</hi> or <hi>Wonderful Sign,</hi> happened upon the 18th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1680. which became ſo miſchievous to all the Sky-Llights, all over <hi>London, &amp;c.</hi> and knockt down many Rooks, by their vaſt weight, and bigneſs, ſome of them (being meaſured) were found ſeven Inches about, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Sign alſo may be exempli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied both out of <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Hiſtory. <hi>1ſt. Sacred</hi> and <hi>1ſt.</hi> The Plague of <hi>Hail ſlones</hi> upon <hi>Aegypt,</hi> Exod. 9.18. to 27. Such as <hi>that Land never ſaw or felt before,</hi> for this ſeventh <hi>Plague</hi> was:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:64617:33"/>1ſt. More <hi>General</hi> than any, being over the whole Land at once. 2ly. None ever was ſo <hi>Temper'd with Fire which ran along the Groun.</hi> v. 23. Though Fire and Hail be of two contrary Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, yet in this they made a Peace betwixt themſelves, that they might obey the Will of their Creatour. This was a ſtrange mixture, and a <hi>Miracle</hi> within a <hi>Miracle,</hi> ſaith <hi>Rab. Solomon:</hi> ſuch Hail-ſtones and Coals of Fire mingled together are menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 18.13.14.15. and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.30.31. as here and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.47.48. and <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.32.33. 3ly. None ever ſo punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally <hi>Predictied</hi> and as punctually <hi>Performed,</hi> according to the Prediction. <hi>v.</hi> 18.23.24.25. 4ly. None ever ſo <hi>Deſtructive</hi> to <hi>Man, Beaſt</hi> and <hi>Trees,</hi> v. 25. Pſ. 66.46.47.48. and 105.33. 5ly. None ever ſo <hi>Distinguiſhing</hi> though it was over all the Land of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> yet the Land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> (a part of it) was <hi>exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> v. 26. Such an Exemption (was that Torrent of Fire which ran down from <hi>Mount Aetna</hi>) vouchſafed to thoſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Children, which ventured to Reſcue their Aged Parents, from thoſe fearful Flames, made <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſay, [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] It extorted from him an acknowledgement of Gods good Providence for the Godly here on Earth, when he ſaw the Flames of Fire, dividing themſelves and making a Lane for thoſe Godly Reſcuers of their Helpleſs Parents. The ſecond ſacred Inſtance of Prodigious <hi>Hail-Stones.</hi> Joſh. 10.11. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the like exemption or diſtinction (as that in <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.26.) 'tis ſaid [the Lord caſt down great Stones from Heaven] ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained there <hi>[beebeni Habarod, Hagedeloth]</hi> ſuch huge Hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones as brained the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> but hurt not the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that were not only at their Heels, but alſo mingled amonſt them as they flew them in their Flight and dreadful Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning came along with thoſe <hi>Hail-ſtones</hi> alſo, as not only <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> ſaith, but <hi>Habaccuck</hi> likewiſe <hi>Habbac</hi> 3.11. Where God ſhot off his ſhining <hi>Arrows,</hi> and darted from him his <hi>Glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Spears,</hi> yea he level'd them (whether Huge <hi>Hail ſtones,</hi> or Hot <hi>Thunderbolts</hi>) with ſo even an Hand to their ſeveral marks, that he <hi>hit the one and miſſed the other,</hi> even when they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64617:34"/>were intermingled together: this was <hi>Digitus Dei.</hi> 2ly. <hi>Civil Hiſtory</hi> mentions ſtrange <hi>Hail-ſtones,</hi> both <hi>Ethnicks,</hi> as <hi>Livy</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cad. 1. Lib. 1. and Decad. 3. Lib. 10. <hi>Claudian,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick,</hi> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> Lib. 5. <hi>Tertullian</hi> Cap. 5. Apolog. And <hi>Dio</hi> in the Life of <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> (the Philoſopher ſo called) who fought againſt the <hi>Quades,</hi> and by the prayers of the <hi>Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>on</hi> (as in <hi>Aurelius</hi> the Emperors time they were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) of Chriſtians, <hi>Ingens Gr ando complur aque fulmina in Hoſtes Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciderunt,</hi> &amp;c. Such huge Hail-ſtones, and hot Thunderbolts falleth upon the Enemy doth that Heathen Hiſtorian ſay, as if he had been an Eccleſiaſtick Writer) and Fire and Water did fall down from Heaven, the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and their Party drank of the water and were Refreſhed, but the <hi>Quades</hi> (their Enemies) were Burnt by the <hi>Fire</hi> and Periſhed, while it fell not at all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the other, or if it did, it was preſently quenched. Neither did the <hi>Waters</hi> Relieve the <hi>Quades,</hi> but Inflame them, as if it had been Oyl, ſo that they called for Water to cool them, when the water fell upon them, yea and wounded their own Bodies, to quench their burnings with their own Blood: many more ſuch ſtrange Stories have we in the <hi>Magdeburg Centuriſts</hi> and in <hi>Oſtanders Epitome</hi> (too long to Relate) I add only that out of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rerius</hi> (the Jeſuite) who tells us of a moſt grievous <hi>Hail</hi> ſhower in <hi>France</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> Son to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, which was ſo prodigious in the weight and bulk of the Stones, that it ſlew both <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Beaſt,</hi> and at that time a peice of <hi>Ice</hi> of 12 foot long, fell with the Hail out of the Air, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If there be ſuch Wonders in a Hail-ſhower, 'tis the leſs Wonder that God propoſeth this great Wonder to <hi>Job,</hi> asking him, <hi>[Haſt thou ſeen the Treaſures of the Hail, which I have Reſerved againſt the time of Trouble, as the Day of Battel and War.]</hi> Job 38.22.23. Shewing that the Inſpection and Adminiſtration of all theſe marvelous Meteors, do only belong to the <hi>Great God,</hi> he hath vaſt <hi>Treaſures</hi> of them, many Arrows laid up in his Quiver (which can never be emptied, as the <hi>Poet</hi> ſaith of <hi>Joves</hi>) againſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time for Puniſhing his Adverſaries, then he brings forth
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64617:34"/>his <hi>upper</hi> and <hi>lower</hi> Troops (as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> Phraiſe it) ready preſt for his Service, and this he will do againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> againſt which God hath a moſt Dreadful Shower of <hi>Hail-ſtones,</hi> Revel. 16.17.18.21. where the ſeventh Plague upon <hi>Aegypt</hi> is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the ſeventh Plague upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet this latter far worſe, as more weighty than the former, every Hail-ſtone weighed a <hi>Talent,</hi> far bigger than thoſe that Brain'd the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiſh Kings. Joſh.</hi> 10. See my <hi>Church-Hiſtory</hi> pag. 507. When our <hi>Joſhua</hi> or bleſſed <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſhall come forth Conquering and to Conquer the World (as that Typical <hi>Joſhua</hi> did <hi>Canaan</hi>) he hath a worſe Shower of Hail-ſtones wherewith to knock down not only all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rooks (that would Rook us of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Religion) but alſo to Brain all the Grandees of the Earth, that lend their Power to uphold the tottering Whore of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon; thoſe prodigious <hi>Hail-ſtones</hi> ſhall drop down out of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> and deſcend upon the <hi>Earth.</hi> Revel. 20.9 as if both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to deſtroy Chriſts Enemies, as they had done <hi>Davids</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Pſ. 18.13.14.15. and the <hi>Churches</hi> Iſa. 30.30.31. <hi>Such as never were ſeen upon Earth.</hi> Revel. 16.18.</p>
            <p>The ſecond <hi>Wonderful Sign</hi> upon <hi>Earth,</hi> is that ſtrange <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition</hi> to the <hi>Maid</hi> at <hi>Hatfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="relation">
                        <head>Elizabeth Freemans <hi>Relation, taken before Sir</hi> Joſeph Jordan <hi>Kt. and</hi> Richard Lee <hi>D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to his Majeſty, and Rector of</hi> Hatfield, <hi>on</hi> Jan. 31.80.</head>
                        <p n="1">I. SHE ſaith, That <hi>Jan.</hi> 24. Sitting by the Fire ſide about 5 in the Evening (which was its conſtant time of appearing) ſhe heard a voice behind her, mildly ſaying, Sweet-heart! She turning back, ſaw the appearance of a Woman (as ſhe thought, all in white, with a white Vail, ſo that ſhe ſaw no Face, but a very white Hand was laid on the back of her Chair) which ſaid to Her; The 15th. of <hi>May</hi> is appointed for the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Blood to be Poyſoned, and further ſaid, be not afraid, for I am ſent to tell thee. II. That on <hi>Jan.</hi> 25. coming home, it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in White and Vail'd, as before, ſaying, Do you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:64617:35"/>what I ſaid? ſhe Anſwered, yes. She farther ſaid, <hi>In the Name of the Father Son and Holy Ghoſt, what art thou?</hi> It immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately appeared in a very glorious ſhape, with a very Beautiful Face, and with a Crown on its Head: and harſhly ſaid, Tell K. <hi>Charles</hi> from me, not to remove his Parliament, and ſtand to his Council, and charging her to obey its Command, to which ſhe anſwered, yes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> III. On <hi>Jan.</hi> 26. It came again, ſhe being at home, and her Mother perceiving her troubled, ſaid Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeeſt thou any thing? ſhe not being able to ſpeak, nodded her Head and waving her Hand: the Mother ſaid, ſhall I go out? ſhe being enabled to ſpeak, and the Apparition nodding to her, ſhe ſaid, yes. The Mother going out, the Apparition bid her do her Meſſage: ſhe anſwered, I will, ſo ſoon as God ſhall enable me, it ſaid be not afraid, and ſo Vaniſhed. IV. It appeared <hi>Jan.</hi> 27. at a Neighbours Houſe, but <hi>ſpake not.</hi> V. It appeared again at home, as formerly, <hi>Jan.</hi> 28. her Mother and two Neighbours being preſent, ſeeing her begin to be troubled, they all kneeled down to Prayer, it commanded her to do her Meſſage, ſaying, the Lord will go with you, but the perſons by did neither hear nor ſee it. VI. <hi>Jan.</hi> 29. It appeared as ſhe was praying, but <hi>ſaid nothing.</hi> VII. Again the 30th. it appeared, but <hi>ſaid nothing.</hi> VIII. <hi>Jan.</hi> 31. It appeared to her again at her Brother-in-Law's Houſe, being in a very glorious ſhape, as on the <hi>Tueſday</hi> before, and ſaid, God hath ſent me to bid you do as he hath commanded you. &amp;c. IX. It appeared on <hi>Feb.</hi> 1. again, in white, but <hi>ſaid nothing.</hi> X. <hi>Feb.</hi> 2. The day ſhe came to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> it appeared again, and commanded her to bid K. <hi>Charles</hi> keep to his Nobles, and them he takes to be his Enemies, and keep the Parliament in the City. XI. <hi>Feb.</hi> 3. She being at <hi>Whitehal,</hi> could not be admitted to ſpeak to the King: as ſhe was coming back faw the Apparition in white, but it <hi>ſaid nothing.</hi> XII. On the ſame day it appeared again, and ſaid, You have done your endeavour to the utmoſt that God hath commanded you, you ſhall be troubled no more.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Feb.</hi> 9th. This Maid, accompanied with Sir <hi>Joſeph Jordan,</hi> Dr.
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:64617:35"/>
               <hi>Lee,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wilkinſon,</hi> her Mother and others, attended the King and Council, where his Majeſty asked her many Queſtions, and heard her Relation patiently, after which bidding her Go home and ſerve God, and ſhe ſhould ſee no more ſuch Viſions; or to that effect, and ſo ſhe was diſmiſſed. Yet about the middle of <hi>April</hi> 81. She Relates, that the Viſion hath appeared again to her, and hath commanded her once more to preſent her ſelf to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>The firſt grand Enquiry, is whether this <hi>Apparition</hi> were a <hi>good</hi> or an <hi>Evil Angel.</hi> Anſwer, 1. In general: A <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Apparition</hi> of <hi>Inviſible Spirits,</hi> is preternatural, and therefore a Prodigy, whether the Spirit that appears be good or bad: 2ly. Learned men give this Character of Diſtinction betwixt the Apparition of a <hi>good</hi> and of an <hi>evil</hi> Angel. That the <hi>good</hi> always appear in the ſhape of <hi>Beautiful Perſons</hi> or <hi>Clean Creatures;</hi> as, of a Lamb to <hi>Clement,</hi> of an <hi>Hart</hi> to <hi>Euſtace,</hi> and of a <hi>Dove</hi> to <hi>Gummarus, &amp;c.</hi> But the <hi>Evil</hi> Angels Appear as <hi>Deformed men,</hi> or as <hi>Filthy Beaſts.</hi> Thus the Devil appeared to an Aſſembly of Witches in the Shape of a <hi>Stinking Goat,</hi> and of a filthy Hog, in theſe Churches of <hi>Agatha,</hi> propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Arrians. Thus Satan (ſoon after his Fall) took the likeneſs of a <hi>Serpent,</hi> and is call'd ſo, yea a <hi>Dragon,</hi> and thus he is ſaid to appear in the ugly ſhape of all loathſome Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to <hi>Hillary, Anthony,</hi> &amp;c. As <hi>Athanaſius</hi> and <hi>Hierome</hi> in their ſuppoſititious Relations have Reported. yea, ſome do further ſay, <hi>Hoc eſt admodum mirahile nunquam Viſos eſſe Daemones utroque pede Humano ull<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bi apparuiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Saith <hi>Fornerus</hi> De Angelis Serm. 9. 'Tis a very Wonderful thing ſaith he, that Devils never are ſeen appearing any where in mans ſhape, with both Feet alike, but either with one Foot cloven, or with a whole club Foot. All this ſeems not an infalibly diſtinguiſhing Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter: for, 'tis true, the great God can put ſuch diſcriminating Brands upon ſuch deceitful Apparitions, of Evil Spirits, and poſſibly doth often mark them ſo: yet this will not hold Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally true, for that <hi>Devil</hi> who can (as the Scripture of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64617:36"/>Truth ſaith) <hi>turn himſelf into an Angel of Light.</hi> 2. Cor. 11.14. may alſo Tranform himſelf into the ſhape of ſome <hi>comely Man,</hi> or <hi>lovely Beaſt:</hi> 3. That which the Apoſtle <hi>there</hi> affirmeth, was <hi>then</hi> taken for granted among the Learned (ſuch as <hi>Pauls</hi> oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers deemed themſelves) and this was acknowledged by <hi>Porphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Jam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lichus,</hi> &amp;c. That the Devil (the Prince of Darkneſs) could Transform himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light,</hi> either by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to himſelf a lightſome, comely and glorious Body, as if he were an <hi>Angel of Heaven,</hi> or by ſuggeſting ſomething that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to ſavour of Piety and Zeal for God, as if it came from ſome bleſſed Angel, whereas his ſuggeſtions (as he ſuggeſteth them) do indeed tend to <hi>Gods D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhonour</hi> and the <hi>Souls Ruine.</hi> 4 The Character that even <hi>Porphyry</hi> giveth <hi>Satan</hi> (calling him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) one of many Forms and Faſhions, doth Evidence, that it was the Opinion of the Ancients, how he doth not always appear in one and the ſame Form, but hath as many ſeveral ſhapes as <hi>Proteus</hi> had among the <hi>Poets:</hi> This is made more manifeſt in the Hiſtory of the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles,</hi> as, firſt at <hi>Lyſtra</hi> he appeared as a <hi>Comedian,</hi> as if a Scene of <hi>Plautus</hi> were to be Acted upon the Stage, <hi>Act.</hi> 14.11.12. &amp;c. Secondly, at <hi>Antioch</hi> he appeared like a <hi>Jeſuite</hi> with <hi>Traditions</hi> in his Mouth. <hi>v.</hi> 26. and <hi>Act.</hi> 15.1. Thirdly at <hi>Athens,</hi> he ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes out like a <hi>Philoſoper,</hi> Act. 17.18. Fourthly, at <hi>Epheſus</hi> he takes the likeneſs of a Maſter-<hi>Artiſicer.</hi> Act. 19.24. And fifthly, ot <hi>Corinth,</hi> he tranforms himſelf into an <hi>Angel of Light.</hi> 2. Cor. 11.14. with <hi>Act.</hi> 18.6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In all thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the Devil Acted the parts of all the aforeſaid, though he did not viſibly aſſume their ſhapes. <hi>5ly.</hi> As to the latter Times touching viſible Apparitions; <hi>Severus Sulpitius</hi> in the Life of <hi>Martinus,</hi> chap. 25. gives this Account, that Satan appeared in the form of a good Angel, among other Apparitions to <hi>Anatho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> a young Monk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He telleth how the Devil appeared to St. <hi>Martin</hi> (ſo called) as he was praying in his Monaſtick Cell, the apparition ſeemed very glorious, ſparkling with a dazeling light, having upon it Royal Robes, upon its Head a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:64617:36"/>Golden Crown beſpangled with Jewels, upon its Feet gilded Shoes, and with a benign Aſpect out of a comely mouth ſpake as followeth [<hi>Oh Holy</hi> Martin, <hi>acknowledg me whom thou beholdeth, I am Chriſt coming down to the Earth, and I would firſt manifeſt my ſelf to thee,</hi> &amp;c.] and the Apparition oft Repeating thoſe Words, the man <hi>(Martin)</hi> Anſwered, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> had no where foretold, he would come again in <hi>ſo glittering and glorious a poſture</hi> (upon Earth) <hi>before the last day.</hi> I will not believe that it is <hi>Chriſt</hi> (who is come now to me) unleſs he <hi>appear</hi> in the ſame <hi>Form and Habit</hi> wherein he <hi>ſuffered,</hi> and having his five <hi>Wounds</hi> wherewith he was <hi>ſtigmatized upon the Croſs;</hi> upon this Anſwer the Devil va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed out of ſight, leaving an horrible ſtink behind him, as ſaith the Author. <hi>See him</hi> of ſundry other Stories of the like Deluſions: and <hi>Johan. Wierus de praeſtigijs Domonum</hi> Lib. 11. Cap. 16. 6. There is another Character whereby the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of an <hi>Evil Angel</hi> to us may be diſcerned from that of a <hi>good one,</hi> which <hi>Peter Thyreus</hi> Lib. 4. of Apparitions, Chap. 16. Numb. 17. mentioneth, ſaying [The Diſcourſe of a <hi>good Angel</hi> doth at the beginning affright a perſon, but afterwards leaves that mind <hi>quieted</hi> and <hi>comforted,</hi> but on the contrary, when an Evil Angel appeareth and diſcourſeth them, 'tis pleaſing and inſinuating at the firſt, but it ever leaves the mind diſturbed and in <hi>little eaſe</hi> at the end. The ſame Sign doth <hi>Pineda</hi> give, in his Notes upon <hi>Job,</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 16 This alſo is no Infalible Note, but a falacious Sign alſo, for the Apparition of a good Angel <hi>1ſt.</hi> To <hi>Sampſons Mother</hi> was no way affrightful to her, but rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, encouraging her to run to her Husband, to acquaint him with the glad Tidings, <hi>Judg.</hi> 13.3.6. Neither was her Husband terrified with this Apparition, ſpeaking boldly to it <hi>[art thou he which ſpake to the Woman]</hi> v. 11. Though after his departure, a Trembling Seiz'd upon <hi>Him,</hi> through want of Faith <hi>v.</hi> 22. not upon <hi>her,</hi> whoſe Faith was ſtrong <hi>v.</hi> 23. and <hi>2ly.</hi> The Apparition of an <hi>Evil Angel</hi> (or <hi>Devil</hi>) to <hi>Saul</hi> (as the <hi>good Angel</hi> was <hi>Chriſt</hi> to <hi>Sampſons</hi> Parents, <hi>Jud</hi> 13.22.30. cal'd <hi>Elohim</hi> and Jehovah) did drive the King into a Swoon. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:64617:37"/>28, 20 preaching to him his Funeral Sermon, yet at the <hi>cloſe</hi> he had ſome ſmall <hi>comfort</hi> from the Witches fatted Calf, not ſo much to refreſh him, as to get him ſafe out of her Houſe, and leaſt his qualm of fear ſhould drive him quite off from the Devil. Both theſe two Inſtances are point-blank contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <hi>Thireus</hi> and <hi>Pinedas</hi> diſtinguiſhing Character. <hi>7ly.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is that Sign (which ſome ſay is diſtinguiſhing) any better than the former, to wit, <hi>It muſt be a good Angel that ſuggeſt good things,</hi> whereas the Devil can give <hi>good Counſel,</hi> and put upon good Duties, but always for evil Ends, as <hi>Bodinus</hi> obſerveth in <hi>Lib.</hi> 23. <hi>de Daemonomania cap.</hi> 6 and <hi>Samuel</hi> (himſelf) could not have ſpoken more gravely and ſeverely than Satan did. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.16. I have read a Story of a good man, who was very weak, and after his Solemn calling upon God, on his Knees by his Bed-ſide, he betakes himſelf to his Bed for Reſt, but being about to ſleep, an <hi>Apparition</hi> ſpeaks to him, ſaying, riſe up to Prayer; The poor Tempted Soul bravely anſwered the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I'le pray at <hi>Gods</hi> bidding not at the <hi>Divels,</hi> &amp;c. And 'tis a known caſe Satan ſuggeſts to his Vaſſals (Witches and Wiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards) to frequent places of Gods Worſhip but all in Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy) leaſt they ſhould ſeem to be ſo bad as they are indeed: yea ſometimes to receive the Euchariſt, but to reſerve it for ſome of their Magick and Diabolical Charms. So that 'tis beſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch Suggeſtions from the <hi>end</hi> propoſed, The Devils e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil <hi>end</hi> in prompting the Sick man to the <hi>Good Action</hi> of Prayer was to diſcompoſe him from ſleep and to deſtroy him thereby. 8. But much leſs may an Evil ſpirit be diſtinguiſhed from a good one by the <hi>place</hi> where the <hi>Apparition</hi> is appearing; for the Devil ſometimes can thruſt himſelf in among the Sons of God or <hi>Elect Angels,</hi> Job 1.6. and when Satan thus maketh himſelf one among the Holy Angels, 'tis by Divine permiſſion, and not without the over-ruling power of God: The good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels came into Gods preſence for <hi>good</hi> to <hi>Job,</hi> but this <hi>evil</hi> one for <hi>evel to him,</hi> to wit, for a Commiſſion to hurt him, yet even this God over ruled for <hi>good:</hi> Jam. 5.11. though the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:64617:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>was the <hi>Devils,</hi> yet the <hi>End</hi> was the <hi>Lords,</hi> So <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.1 2. yea and long before that, that <hi>Evil Angel</hi> was got into <hi>Pardice</hi> the beſt <hi>place</hi> that was then in the World; yea, and long after that he could not only accompany, but even carry Chriſt himſelf to the <hi>Holy Temple,</hi> when he placed him upon a Pinacle of it, thus it appeareth from Scripture-Record, that <hi>evil</hi> Spirits may appear. even in <hi>good places,</hi> as well as bad ones: to this <hi>Drexelius</hi> Viſion gives a farther confirmation, ſaying, <hi>He ſaw ten Devils at a Sermon,</hi> and <hi>but one at a Market;</hi> the Reaſon whereof he giveth, is, that <hi>at a Sermon,</hi> men ſtand in Awe of Gods <hi>preſence there,</hi> Act. 10.33. and therefore ten Devils Satan thinks few enough to tempt them, that they may <hi>not ſerve the Lord without Diſtraction.</hi> 1. Cor. 7.35. But at a <hi>Market</hi> the Tempter needs not ſo many tempting Tools, for <hi>there</hi> one man will (faſt enough) Tempt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, The <hi>Buyer</hi> the <hi>Seller,</hi> and the <hi>Seller</hi> the <hi>Lyer.</hi> The ſecond <hi>great Enquiry</hi> is, Whether God uſeth the <hi>Miniſtry of good Angels</hi> to his Servants now under the Goſpel? Anſwer <hi>1ſt.</hi> without all controverſy he doth, yet in an inſenſible and in an inviſible manner, that God might draw up our Hearts Heaven-ward, and have our <hi>Gonverſation</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> while our Commoration is on Earth. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Devils</hi> are not more ready to <hi>tempt</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> us, than the <hi>Angels</hi> are to <hi>ſuccour</hi> and <hi>deliver</hi> us: As Evil <hi>Angels</hi> do ſuggeſt Evil <hi>Motions,</hi> ſo do good Angels good ones, and as our <hi>good endeavours</hi> are oft <hi>hindred</hi> by the Evil Spirit: 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.18. So are our evil undertakings oft by the good Angels, otherwiſe our Protection were not equal to our Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The Devil moved <hi>Balaam</hi> to go and curſe <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a good Angel reſiſts him, and ſpeaks in the mouth of his Aſs to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> noteth well, in his contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion on that Scripture, If an Heavenly ſpirit ſtands in the way of a Sorcerer Sins, how much more are all thoſe Caeleſtial pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ready to ſtop the miſcarriages of Gods deareſt Children: how oft (yet more) had we fallen, had not theſe Bleſſed Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians upheld us in their Arms. Pſ. 91.11. whether by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the occaſions and opportunities of Evil, or by injecting
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64617:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>contrary inſtincts and motions to Good. As <hi>Michael</hi> oppoſed <hi>Satan</hi> about the <hi>Body of Moſes,</hi> ſo do the good Angels about the Bodies and Souls of the Saints <hi>while they live</hi> and carry their Souls immediately into <hi>Abrahams</hi> Boſom <hi>when they Dye;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhould we bleſs God for Angels Miniſtry, as a part of Chriſts Purchaſe. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6.7.14. who have their <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from him (to keep the Saints in their way) as well as their <hi>Confirmation</hi> by him in their own Everlaſting go dneſs: hence he is their <hi>Head,</hi> Col. 2.10. and that <hi>Jacobs Ladder</hi> on which they Aſcend with Mens Deſires, and <hi>Deſcend</hi> with Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.12. much more I might add, but I avoid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixity.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Second</hi> Anſwer. It muſt be granted that in the times of the Old and New Teſtament, God did uſe the Viſible Miniſtry of good Angels, as in the Old to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 18.17. to <hi>Lot,</hi> Gen. 19.15. to <hi>Gideon,</hi> Judg 6.12.14. and to <hi>Manoah,</hi> Judg. 13.3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in the New Teſtament, to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Matt. 1.20. to <hi>Zachary,</hi> Luke 1.13. and to the Bleſſed Virgin, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.26. &amp;c. Then did God ſpeak to his Servants at <hi>Sundry times and in diverſe manners,</hi> that is, in <hi>Dreams and Viſions by his Angels,</hi> but now he hath <hi>ſpoke to us by his Son,</hi> Heb. 1.1.2. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all <hi>Viſible Apparitions</hi> are ceaſed but not their <hi>Inviſible Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi> They ſtill Act for Gods Church and Children, though inviſibly, therefore their Hands are repreſented to be under their Wings, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 1.8. becauſe their Actions are for the moſt part inſenſible and inviſible: For God now Governs his Church in a ſpiritual manner, without the viſible Apparitions of Angels, though they be preſent with the Church in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible way: <hi>Eccleſ</hi> 5.6. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.10. 'Tis true, the <hi>Retired Saints</hi> of the primitive Times (as well as the Holy <hi>Martyrs</hi>) ſince the New Teſtament Times, had ſometimes good Angels appeared to them, for their conſolations in their <hi>forced ſolaudes</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> as the beſt Eccleſiaſtick Hiſtorys Record, concerning the <hi>Holy Virgin, Theophyla, Agnes, Lucia, Caecilia,</hi> and others, to prorect them in their Chaſtity, whilſt driven into
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64617:39"/>Deſarts by Perſecution; as alſo concerning <hi>Theodorus</hi> (who had an Angel wiping off his Sweat, with a ſoft Handkerchief, while he was under hard Torments by his Tormentors) and many others: but the Elder the Church grew, the more rare became thoſe Apparitions, as of other miraculous Signs, not becauſe Gods <hi>Arm was ſhortned,</hi> &amp;c. but becauſe his Church was (through his gracious Providence) now ſetled in an ordinary way: Thus it was with the Infant Church in the Wilderneſs, there ſhe had the <hi>Food of Angels</hi> rain'd down daily upon her, but when come into <hi>Canaan</hi> that Ceaſed, and then Iſrael muſt purvey for themſelves: ſo now we muſt not expect either the <hi>Food</hi> or the <hi>Apparition</hi> of <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Anſwer, <hi>Goulartius</hi> in his Collections of the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Hiſtories of later (than thoſe primitive) Times, makes his Reports of ſeveral ſuch Apparitions, yea <hi>Melancton</hi> in his Coment upon <hi>Daniel,</hi> tells us of his own knowledge, how holy <hi>Grynoeus</hi> was delivered from a bloody Popiſh Prieſts intention to Murder him (for reproving him of falſe Doctrine) by an <hi>Angels</hi> appearing to <hi>Melancton</hi> (like a grave goodly old man) and warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to bid <hi>Grynoeus</hi> haſten out of <hi>Spyres</hi> quickly, who no ſooner had got a Boat upon the <hi>Rhine,</hi> but he was immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and eagerly ſought for at his Lodging, by his very name, which (it ſeems) the good man had told the Prieſt, upon his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblingly deſiring ſome farther Conference with him.</p>
            <p>Anſwer the <hi>Fourth,</hi> The beſt Caſuiſts (I can conſult with) do ſay, that it is neither pious nor profitable now for men to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect either the <hi>Apparition</hi> or <hi>Conference</hi> with <hi>Holy Angels:</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the carnal Jews did of Old, attribute much to this, <hi>John</hi> 12.29. thinking that Bath-kol, or Daughter of a voice from Heaven, was the Voice of ſome Angel, not only becauſe the <hi>Decalogue</hi> (which God himſelf is ſaid to ſpeak) was aſcribed by them to be ſpoke by <hi>Angels,</hi> Act. 7.38. and Hebr. 2.2. but alſo becauſe they did not think God would ſpeak to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his own perſon, being they looked upon <hi>Moſes,</hi> as greater than <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> Hiſt. Lib. 5. Cap. 15. Tells us, how the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64617:40"/>
               <hi>Montaniſts</hi> (as well as <hi>Jews</hi>) were great pretenders to <hi>Angels-Apparition,</hi> from whom they ventured to foretel ſundry things which came not to paſs, ſo event proved them Lyars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea <hi>Mahomet</hi> (that Grand Cheat) pretended he received his Hodg-Podg <hi>Archaron</hi> from <hi>Gabriel</hi> the Angel, and the Romaniſts boart (even our-vying <hi>Mahomet</hi>) of a mighty power over Angels, Inſomuch that they pretend to ſhew a Plume of Feathers, that was pluckt out of <hi>Gabriels</hi> (that Arch-Angels) Wings: poſſibly it might be got when Angels (as common Fowls) do Mowt and caſt their I eathers: yea Popery (at this day) aſcribeth much to the Apparition of Spirits, from whom they underſtand the ſtate of their Friends in <hi>Purgatory:</hi> Thus are they (for rejecting the Truth) judicially given up of God to believe Lyes, as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience (the School Miſtriſs of Fools) do ſuffciently Teach, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.12. This is a part of the <hi>Romiſh Apoſtacy,</hi> to <hi>give heed to ſeducing Spirits,</hi> and to <hi>Dectrine of Divels.</hi> 1. Tim. 4.1.</p>
            <p>Anſwer the <hi>Fifth,</hi> To receive any new Doctrine from an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> is now abominable, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8. For Angels have no Divine Inſtitution to be Teachers of Men in the Church, they have no Sacred <hi>Miſſion</hi> or <hi>Function</hi> thereto, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.11. God hath Inſtituted the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> (not of <hi>Angels</hi>) to Build up his Church, this Honour God gives to Man, and the Word Preached by Man is called <hi>the Word of God.</hi> 1. Theſſ. 2.13. and they that Hear Man (according to the Goſpel are ſaid to <hi>hear God.</hi> Luke 10.16. yea 'tis ſo far the <hi>power of God,</hi> as to pull down the power of the Divel, therefore <hi>let none he beguiled into a voluntary Worſhip of Angels,</hi> Col. 2.18.</p>
            <p>Anſwer the <hi>Sixth.</hi> The very light of Nature among the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, did lead them to ſpeak of both <hi>Lares,</hi> or good Angels, the Guardians of <hi>Good Men,</hi> and of <hi>Lemures,</hi> to evil Angels, the <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuers</hi> and <hi>vexers of Evil Men,</hi> thus a Devil entred into <hi>Judas</hi> and an Evil Spirit oft Vexed <hi>Soul.</hi> 1. Sam. 16.14. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, 'tis not ſcarce yet out of the Memory of ſome men, how frequent were the <hi>Apparitions</hi> of Evil Spirits, <hi>Phayrie, Hebgeblins,</hi> and many frightful Spectrums, wherewith many places were fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64617:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>Haunted, and many perſons horribly diſtracted in Times of <hi>Popery</hi> and groſs Superſtition; and the rareneſs of ſuch ſcaring Viſions, in theſe latter times of Reformation, is ſufficient to diſcover the difference (as Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> excellently ſaith betwixt the ſtate of Ignorant (Popiſh) Superſtition, and the clear Light of the Goſpel. Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> of Evil Angels, <hi>pag.</hi> 993. And <hi>Camerarius</hi> (with others) tell us, how uſual thoſe Strange <hi>Apparitions</hi> were in times of Darkneſs, although <hi>now</hi> (bleſſed be God) the Relation thereof is terrible to us. <hi>Camer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius</hi> his Hiſtory <hi>Obſer. Lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Cap.</hi> 15. <hi>pag.</hi> 288. <hi>Theatre of Gods Judgments</hi> pag. 531. to 437. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Reſt, <hi>Edi.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 271. <hi>Lavater de ſpectris per totum,</hi> &amp;c. 'Twas frequent then before the Reformation in <hi>Europe</hi> (where the Goſpel hath not come to Dethrone the Devil) The Ignorant Indians <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>hear</hi> ſtrange Spectrums and Spirits in bodily ſhape, Night and Day, whereas in New <hi>England</hi> (by the Light of the Goſpel) is much delivered from that Prince of Darkneſs: <hi>Sozomen</hi> writes of one <hi>Apelles</hi> (a famous <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Smith) who was tempted to uncleanneſs, by a Divel in the ſhape of a Woman, in which ſhape (ſaith <hi>Trimethius</hi>) never any good <hi>Angle</hi> Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; hereby we may make ſome gueſs at Dr. <hi>Dees Galitah</hi> the <hi>Maid,</hi> one of his Spirits, which after appeared as a <hi>Man.</hi> Dr. <hi>Dee,</hi> pag. 12.16. and at his Friend E. <hi>Kelly,</hi> who could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide his own Wife, but abhorr'd her. <hi>pag.</hi> 30. and at his <hi>Uriel</hi> (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of his Spirits) that oft ſwore [marry] <hi>pag.</hi> 411. yea and himſelf who condemns <hi>Calvin, Luther,</hi> &amp;c. and denys the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ope to be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Joh. <hi>Bromiar. Sum proedict. v. ſuperbia.</hi> Tells a famous Story of an <hi>Angel,</hi> and an <hi>Hermite</hi> walking together, there laid in their way ſome ſtinking Carrion, at this the Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite ſtops his Noſe, turns away his Head and haſts out of that offenſive Smell, but the Angel held on his way, without any ſhew of diſlike: ſtraightway they met with a very proud, pragmatical man, gayly adorned, deeply perfumed, looking loftiy, and ſtrutting along in a moſt ſtately poſture, the <hi>Hermite</hi> gave this man great reverence and admiration, but the <hi>Argel</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:64617:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſtop't his Noſtrills, turn'd away his Head, &amp;c. Rendring this Reaſon, that the ſtench of Pride was more loathſome to <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Angels,</hi> than that ſtinking Carcaſe could be to him: Here was a better Character of the Apparition of a good <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> than of thoſe <hi>Spirits,</hi> that Dr. <hi>Doe</hi> mentioneth: I might add much more, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Anſwer the <hi>Seventh:</hi> Suppoſe an <hi>Apparition</hi> of <hi>Evil Spirits,</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſts conclude it unſafe to <hi>confer</hi> with them: our Grandmother <hi>Eve</hi> got a fall by holding Chat with the Divel in Paradice. That Fort or Caſtle which yields to a <hi>Parley,</hi> is accounted half loſt, they are too wily for us, having much advantage over us, ſtanding upon higher ground to us, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi>'s Caſes of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> pag. 161. ctc. Saying he admired at the Jeſuite <hi>Cottons</hi> conſidence, who provided many Queſtions to propound to a <hi>Demoniack,</hi> ſome whereof were matters of State, concerning the then French King, and the King of <hi>England,</hi> pag. 165. and <hi>Cotton</hi> being queſtioned for this, anſwered he had Licence from <hi>Rome</hi> for his ſo doing, <hi>ibid.</hi> and much more of <hi>Romes</hi> traſh. As to this <hi>Apparition</hi> in <hi>particular,</hi> though at firſt ſight, it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to me dreſſed up like the Divels Oracle at <hi>Delphos,</hi> in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous Expreſſions, yet upon ſecond thoughts (which ſhould always be the beſt, as being moſt deliberate) I ſhall not take upon me to Determine, either its <hi>goodneſs</hi> or <hi>badneſs,</hi> as to <hi>kind</hi> or <hi>thing,</hi> but ſhall refer my Reader to a ſerious comparing it with the Circumſtances of the aforegoing general Anſwers, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning only, that it is Gods declared Will, we ſhould <hi>Live by Faith,</hi> and not <hi>Walk by Sence</hi> or ſight of ſuch <hi>Apparitions,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in there may be much <hi>Daceptio Viſus.</hi> Hiſtory (indeed) tell us, that in ſome extraordinary caſe, God hath given out ſome <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritions</hi> for the diſcovery of ſome ſecret heinous Murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and this he may do by Devils, who are reputed ready to make ſuch Diſcoveries, that their Prey may come ſooner into their Hands, by the ſtroke of Juſtice. As to the Predictions of fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Events, which <hi>Apparitions</hi> do pronounce; ſome few things (for Brevity ſake) only, ſhall be ſaid here. As firſt, 'tis God and God alone (who is Omniſcient) that himſelf can foretel <hi>fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64617:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>Events,</hi> Iſa 41.22.23. The Prophet convinceth the Heathen of the Vanity of their Gods (or Idols, ſaying, That all certain Predictions of future Providences (which yet have no aſſured natural <hi>Cauſe</hi> or ſignificant <hi>Sign</hi>) belongeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the true God. Thus the Prophet Argues, <hi>ch.</hi> 44.7. and 45.20.21. and 46.10. and 48.14. Idols cannot declare things to come. Secondly. The Devil (though a moſt Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Spirit can know nothing of what ſhall befal for the future, ſave only thoſe things he ſeeth in their <hi>Cauſes,</hi> or in the light of <hi>participation:</hi> The Devil can better Diſcover what is paſt and done, by his own Inſtigation, as that Murder committed on a Stranger, at an Inn in <hi>Exeter,</hi> 30 years before the Diſcovery was made by an <hi>Apparition:</hi> as was likewiſe the Fraud of an <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor</hi> converting a Gentlemans Eſtate from his Children to his own uſe, who was affrighted by an <hi>Apparition</hi> unto a Reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the right Heirs, both hapned lately, and ſeem to be well atteſted by Godly Miniſters. 'Tis certain that future Contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents are not within the compaſs of the Devils Cognizance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other way, ſeeing they are wholy at Gods diſpoſing: yet <hi>Satan</hi> in ſome Caſes, and at ſome times, can foretell things to come, as <hi>1ſt.</hi> He being a <hi>Mighty Naturaliſt,</hi> able (by his Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſagacity) to dive into the deepeſt <hi>cauſes</hi> and <hi>ſecrets</hi> of Nature which men cannot do) and ſo accordingly to frame his Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſuch as ſeem ſupernatural to us he is alſo an <hi>Exact Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> attained (both by his acute Obſervations, and almoſt 6000 years Experience) to an acquaintance of all natural, moral, and political cauſes of things, as the <hi>Premiſſes,</hi> hence may he give ſhrewd gueſſes (though he know nothing Infalibly) and gather ſuch conſequences, as may probably come to paſs, if the great God be not pleaſed to interrupt this Chain of Cauſes, as he ſometimes doth, by his over-ruling Power. Though <hi>Satan</hi> be a Prince of Darkneſs, yet may he have ſecondly ſuch a <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation</hi> of ſome <hi>light</hi> by Divine (not only <hi>pirmiſſion,</hi> but) <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</hi> when God makes him the Executioner of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in ſuch a caſe 'tis eaſy for him to foretel future
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:64617:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>things, as in the Caſe of <hi>Job,</hi> he could predict (without dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty) that ſuch and ſuch Evils would ſhortly befal that good man, when he had got a Commiſſion from God for them, and wanted no tools to work them: and as in the Caſe of the 400 falſe Prophets of <hi>Ahab,</hi> in whoſe Mouth he had a <hi>Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from God to be a <hi>Lying Spirit,</hi> and delude them. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 22.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 22. which ſhews <hi>King Ahab</hi>'s Death, was revealed to the Devil, and then he could Reveal it to whom he pleaſed. The Devil Deceived thoſe Deceivers the falſe Prophets, and they Deceived <hi>Ahab,</hi> and draws him (as the <hi>Mouſe</hi>) into the Trap, where he Periſhed, not only for his <hi>Cruelty</hi> to <hi>Nabeth,</hi> but by his <hi>Credul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty</hi> to thoſe many curſed Sycophants: yea, and in the Caſe of <hi>Saul</hi> (which is yet higher) he only could have foretold the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of King <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> (ut ſupra)</hi> but he actually did foretel the Death of King <hi>Saul.</hi> 1. Sam. 28.19. Naming the time, though in ambiguous Words, as [to morrow] is indefinitely uſed, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13.14. and <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.34. Thus the Devil Equivocates in all his Oracles (as in this and in that of <hi>Ahab</hi>) <hi>The Lord ſhall deliver into the Hands of the King</hi>) 1. Kin. 2.26. where the Particle [it] is not in the Original: The word [thee] may as well be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed: and this Lying Spirit names not which of the Kings he meant, whether <hi>Ahab</hi> or <hi>Benhadad,</hi> yea his quibling O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle (as the <hi>Delphick</hi> Devil had many) might be conſtrued in a quite contrary Senſe: either <hi>1ſt.</hi> The Lord will deliver [thee] <hi>Ahab</hi> into the hands of <hi>Benhadad,</hi> or <hi>2ly.</hi> [It] to wit, <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> into the hand of <hi>Ahab:</hi> thus the deceitful Devil will ſave his Credit, what ever hapned, and yet as bad as this <hi>Abaddon</hi> is, he ſhews more ingenuity here than doth the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> for he ingeniouſly acknowledgeth his <hi>Equivocating Oracle,</hi> to be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than a <hi>Baſe Lye,</hi> ſaying <hi>I will go and be a Lying Spirit, in the Mouth of all Ahabs Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſytical Prophets. v.</hi> 22. However Satan (that mock-<hi>Samuel</hi>) ſeems more poſitive and peremptory in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of <hi>Sauls Dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fal</hi> (as above) yet this was no more than what a prudently-thinking man might have conjectured from the concurrence of ſecundary Cauſes how much more might
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64617:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>an acutely obſerving Devil make up a ſhrewd Gueſs (by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring things with things) of <hi>Sauls</hi> approaching Ruine: He could not be ignorant both of <hi>Sauls Rejection,</hi> and of <hi>Davids E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection,</hi> the <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Confidence</hi> of the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> Army, the <hi>Deſpondenties</hi> and <hi>Diffidence</hi> of <hi>Saul</hi> and his <hi>Souldiers</hi> (both which had been formerly Valorous) were not unknown to him, or poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he might peep into thoſe Prophetick Predictions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> in ch. 15. and 16. of the firſt of <hi>Sam.</hi> Yea he well knew, what himſelf deſigned to do in the day of Battle (with Gods Permiſſion) againſt <hi>Saul</hi> who had forfeited <hi>Gods Protection.</hi> The third Conſideration I ſhall conclude with is, that the <hi>Devil</hi> hath his Inſtruments or Vaſſals amongſt Mankind, to whom he imparts his Predictions, that they may impart them to others; and thoſe are moſtly <hi>Women</hi> (of the Devils choice) more than <hi>Men,</hi> becauſe they are <hi>Weaker Viſſels,</hi> whoſe credulity is ſooner impoſed upon, and eaſilyer abuſed and deluded by the Devil: we have two ſamous Inſtances one in the Old the other in the New Teſtament) the <hi>1ſt</hi> hereof is 1. Sam. 28.7. where <hi>Saul</hi> ſaid, <hi>ſeck me out a Woman that hath a familiar Spirit</hi> not a <hi>Man</hi> but a <hi>Woman,</hi> he had put down Witches before, yet hoped he ſome might be remaining (though not of <hi>Men,</hi> yet) of <hi>Women,</hi> which are wont to be lighter and proner to Superſtition, not only becauſe of weaker Wits and apter to be Deceived, but, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they cannot compaſs any Fame or Glory by Noble Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits (as men can) they therefore would become Famous by Magick Art: hence this Woman became a Dame to a familiar Spirit, and thither <hi>Saul</hi> comes, who rather than fail would crave help from Hell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the ſecond Inſtance is not unlike this firſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 16.16. The <hi>Divining</hi> Damoſel, who probably foretold many things that came to paſs, otherwiſe ſhe could never have <hi>brought ſo much Gain to her Maſters,</hi> as that Scripture ſaith: ſhe might make unhappy Hits ſometimes, from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacity of (her grand Maſter) Satan; yet miſs too at other times; for if the Divel himſelf cannot foretel all future Events, nor any thing Infalibly himſelf, but either as it is Revealed to him
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:64617:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>by God (as was <hi>Ahab's</hi> Fall at <hi>Ramoh Gilead</hi>) or as be foreſeeth them in the <hi>Cauſes, Signs</hi> or <hi>Prophecies</hi> of Holy Scripture, wherein he is not a little skil'd, and out of which he ſometimes ſtealeth a parcel. Far be it from me to apply our preſent <hi>Apparition</hi> to either of theſe aforementioned, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon theſe Grounds. <hi>1ſt.</hi> We do not find that this <hi>Apparition</hi> required any <hi>Adoration;</hi> when <hi>Saul</hi> bowed himſelf to <hi>Satan</hi> (that Mock-<hi>Samuel</hi>) 1. Sam. 28.14. That <hi>Adoration</hi> was the main thing that the Devil chiefly aimed at: <hi>2ly.</hi> We do not find (in our Caſe) any ſeeking to this <hi>Apparition,</hi> for that is (Tantamount) a <hi>Worſhipping,</hi> though there be no bowing, and how far amounts <hi>holding Conference</hi> with Apparitions (ſee above) but yet it ſeems an higher ſtep to <hi>obey their Commands,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as are diſſonant to the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> or <hi>Nations,</hi> or Scripture, which is not our Caſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth this comport with the latter Inſtance, though here's a <hi>Divining Damſel,</hi> yet not ſuch an one as the Septuagints uſually call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe the Devil ſpake out of their Bellys; for which cauſe alſo the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews call them <hi>Oboth</hi> or Bottles, becauſe the Bellys of thoſe Women (thus made uſe of by the Devil) ſwelled as big as Bottles, when they began to Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy. <hi>2ly.</hi> Neither do we hear of any gain either to her ſelf or to her Maſters <hi>here,</hi> as appeareth <hi>there. 3ly.</hi> Neither do we find any Diſturbance given to Gods Worſhip under ſpecious pretences <hi>here,</hi> as is found <hi>there.</hi> They that deſire to know more of thoſe Divining Intrigues, let them conſult <hi>Baldwins</hi> Caſes of Conſcience. <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 533. to 620. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> too long here (ſo much as to abridge in this ſmall Treatiſe) and other <hi>Caſuiſts;</hi> I add this on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>1ſt.</hi> If the <hi>Death</hi> of any be foretold by the Devil we ought not to believe it, as from him (the <hi>Lyar</hi>) God can Croſs it, <hi>2ly.</hi> If God permit it, 'tis to harden the ſuperſtitious Obſervers of it: <hi>3ly.</hi> 'tis enough Gods Word. fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels that all ſhall fall out for the beſt to them that love God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. So ail's welcome: ſo far as Gods Word guideth us, we walk ſafely, but if we ſtep farther into a By-way 'twill lead us down into the Chambers of Death.</p>
            <p>I Omit the ſtrange Apparitiors at <hi>Pons Town</hi> in <hi>Tipperary</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted by 16 perſons Eye Witneſſes, and Printed. The laſt and lateſt of Land-Prodigies (omitting many others that come not yet well proved to my Hand (is the <hi>Death</hi> of 3 <hi>Tower-Lyons;</hi> called Old <hi>Charls, Queen</hi> and <hi>Duke</hi> which is the more Remarkable, becauſe we do not find (ſcarce in a whole Age) any Record of the Death of ſo much as <hi>one</hi> of thoſe Royal Long Lived Creatures (the Keeper whereof is ſo much obliged both by Loyalty and Advantage to preſerve them) much leſs of ſo many and that within few days, as if they had conſpired to march off together, the more to amuſe and amaze this Tripple Realm, for every Kingdom one: to Exemplify it in our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Chroniels,</hi> though ſomething like it is ſaid to happen in King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards</hi>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:64617:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>Reign, yet I cannot find a fit <hi>Paralel</hi> unto this ſtrange Prodigy <hi>upon Record,</hi> ſave only in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixths Reign, Whereof Sir <hi>Richard Baker</hi> (who is generally owned as an Impartial Chronicler of former Times) giveth us this Account. That in the 18th. year of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth <hi>all the Lyons in the</hi> Tower <hi>Dyed. Bakers Chron.</hi> pag. 199. This Kings Reign was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with many miſchiefs betwixt him and the then <hi>Duke of York. Henry</hi> the Fifth after he had Conquered <hi>France,</hi> and kept his Court with incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Magnificence for ſome time, then he Returns with his Queen into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who was delivered of a Son at <hi>Windſor,</hi> called therefore <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. of <hi>Windſor</hi> (upon whom at his Birth his Father ſpake Prophetically <hi>[I Henry of Monmouth have gain'd much</hi> and ſhall remain but a ſhort time: but <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Windſor</hi> ſhall Reign long and looſe all] and acording to this <hi>Paternal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy</hi> the Son firſt loſt <hi>His All</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and after, 2ly. <hi>His All</hi> in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> In this <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixths time, <hi>France, Normandy, Aquitain,</hi> were all loſt from the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> ſuch were the bloody Contentions be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaster,</hi> that ten ſeveral fierce Battels were fiercely fought between the two Factions, whereof 5 were fought in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixths time. The <hi>firſt</hi> at <hi>St. Albans</hi> in which <hi>Yorks</hi> prevailed: the <hi>ſecond</hi> at <hi>Black-Heath,</hi> in which the <hi>Confederate Lords were Conquerors:</hi> the <hi>third</hi> at <hi>Northampton,</hi> in which <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth was again overthrown: the <hi>fourth</hi> at <hi>Wakefield,</hi> in which the <hi>King</hi> was Victorious: the <hi>ſixth</hi> at <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in which the new <hi>Duke of York</hi> carried it, who became thereby King <hi>Edward</hi> the IV. In whoſe time alſo five more ſeveral ſet Battels were fought upon the ſame Quarrel: as <hi>firſt,</hi> that at <hi>Exham: ſecondly,</hi> that at <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury: thirdly,</hi> the Battel of <hi>Looſe-Coats: fourthly,</hi> that in <hi>Barnet Fields:</hi> and <hi>fifthly</hi> that at <hi>Tewxbury.</hi> Thus even the <hi>White Roſe</hi> was Dyed Red, over and over again, with the blood of many brave men, and a Period was never put to this Contention twixt the <hi>White</hi> and <hi>Red Roſe,</hi> until that conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Battel at <hi>Boſworth Fields,</hi> in which the <hi>Plantaginets</hi> expired, and both the <hi>Houſes</hi> were after united in <hi>Henry</hi> the VII. <hi>Roſſe</hi>'s Hiſtory of the World, <hi>pag.</hi> 534. &amp;c. and Dr. <hi>Prideaux</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory of Succeſſions</hi> in our own Land, <hi>pag.</hi> 333. Who tells a memorable Story of thoſe ſuch Catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Times (as he calls them) of one <hi>Burdet</hi> a Mercer in <hi>Cheap. ſide,</hi> who jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly ſaid to his Son, if he would ply his Book, he ſhould be <hi>Heir to the Crown</hi> (meaning his own Houſe, which had the <hi>Crown</hi> for its <hi>Sign,</hi> and had no Relation to the <hi>Crown</hi> of the Kingdom) for this Jeſt the Man loſt his Life: aſſuredly an <hi>Honeſt Jury</hi> would not have given him ſuch <hi>hard Meaſure.</hi> God bleſs us from ſuch <hi>Contentious</hi> and ſuch <hi>catching Times,</hi> which were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaged not only by the Death of the <hi>Tower Lyons,</hi> as above, but alſo by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Prodigies, as a <hi>Blazing Star, Monſtrous Births,</hi> a prodigious
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:64617:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>k out of the Sea at <hi>Portland,</hi> crowing three times, and turning his Head to the <hi>South, North</hi> and <hi>West,</hi> and <hi>Pauls</hi> Steeple was fired with Lightning: See <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es Hiſtory of the World,</hi> pag. 534. And Sir <hi>Richard Bakers Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> of the ſame time, all theſe Prodigies were <hi>Preſages</hi> of ſad future Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. Enquiry, <hi>Why muſt the Death of</hi> Lyons <hi>be made a</hi> Prodigy, <hi>ſeeing they are M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> as other Beaſts, and Dye only in the common courſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> Anſwer the <hi>firſt,</hi> Conſider in the general, A <hi>Lyon 1ſt.</hi> For his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> that ſits enthroned in his looks. <hi>2ly.</hi> For his <hi>Magnanimity,</hi> as diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go out of his ſtately pace, though Danger purſue him, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. <hi>v.</hi> 30. <hi>3ly.</hi> For his <hi>Formidableneſs,</hi> inſomuch that when the <hi>Lyon</hi> Roareth, all the Beaſts Tremble, <hi>Am.</hi> 3.8. and have not power to fly from him, though they can out run him; hence he is the <hi>Hyeroglyphick</hi> of <hi>Dominion,</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily</hi> as well as <hi>vulgarly</hi> is called the <hi>King of Beaſts.</hi> Hereupon the Fall of a <hi>Lyon</hi> is as the Fall of <hi>Abner,</hi> the <hi>Fall of a Prince,</hi> 2. Sam. 3.38. 'Tis look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on as a <hi>Fatal Fall,</hi> the Death of a <hi>Lyon</hi> was the preſage of <hi>Julian's</hi> death, ſaith <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> Anſwer the <hi>ſecond,</hi> more ſpecially as the <hi>living Lyon</hi> Reſembleth <hi>Majeſty Domineering</hi> (according to <hi>Aeſops</hi> Apologue) over the <hi>Aſs</hi> and the <hi>Fox</hi> in ſharing the Prey they had joyntly caught in Hunting: So the <hi>Dead Lyon</hi> repreſenteth <hi>Majesty Deceaſed</hi> (according to <hi>Alciats</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem and the Greek <hi>Epigram</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Thouth the <hi>Lyon</hi> while living be the Nobleſt of Beaſts, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.30. yet when Dead, this Noble Beaſt is expoſed to the Scorn of the moſt weak and timorous <hi>Hares.</hi> Hence aroſe the Hebrew Proverb, that a <hi>living Dog</hi> (with them the <hi>baſeſt</hi> of Creatures) <hi>was better than a Dead Lyon</hi> (both as to Uſe and as to Eſſence) <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.4. Importing that the <hi>meaneſt man Living,</hi> is better than the <hi>greateſt man Dead.</hi> Anſwer the <hi>third,</hi> The Death of a <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Lyon</hi> is more portentous than the Death of many <hi>Lyons</hi> in the Wilds of <hi>Lybia,</hi> whereof no notice would be taken, but a <hi>Tower Lyon</hi> is the <hi>Darling</hi> as well as <hi>Emblem</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> and the <hi>Delight</hi> as well as <hi>Wonder</hi> of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that have been admitted to behold them; and ſeeing they naturally live longer than the oldeſt of Men, ſcarce any one Age brings Tidings of the Death of a <hi>Tower Lyon</hi> (as before) ſo carefully attended, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This occaſions the general Opinion, that ſuch an Occurrence is a <hi>Fore-runner</hi> of ſome <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality.</hi> Anſwer the <hi>fourth,</hi> How much more the <hi>Death</hi> of 3 <hi>Tower Lyons</hi> at once, as if a <hi>Lyon Peſtilence</hi> (that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Divine Thing had been ſent to kill three <hi>Lyons at one blow,</hi> this hardly finds a Paralel in Hiſtory, the <hi>ſtrong Tower</hi> (it ſelf) with all its high Walls, deep Trenches, braſs Guns, great Guards, and warded Gates, could not be a Tower of Defence to them or to any one them, and if <hi>Tria</hi> had been <hi>Omnia</hi> here (as it is in <hi>Philoſophy</hi>) the <hi>Tower</hi> had been left a Lyon-leſs Tower. Sacred Story ſpeaks of one Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:64617:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>not altogether diſſonant to this, to wit, <hi>Samſon turned aſide to ſee the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe of the Lyon, and behold there was a Swarm of Bees and Honey in the Carcaſe,</hi> Judg. 14.8. <hi>prodigioſum eſt</hi> (<hi>ſaith</hi> Lovater) <hi>quòd Meilificarunt Apes in Cadavere, &amp;c.</hi> 'Twas no leſs than a <hi>Prodigy,</hi> that Bees ſhould breed and make Honey ſo ſoon in ſuch a place, ſeeing they are naturally driven away by an ill Smell, as abhorring all ſtinking things, ſuch as this Carcaſe muſt needs be upon its Putrefaction; herein <hi>Pliny, Columella, Aelian, Var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> and all Naturaliſts do unanimouſly concurr: Indeed ſome (as <hi>Virgil, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> &amp;c.) do ſay, <hi>Bees</hi> may breed in the Carcaſe of a Bullock raturally, but never in the Carcaſe of a <hi>Lyon,</hi> which hath a more foetid fleſh and a more ſtinking ſmell; however, not in ſo ſhort a time as was between <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Contract and the ſolemnizing of his Marriage. It therefore only came to paſs, by the ſpecial Providence of God producing this <hi>Prodigy,</hi> not, only by a <hi>praeternatural,</hi> but alſo by a <hi>Supernatural</hi> power. Now that the <hi>Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Lyons</hi> be dead (though we had no hand in their Death, as <hi>Samſon</hi> had in his) let us turn aſide (a little) to view theſe Carcaſes, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did this) and behold both the <hi>Congruity</hi> and <hi>Diſparity</hi> of them: As <hi>1ſt.</hi> God Bleſs us, that no Swarms of thoſe Bees of <hi>Babylon</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.18.) may breed out of their <hi>Carcaſes,</hi> nor out of them whoſe names they bore, to Sting us with their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Stings: And God bleſs us not only from thoſe Honey-leſs Waſps and Droniſh Robbers, but alſo that the right Honey may be bred in the body of the ſuperviving <hi>Lyon,</hi> call'd <hi>Charles</hi> the II. and in him whoſe name he beareth: <hi>3ly.</hi> Though we find no <hi>Honey</hi> in any of thoſe 3 Carcaſes, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did in his one, yet may we find ſuch a <hi>Riddle</hi> in them which may puzzle and <hi>Non-Plus</hi> all the uncircumciſed <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> Judg. 14.12.14. <hi>Out of thoſe Eaters may came forth Meat and out of the ſtrong ſweetneſs.</hi> This <hi>Problem</hi> (as many of Gods <hi>Providences</hi>) is made up of contraries, yet the aenigmatical Sentence ſeems to ſignify, that it ſhould come to paſs, the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> which ruled with rigour over the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> at that time, ſhould be ſubdued and eaten up by the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and when they were moſt ſtrong, they ſhould not damnify but accommodate the <hi>Hebrews:</hi> The good Lord grant the ſame Priviledges to the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> over the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> who have eaten us up as their <hi>Daily Bread,</hi> with the like voracity as the Hungry devour <hi>Bread,</hi> Pſ. 14.4. Yea, thoſe cruel Cannibals makes <hi>Fleſh</hi> as well as <hi>Bread</hi> of poor <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and do as barbarouſly and brutiſhly worry them with open Mouth, as the bloody <hi>Lyons</hi> do the helpeſs <hi>Sheep,</hi> Pſ. 27.2. O that they may now ſtumble and fall in attempting it, and both they and their <hi>Leviathan</hi> (the <hi>Pope</hi>) with his <hi>broken Head,</hi> may be given <hi>as meat to the people Inhabiting the Wilderneſs,</hi> Pſ. 74.13.14. Then would God unriddle, how <hi>out of the grand Eater cometh Meat, and out of the ſtrong cometh Sweetneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:64617:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>This Leads me to the <hi>third and laſt Scene</hi> or Theatre, whereon God thews his <hi>Wonderful Signs,</hi> to wit, (as in <hi>Heaven</hi> and on the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſo) upon the <hi>Waters:</hi> As I do deſignedly omit many marvelous things, mentioned in Forreign and Domeſtick Letters, ſuch as the <hi>Earth-quake</hi> at <hi>Malago,</hi> which overturn'd their Religious Houſes, and put all <hi>Spain</hi> into a Fright, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And ſuch as have lately hapned alſo in our Lands) becauſe they come not well Atteſted to make them enough Authentick, in the foregoing Stage or Theatre: ſo I muſt do in this laſt, omitting many Stories, and pitch firſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which hath unqueſtionable Teſtimony of the Truth thereof, to wit, the Drying up of the River <hi>Wye</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> between <hi>Radnorſhire</hi> and <hi>Breck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nock-ſhire</hi> (where 'tis near as broad as <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>Brainford</hi>) about a ſtones caſt over, and of a ſierce Current, yet on the 25th. of <hi>January</hi> laſt at <hi>Lewys<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> it ſtop't its courſe and parted it ſelf, and became dry, ſo that ſeveral perſons walked over Dry-ſhod, ſome gathered up Fiſhes for ſeveral Miles, this continued for ſeveral Hours: This is Atteſted for Truth, by Mr. <hi>Probat</hi> High Sherriff of <hi>Radnorſhire,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Jones,</hi> (whoſe letter hereof I had to aſſure me) both Eye-Witneſſes, and it was alſo obſerved that the two Rivers (<hi>I thou</hi> and <hi>Yrvon</hi>) which fall into that River <hi>Wye,</hi> were at the ſame time like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſuddenly dry: but after a few hours flowed with more Violence, and higher than uſual: and (as my Letter addeth) no natural Reaſon could be rendred hereof: Now to exemplify this <hi>Prodigy</hi> by Paralel Inſtances, from <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Hiſtory: <hi>1ſt. Satred</hi> Story ſaith, that when <hi>God brake the Heads of the Dragon</hi> (Satans ſworn Sword-men and <hi>Pharoahs</hi> chief Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains) and the <hi>Head</hi> of the grand <hi>Leviathan</hi> or <hi>Pharoah</hi> himſelf, then did God alſo <hi>Divide the Sea, and clave alſo the Fountains and the Flood,</hi> Pſ. 74.13.14.15. <hi>Drying up mighty Rivers, as Jordan, Euphrates and the Red Sea,</hi> which (in reſpect of the <hi>Main Ocean</hi>) was but a mighty <hi>River.</hi> This the <hi>Angel of God Divided and dryed up,</hi> for ſix hundred Thouſand to paſs over in Rank and File. <hi>Exod</hi> 14.21.22. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 136.13. and 106.9. Gods Rebuke was upon the Waters, clove them in twain, and bound them up with his <hi>Swadling Band</hi> (as eaſily as a Nurſe doth her Infant) <hi>Job</hi> 38.9. ſo that they could neither wave, nor ſwell, nor flow, but became as a firm Wall (fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen into hard Ice) on both ſides of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Pſ. 78.13. Thus the fluid Waters, were fixed and became as Stone Walls, on each hand of them, while they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed through with eaſe and ſafety. This the Pſalmiſt Wonders at, and asks the Waters, <hi>What ailed thee, O thou Sea,</hi> &amp;c. Pſ. 114.5. and thence he paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to <hi>Jordan,</hi> (more Paralel to our Caſe) asking what was the matter with you <hi>both,</hi> that the one <hi>Fled</hi> and the other was <hi>Driven back:</hi> can there be any natural Reaſon given? or was't the powerful preſence of God that affrighted you into this <hi>Retrograde Run</hi> or <hi>Motion,</hi> v. 7. This Inſtance ſheweth we may
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:64617:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>many times ask Queſtions, and yet neither <hi>doubt of the matter,</hi> nor be <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the Cauſe:</hi> This more Paralel Caſe of the drying up <hi>Jordan,</hi> Joſh. 3.13. <hi>The Waters of that River were cut off,</hi> that is, the Waters that came from above were cut off ſo as to ſtand ſtill as on a Heap, and the waters that were below (according to their ordinary courſe) ran away into the Dead Sea, ſo the Channel was left Dry, having no waters coming down from above to feed and fill it. This was a wonderful Work of God, and much admired by the Pſalmiſt in his <hi>Pſ.</hi> 114. Now this <hi>Jordan</hi> was a compound of two Rivers (<hi>Jor</hi> and <hi>Dan</hi>) as our Welſh River was, yet the Courſe of both the ſtreams were ſtop't for ſome Hours, ſo the Channel was dry, though ('tis true) the Camp of <hi>Iſrael</hi> was not there with the Ark to paſs over into <hi>Canaan:</hi> The <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe Addeth the drying up of <hi>Arnon</hi> and <hi>Jabbok,</hi> whereof ſee <hi>Num.</hi> 21.14. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 2.37. as <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.12. mentions the drying up of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates</hi> for the Kings of the <hi>East to paſs over,</hi> &amp;c. but leaving <hi>Sacred,</hi> come we to <hi>Civil</hi> Story: Our Famous <hi>Cambden</hi> Reports of another River in <hi>Merionith ſhire</hi> in <hi>Wales,</hi> the River <hi>Dee</hi> that runneth through <hi>Pimble-Meer</hi> or <hi>Lake,</hi> it mingles not her Streams with the Waters of the Lake, though this be a great <hi>Marvel,</hi> and hath alſo a good <hi>Moral</hi> (to wit, that we ſhould not mingle the <hi>ſtreams</hi> of our <hi>Affections</hi> with the puddle Water of <hi>Corrupt Company,</hi> when carried headlong at unawares among them) yet it is far ſhort of our preſent <hi>Prodigy:</hi> and the ſame <hi>Cambden</hi> relates, how the <hi>River Ouſe</hi> near <hi>Bedford</hi> (in the laſt year of King <hi>Richard</hi> the II.) ſtood ſtill, and ceaſed his Courſe, ſo as the Channel remained dry for the ſpace of three miles together. <hi>Cambden Brit.</hi> pag. 399. which was then adjudged to ſignify the Revoltings of the Subjects from their Prince. <hi>Bakers Chron.</hi> pag. 154.167. He being miſlead by his Favorite <hi>Michael de-la-pool</hi> and other <hi>Sycophants,</hi> did incurr the hatred of his People, <hi>Prideaux Introduction,</hi> pag. 324. In his time was the marvelous <hi>Parliament,</hi> and that which wrought Wonders. See <hi>Baker</hi> of his Reign. Alſo in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the VI. The ſame <hi>River Ouſe</hi> (on New-Years Day) ſuddenly ſtood ſtill and divided it ſelf, which (as was conceived) did portend the prodigious Broyls between the Houſes of <hi>York</hi> and <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> ſee <hi>Bakers Chron.</hi> among the Caſualties (as he calls them) of his Reign. The like hapned in the year 1660. to the River <hi>Derwent</hi> near <hi>Darby,</hi> which was dryed up upon <hi>Nov.</hi> the 29. for many miles and ſome hours, ſo that the Mills ſtood, the Boats were on ground, the Fiſhes taken up upon the Sand by Children, and men walked over dry ſhod. This was the <hi>greater Prodigy,</hi> not only becauſe 'tis a broad River and runs with a <hi>fierce and full Stream</hi> (as <hi>Cambden</hi> Britt. pag. 554. relateth) but alſo becauſe the <hi>Waters</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> were dryed up ſoon after, by the Silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſome thouſands of Orthodox Miniſters: As thoſe Rivers returned (all of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:64617:46"/>them) to their courſe again, ſo the good Lord <hi>know us in our Wilderneſs and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Land of great Drought,</hi> Hoſ. 13.5. and make us again as a <hi>watered Garden, whoſe Waters fail not:</hi> Iſa. 58.11. That our <hi>Fleece,</hi> as <hi>Giacons</hi> may not <hi>ſtill be Dry.</hi> Judg. 6.39. but the Lord be <hi>as ſprings of Water to us,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all our <hi>freſh ſprings are in him,</hi> Pſ. 87.7. an <hi>everflowing and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> Fountain of Grace and Comfort.</p>
            <p>Were not my Book already ſwoln too bulky, I might inſiſt alſo upon the <hi>pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gious Whale,</hi> which was found lately in the River <hi>Wevner,</hi> within 6 miles of <hi>Chicheſter,</hi> 50 foot in length, and 28 in thickneſs, who broke off his own Tail with ſtrugling, and turn'd the River into Blood with his Blood: an undoubted <hi>Prodigy,</hi> for the <hi>Whale</hi> never breaks forth out of her beloved Ocean (which is her peculiar Dominion) into narrow Rivers, but it preſages Storms, where ſuch a thing hapneth: Aſſuredly <hi>Jonah</hi>'s was the greateſt of <hi>Prodigies,</hi> who ſhip'd him to the ſhore, and in the mean time afforded him an <hi>Oratory</hi> a place to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in. Four <hi>Prodigious Wonders</hi> were concurring therein ſaith <hi>Mercer, eſt.</hi> That the Heat of the Whales Stomach did not Conſume <hi>Jonah</hi> as it did other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>2ly.</hi> That in ſo cloſe a Priſon he could both breath and live, without the common uſe of <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>light. 3ly.</hi> That be was not choaked with the Stench of ſo fifthy a Jakes as the <hi>Whales Belly. 4ly.</hi> That he had his Senſes (as well as Life) there, to <hi>pour out</hi> ſuch an excelient <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Praiſe</hi> to God. <hi>Jonah</hi> was the true <hi>Arion</hi> (the Poets mention) out of whoſe <hi>Hiſtory</hi> Chriſt gathers the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of his own <hi>Death, Burial,</hi> and <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> Jon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. and 2.10. with Matt. 12.40. This great Sea-Monſter (that never uſeth to come near the Shore, but Sports himſelf in the deep Waters <hi>Pſ.</hi> 104.26.) yet when the Great God (the chief <hi>Centurion</hi>) commands him thither; he <hi>must go</hi> and Vomit up <hi>Jonah</hi> upon dry Land. <hi>He breaks the Head</hi>) as well as <hi>Tail</hi>) of this Monſtrous <hi>Leviathan,</hi> and <hi>gives him to be Meat to the People inhabiting the Wilderneſs</hi> Pſ. 74.14. Though no <hi>Mortal man can Ring</hi> him like an <hi>Hog,</hi> or <hi>Rule</hi> him like a <hi>Bear,</hi> Job. 41.2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal God can</hi> and <hi>did ſo,</hi> to Senacherib that <hi>crooked Leviathan.</hi> Iſa. 27.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 37, 29. and doth ſo, both to the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> who would Devour <hi>Europe,</hi> and to the <hi>Great Pope,</hi> who would deſtroy the <hi>Reformed Countrys: Proco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> tells of a great Whale in his Time, that much Infeſted the Coaſts of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and did much Miſchief for fifty years together, but at laſt was <hi>taken and tamed</hi> (by ſlaughter) though 30 Cubits long and ten bread. Thus <hi>Jehovah</hi> will Take and Tame both <hi>Behemoth,</hi> the <hi>Turk</hi> who Eats up men like <hi>Graſs upon the Mountains.</hi> Job. 40.15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>Leviathan</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> who <hi>Sports</hi> himſelf in his <hi>See</hi> to devour <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> God will pull thoſe 2 <hi>Kings of the Children of Pride</hi> out of their Seats (though they have Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Church many fifty years, and both <hi>Saddle and Bridle them.</hi> Job. 41.13.34. In due Time God will make this latter <hi>(Leviathan) to break his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:64617:47"/>own Tail,</hi> and let <hi>out his own Blood,</hi> as that <hi>Colcheſter Whale</hi> did, and God <hi>will break his Head,</hi> and give him to be meat to his People: There be many more <hi>Signs and Wonders</hi> I omit (though mentioned in publick Intelligences) becauſe not (to me enough <hi>Authentically Atteſted,</hi> I would alſo ſubjoyn here the many marvelous and prodigious Providences, not only <hi>reported,</hi> but likewiſe <hi>Recorded</hi> in our <hi>own Land of late</hi> (were it not to avoid prolixity) ſuch as the <hi>Wonderful Diſcovery of Juſtice Godfreys Death: The Wonderful delivery of Juſtice Arnolds life.</hi> The Wonderful diſappointment <hi>(hitherto)</hi> of all the Popiſh Plots (both <hi>Sham</hi> and <hi>Real</hi> againſt King and Kingdom. The <hi>Wonderful Death</hi> of three grand Enemies (to an honeſt Alderman in <hi>Hull</hi>) who all dyed in three Weeks time, in the heat and height of their Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions againſt him: with many more ſuch marvelous Occurrences, befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſeveral Perſecutors and Prophane Scoffers (as him whoſe Eyes dropt out of his Head, immediately after his Scoffing at the <hi>late Comet</hi>) not yet plenarily proved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Application</hi> in ſhort (after a long <hi>Explication</hi> general and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, yet Applicatorily Explained all along) is twofold, <hi>1ſt. General. 2ly. Particular,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> of thoſe to be poſſitive and peremptory in (without a peculiar Gift, which we pretend not to) is by the beſt Caſuiſts called <hi>Nefas,</hi> and no better than preſumption to pry too curiouſly into the <hi>Ark</hi> of Divine Secrets, for which <hi>fifty Thouſand Bethſhemites were ſlain,</hi> 1. Sam. 6.19. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana Dei ſunt Arca Dei,</hi> we may not <hi>ſearch into Gods Secrets.</hi> Deut. 29.29. <hi>Mirari oportet, rimari non licet,</hi> 'tis as unmannerly to <hi>pry</hi> into our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Houſe, as 'tis to <hi>preſs</hi> into it, ſaid <hi>Xenocrates:</hi> how much more may men be paid for peeping into Gods Houſe, as the men of <hi>Bethſhemeſh</hi> were, contrary to Gods Command. Num. 4.20. <hi>Eorum que ſcire nec Datur nec fas est, Docta est ignorantia, iſtius ſcientiae Appetentia eſt inſaniae ſpecies,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin:</hi> 'Tis a learned Ignorance not to know what we ought not to know, and 'tis a kind of madneſs to deſire it, <hi>Funccius</hi> ſings well, ſaying, <hi>Tufuge ſeu peſtem</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And <hi>Peter</hi> giveth charge againſt this Impious <hi>Curioſity</hi> as againſt <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Murder,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.15. 'tis a being too <hi>buiſy with Gods matters. Baldwin</hi> therefore concludes this point, <hi>praeſtat Ergo,</hi> &amp;c. 'tis better to paſs over prodigies in ſilence, and leave the particular Application of them to the moſt Wiſe God, than by an <hi>over-curious Divining</hi> to betray our own temerity, <hi>Bald. Caſes of Conſcience, Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Pag.</hi> 813. However to make a general Application (which is the former) of them, is to be <hi>Wiſe unto Sobriety,</hi> ſeeing Events in all Ages do evidence, that <hi>Prodigies</hi> do portend (in the general) a Futurition or Approach of ſome things (not yet exiſtent) and ſuch as bear ſome proportion in quality to the <hi>Predigies</hi> themſelves: as Armies portend Wars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is acknowledged by <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:64617:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Machiavel,</hi> that no extraordinary Calamities befal Nations or Cities, but 'tis foreſhewn by ſome <hi>Extraordinary Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> as the Reverend Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> (in his Sermen preached before King <hi>Charles</hi> the I.) quoteth them. <hi>pag.</hi> 9.10. Yea, our Saviour himſelf did Inſtitute <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> as immediate forerunners of that final Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſo forely threatned and ſo ſeverely executed by <hi>Titus Veſpaſian, Matth.</hi> 24. <hi>Mark</hi> 13. and <hi>Luke</hi> 21. and <hi>Joſephus</hi> hath a good Note upon it, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12. of the Wars of the <hi>Jews,</hi> that it was Gods Clemency to Mankind to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhew by thoſe extraordinary <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> what waſting Deſolations were approaching that his people being <hi>forewarned</hi> might be <hi>forearmed</hi> alſo and take the beſt Courſe for their own ſafety. The <hi>General Application of Prodigies,</hi> (which are unqueſtionable) be principally two, according to <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelins à Lapide's</hi> Notion, on <hi>Joel.</hi> 2.30. Prodigia ſunt Credentibus benefica, incredulis vero Malefica &amp; Horribilia. 1ſt. <hi>They do portend much miſchief to that part of the World, which wallows in Wickedneſs without Repentance:</hi> The <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> God ſhewed to <hi>Pharoah</hi> were not only <hi>Meſſengers,</hi> but even <hi>Harbingers</hi> of <hi>his</hi> and his <hi>Peoples</hi> Deſtruction, ſo was the <hi>Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing</hi> upon the <hi>Wall</hi> a <hi>Prodigy</hi> portending <hi>Belſhazzars</hi> Downfal for his Drunken and Debauched Quaffings, <hi>Dan.</hi> 15.22.23. So were the <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> in <hi>Heaven, Earth</hi> and <hi>Sea</hi> (as <hi>Luke</hi> ranks them <hi>Luke</hi> 21.25.) Infallible portents and preſages of the final fall of the <hi>Jews</hi> and their <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for Perſecuting Chriſt and his Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus it was of latter times in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> as their wickedneſs and Debauchery increaſed, ſo did their <hi>Prodigies, Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Iron-Age,</hi> pag. 66. Yea and in our Land Sir <hi>Rich. Baker</hi> hath worthily Recorded. How the many Miſchiefs (that have befallen this Nation) were all foreſhewed by many foregoing <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders</hi> (which he calleth Caſualties) in every Reign, whereof I have extracted an Epitome, and thought to have inſerted it here, were not my Book too bulky already. <hi>2ly.</hi> They do Prognoſticate <hi>Relief and Remedy</hi> to the <hi>Religious part of the World. Aegypts</hi> Overthrow was <hi>Iſraels</hi> Deliverance, and ſo was and will be <hi>Babylons</hi> to <hi>Sion.</hi> Therefore Chriſt encourageth his <hi>Servants</hi> at the ſight of ſuch <hi>Signs, to lift up their Heads for their Redemption draweth nigh,</hi> Luke 21.25.28. All men ought therefore to <hi>Regard the Works of the Lord</hi> and to <hi>conſider the Operations of his Hands,</hi> leaſt by neglect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they provoke a Jealous God to <hi>Destroy them</hi> and not <hi>build them up.</hi> Pſ. 28.5. How oft doth God call on <hi>Zechary,</hi> lift up thine Eyes and behold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and <hi>what ſeeſt thou?</hi> &amp;c. God ſhews his <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> not that men ſhould caſt <hi>ſcurrilous Scoffs</hi> at them, (who knoweth whether ſuch have a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute betwixt his laſt <hi>Jest</hi> in this World, and his Everlaſting <hi>Earneſt</hi> in a worſe World) but to make <hi>ſerious Contemplations</hi> on them: what curious
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:64617:48"/>Artiſt can endure (when he expoſes ſome ſpecial peice to publick View) to ſee <hi>ſottiſh men take no notice of it,</hi> or <hi>ſilly ſpectators</hi> (that cannot underſtand its Admirable Art) <hi>Deride it.</hi> God is Certainly <hi>Tuning</hi> his Inſtrument (as I ſay in pag. 32.) and will ſhortly play ſome choice Tune, though made up of Diſcords. The good Lord help us to <hi>Dance after his Pipe,</hi> and to <hi>meet him in the way of his Judgments,</hi> or in the <hi>way of his</hi> Mercies, Iſa. 26.8. Otherwiſe the <hi>Great Turk</hi> (who ('tis ſaid) is ſo allarm'd with thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies that he hath proclaimed a Faſt to be kept throughout all his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) will riſe up in Judgment againſt all Scoffers, as the Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> will againſt the Jews, <hi>Math.</hi> 12.42. The <hi>Heavens,</hi> thoſe Catholick Preachers: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 19.1. The ſpangled Curtains of the Bridegroomes Chamber, hath Read ſuch a Divinity-Lecture to us in <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Wonders,</hi> and ſo hath the <hi>Earth</hi> and the <hi>Sea,</hi> all terrifying and teſtifying Gods <hi>Anger</hi> againſt Mans Sin, yea in his own people, in whom he will pardon, but not patronize Evil: and ſhall we look on thoſe <hi>Signs of the times,</hi> to be <hi>Inania Terriculamenta,</hi> inſignificant Scar-crows, which the Sorcerers of <hi>Aegypt</hi> (were they here to ſee them) would acknowledge to be the <hi>Finger of God.</hi> As <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (that Slaughter-houſe) of Saints) had her <hi>Signs</hi> of Deſtruction. So <hi>Rome</hi> (the like Slaught<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-houſe) had (at the Riſe of <hi>Luther</hi>) ſuch a Storm upon her chief Church, as ſtruck the Keys out of <hi>Peters</hi> Hands, while the <hi>Pope</hi> was creating Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals in it: ever ſince a cold Sweat hath ſtuck upon all the Limbs of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,</hi> as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> (his great Champion) confeſſeth, aſſuredly the pouring out of the <hi>ſeaven Vials</hi> (mentioned <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.) will produce ſuch a prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Storm upon <hi>Rome,</hi> as will not only blow down her <hi>Keys,</hi> but her <hi>Images</hi> alſo, yea blow away all the Traſh and Trumpery of that Scarlet <hi>Whore,</hi> and the <hi>Whore</hi> her ſelf with all her proud helpers; all Chriſts Foes ſhall then be made his Foot-ſtool (the fitteſt place for them) in all Lands: yet before the accompliſhment hereof, ſad Calamities, (if not the <hi>Salaughter of the Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>) may be ſeen, yea ſuch <hi>Tribulation</hi> as hath not heretofore. <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.21. The very Time may ſeem nothing elſe but <hi>Affliction</hi> it ſelf. <hi>Mark</hi> 13.19. So befel it to the <hi>Jews</hi> that (had not God cut ſhort thoſe Days <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.22. <hi>No Fleſh had been Saved</hi>) no Jewiſh Fleſh had been left alive. What Woes may befal the <hi>Gentile World,</hi> after ſuch prodigious preſages, we know not. 'Tis good for us to get into <hi>Auguſtus's</hi> poſture, (who once ſitting 'twixt <hi>Virgil</hi> (a frequent ſigher) and <hi>Horace</hi> (that had watery Eyes) pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, he ſat <hi>inter Suſpiria &amp; Lachrymas,</hi> betwixt Sighs and Tears: ſure I am, Our Day calls upon us, not only to <hi>ſay ſo,</hi> but alſo to <hi>ſit ſo,</hi> with all <hi>ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs:</hi> Chriſts Council to the <hi>Jews</hi> was <hi>[pray ye]</hi> Matth. 24.20. 'Tis no leſs the Duty of us <hi>Gentiles, Prayer</hi> is the beſt Ordinance and Artillery, wherewith to Batter Heaven, <hi>Flecti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur Inatus Voce Rogante Deus:</hi> Wher God
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:64617:49"/>ſeems moſt bitterly bent, yet will he yield ſomething to prayer, which is the beſt lever at a dead lift, provided it be the <hi>Prayer of Faith,</hi> for as Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is the <hi>Mother,</hi> ſo the Churches <hi>Faith</hi> is the Midwife of Deliverance, Hereupon <hi>Joel</hi> in ſetting down the Dreadful Signs of direful Days (leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould deſpondingly ſay, as <hi>Mark</hi> 10.26. <hi>Who then can be ſaved</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth with this comfortable Corollary, <hi>whoever calleth on the Name of the Lord ſhall be ſaved.</hi> Joel 2.31.32. That ſuch may be Reſerved as a Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Royal Uſe being <hi>accounted</hi> worthy to eſcape thoſe things that may yet come to paſs: <hi>Luke</hi> 21.36. Is the Hearty prayer of <hi>C. N.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>The <hi>Reader</hi> is requeſted to correct theſe following Faults that have eſcaped the Preſs.</head>
            <head type="sub">Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 1. line 19. read <hi>Math.</hi> 12. p. 6. l. 14. r. <hi>Ear</hi> p. 11. read line 20. <hi>before</hi> line 19. p. 18. l. 25. for 80. r. to. p. 31. l. 16. for 18. r. 11. p. 37. l. 27. r. <hi>prognoſtick</hi> p. 40 d. 24. r. <hi>Truths.</hi> p. 48. l. 29. for <hi>through</hi> r. <hi>though.</hi> p. 49. l. 2. for <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celor</hi> r. <hi>Councel.</hi> p. 55. l. 16. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 57. l. <hi>the latter</hi> r. 65, 66, 67, <hi>&amp;c. to</hi> 71. <hi>in</hi> p. <hi>which ſhould be</hi> 96. l. 11. r. <hi>next Anſwer</hi> [as <hi>Meſſengers</hi> only, not as <hi>Mediators,</hi> according to the Popiſh Doctrine, and l. 22. after are r. moſtly: and l. 34. for <hi>Virgin</hi> r. <hi>Virgins.</hi> p. 69. l. 20. for <hi>Trimethius</hi> r. <hi>Trithemius.</hi> the Sheet <hi>(L.)</hi> ſhould begin with 73, and ſo on. p. 76. falſly paged 68.) l. 20. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:64617:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
